<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Towards Freedom</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/</id><updated>2016-07-08T00:00:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>P2P File &amp; URL Sharing App on LAN</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/working-on-p2p-file-url-sharing-app.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-07-08T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2016-07-08:blog/working-on-p2p-file-url-sharing-app.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the past 1 week, I have been working on a peer-to-peer File and URL sharing app and I have named it as &lt;strong&gt;Transceiver&lt;/strong&gt; (the ability to transmit and receive data). I would like to log the progress of what I have done so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are various reasons, why I am writing this application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to try and learn how to build cross platform Desktop applications using &lt;a href="http://electron.atom.io/"&gt;electron&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to write a p2p application, since I have been exploring p2p and mesh networking quite often.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Last thing, I needed this application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever I attend meetups and I wanted to share some URLs that I have bookmarked to others, we do this by using some service that runs on Internet. It could be IRC or any Instant Messengers. Sometimes we have even tried using Pidgin + Bonjour (Avahi for GNU/Linux) and that have worked well too. But we have never succeeded file transfer through Pidgin + Bonjour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following is a GIF of what have been done so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style="border: 1px solid black" src="images/transceiver.gif"&gt;&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First thing, it doesn't make sense to send URL links or Files or any data through Internet to a person who is sitting next to me or in the same hall, connected to the same network. The data doesn't need to leave the network in first place and also you don't need to expose to all those centralized services out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second thing, even in such a WLAN (or) LAN, there should be no central server / single point of failure. People should be able to form ad-hoc networks and should be able to communicate. In this sense, this application is serverless and peer-to-peer such that it doesn't need any central server (or) signalling server (like how they have in torrent trackers or webRTC peer connection) to connect to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third thing, it has to be a Free Software. There already exists few of them like D-LAN (Distributed File Sharing on LAN), Lan Messenger, etc., I am just stacking up mine to the list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.zeroconf.org/"&gt;Zeroconf&lt;/a&gt; (also known as Bonjour or Avahi in GNU/Linux) for automatically registering and discovering peers on the same network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://socket.io/"&gt;Socket.io&lt;/a&gt; for end to end socket connection. (I could still make use of socketio to upgrade the connection to webRTC).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electron + nodejs as a cross-platform framework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An instance of this application can act as both server and client at the same time, thus can listen for incoming data and also it can send data to other peers on the network. Since the peers are discovered through zerconf, their identities are exposed to everyone on the network using this app and thus we are able to eliminate central signalling server here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now the text / URL sharing is complete. I am yet to work on the File transfer part. I am releasing this work under Free Software license (GPL v3) and the source code is hosted on &lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/prashere/transceiver/"&gt;gitlab here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="code"></category><category term="free software"></category><category term="networks"></category><category term="tech"></category></entry><entry><title>Cross Compilation in Go</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/go-cross-compilation.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-06-24T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2016-06-24:blog/go-cross-compilation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I have started to explore the Go programming language or golang in short. Go is a compiled language which can produce standalone binaries for the go programs, which means the receiver of this binary need not have go compiler and the libraries that this program is dependent installed on their machine, instead they can just run the binary and the program will be executed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also the same case with C and C++. If you have used GCC (GNU Compiler Collection) then you could have come across something called cross-compilation in gcc. Compilation means converting from source code to binary, while cross compilation means producing binaries that can be used on other target architectures too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I am writing code in my laptop which is running Linux kernel and the cpu &amp;amp; operating system architectures are 64-bit (often represented as amd64 or x86_64). When I compile this source code on my laptop, I will get a binary. I can execute this binary and can also distribute. But the only constraint is this binary is build for 64bit architecture and linux based machines only. Therefore if someone who runs 32bit or ARM based architectures even with Linux kernel, they cannot use this binary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to overcome this, gcc allows developers to do cross compilation. Similarly go compiler also has this feature inbuilt. Here is how we do it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;env GOOS=linux GOARCH=arm go build somefile.go
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the above command, I am setting values for two environment variables GOOS and GOARCH respectively where GOOS is the name of the kernel used in target operating system and GOARCH is the name of the cpu architecture used in the target computer hardware. Succeeding that is the go command to build binary from the source code &lt;code&gt;somefile.go&lt;/code&gt;. It will take few seconds to build the binary, once that is done now the binary can be used to execute the program in the target machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To know the valid and available GOOS and GOARCH values that go accepts, &lt;a href="https://golang.org/doc/install/source#environment"&gt;go here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Producing binaries and distributing them is very good from users usability point of view. It will be convinient for users to just double click on something to see it work (in fact that's how most of them were training through Microsoft Windows). As a free software activist, I appeal that we should also consider the users freedom point of view and give them links to access the source code of the same program that they use in their computer in the binary. The users have the right to know what is being executed in their machines.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="tech"></category><category term="code"></category></entry><entry><title>Marx, Wikipedia &amp; Torrents</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/marx-wiki-torrents.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-06-17T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2016-06-17:blog/marx-wiki-torrents.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl_Marx"&gt;Karl Marx&lt;/a&gt; - 19th Century Philosopher, Economist, Sociologist, Journalist and an Revolutionary Socialist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; - An Internet encylopedia available in many languages built by people around the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BitTorrent"&gt;BitTorrent&lt;/a&gt; - A Peer-to-Peer file sharing protocol / program that is used by most of the people around the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why did I pick these three? What is so common about these three topics and how are these topics related to each other? For quite sometime, I was reading works based on Marx and was also reading materials that took a marxist approach on analysing the free software and other technologies. It is under this context, I am writing this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Marx &amp;amp; Engels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karl Marx is well known for his work on analysing and understanding &lt;strong&gt;Capitalism&lt;/strong&gt; and is also known for his famous work along with his comrade &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friedrich_Engels"&gt;Friedrich Engels&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1848/communist-manifesto/index.htm"&gt;The Communist Manifesto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. As a sociologist, economist and  philosophers they both had a vision to change the world. That vision echoed in their famous statement,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/From_each_according_to_his_ability,_to_each_according_to_his_needs"&gt;From each according to his ability, To each according to his needs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i.e the society they envisioned will revolve around this central theme where people can contribute something to the commons according to their ability or capacity and they can take back from the commons based on how much they need. Whenever people discuss about communism or socialism they miss this central theme and the discussion always gets diverted to the failure of U.S.S.R and other attempts of 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marx was also right about capitalism that, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"It will take science and technology to greater level in order to increase their productivity and it will do wonders". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And today we are seeing this live all around us and our next generations will continue to see more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now heading to Wikipedia. It is no doubt that Wikipedia has disrupted the knowledge sector, especially the Intellectual Property Rights and Copyrights of the encyclopedia industry. Today Wikipedia is one of the world's largest Digital Commons (i.e belongs to everyone) available and continues to grow into many more projects like Wiktionary, Wikibooks, Wikidata, etc., It is also well known fact that Wikipedia is built by people all around the world. We approach wikipedia whenever we wanted to lookup for something (search engines doesn't matter, all of them point to wikipedia) and if I know about something, I can also contribute back to Wikipedia by creating or editing an existing article. This is exactly the same vision of Marx and Engles, taking what is necessary and giving back based on the ability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Torrents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's focus on Torrents. People using torrents definitely would have encountered these words, "seeding" and "peers". When we download from a torrent file, we look for more peers. Peers are those people who already have these files in their computers. If those peers upload what they have in their computers to other people who wanted to download the same file through this torrent file, then we call this process as seeding and those peers who does seeding are termed as seeders. While we expect more peers during the download, we look for more seeders. Downloading what you need and seeding back what you can!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are just two examples. this is the same case with how a free software is also developed. Of course, one can point out and say "hey, the examples you have pointed out are immaterial things. what about material things?". Indeed they are right, Marx's works were based on 19th century capitalism and even with that he is able to pin-point a lot of things about capitalism beyond his age. We shouldn't miss to see the fact that today Capitalism is also riding on these immaterial stuff which in turn reflects on their material wealth. For mens (Marx &amp;amp; Engels) who have developed their framework based on &lt;a href="https://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/stalin/works/1938/09.htm"&gt;Dialectical Materialism&lt;/a&gt;, they wouldn't be stupid to deal with material stuffs either, for they did not leave any readymade blueprint, rather they left their vision to be carried by the actors of the corresponding age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether the society goes towards dystopia or utopia, we are all collectively responsible for it. So don't stay neutral, pick you side and act.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Internet"></category><category term="networks"></category><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Contradictory Microsoft</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/microsoft-contradiction.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-04-08T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2016-04-08:blog/microsoft-contradiction.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;At Pondicherry University, we (Computer Science Students) were invited to attend a lecture by someone from Microsoft. My anticipation was that someone is going to promote (or) show-case the products of Microsoft. If this is going to happen, I made sure I have to rip off the evilness of proprietary culture by raising questions from their End Users License Agreement itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were seated at an auditorium and waiting for the guest to arrive. In the meantime myself and Shaswata (free software activist from West Bengal) were discussing about which questions to fire from their licensing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally a male guest arrived and the professors introduced him to us as one of the youngest man to be at the director level of Microsoft India and gave the chance for him to address us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He shared his experience. To be frank, I felt like reading some self-help tips book, like how to be successful in your life, what is your carrier goal, etc., because he did speak about that. And my thought is, "Why the hell, use MICROSOFT label for this?". Ironically, while pointing out some examples, he used the name of Jack Ma, Steve Jobs and no where he mentioned Bill Gates nor Satya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seems he is from the Consultancy section and no surprise, he spoke about managerial skills. He spoke for about 20 to 25 minutes and gave a chance for us to question him. After some couple of people, I raised my questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Points follow after 'My take' is presented here, but I did not talk there, because more the argument, more people are going to hate and blame me for spoiling the event, after all our university professors want to impress him to bring Microsoft for campus recruitment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Question&lt;/strong&gt;: After Mr. Sathya Nadella took charge as the CEO, we are seeing a lot of FOSS integration into Microsoft,  What's preventing Microsoft from Open Sourcing their entire products?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;His Answer&lt;/strong&gt;: Because we make money out of selling it closed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My take: First of all, the assumption that open sourcing (or) releasing the source code under GPL cannot be used for making money is false. This shows their lack of understanding of the model itself. &lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/selling.en.html"&gt;Selling Free Software is Ok&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Business_models_for_open-source_software"&gt;Business models for FOSS&lt;/a&gt;. Most people have only heard of the terms Open Source software and assume they know everything about it and more incorrectly they equate &lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html"&gt;Free Software&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freeware"&gt;Freeware&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Question&lt;/strong&gt;: Do you think, selling the proprietary software (i.e binary only) is ethical because software code is not material? Let's assume for example, my friend wanted a software binary from me and there is nothing that prevents me from sharing it with him, but the label that we get is "Pirates". Should I share the binary file with my friend or should I risk losing their relationship abiding to the definition of Piracy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;His Answer&lt;/strong&gt;: See, there is no question of ethical or unethical. If someone does something that gradually becomes their livelihood, then people would continue doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My take: Right, I don't disagree about the fact that someone does something can gradually become their livelihood. Still my question is whether that 'something' they do is ethical or unethical. For example, the practice of stealing something from someone is what we call a theft. Theft is universally considered to be an unethical practice. Still someone can have a livelihood by stealing off. So he didn't answer my question, but just tried to beat around the bush. And for the second part regarding piracy, he ignored it. I did not get a answer from that context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://p2pfoundation.net/Why_All_Knowledge_Should_Be_Free"&gt;Proprietary software has been considered to be an unethical practice&lt;/a&gt; by a lot of people at FOSS community. Microsoft today is facing a self-contradictory situation where they support and oppose the practice of FOSS at the same time. Pity!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Question&lt;/strong&gt;: When you spoke to us initially, you said that, everyone should be driven by Curiosity. Now as a Computer Science students, if we had curiosity to look at the source code of windows operating and learn from it and at the same time improve the algorithms, the End Users License Agreement of Windows doesn't allow us to do. Your license puts restrictions on, "Reverse engineering, decompilation or working around technical restrictions". While these restrictions are in effect, how are your products useful for computer science engineers which very well kills these curiosities?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;His Answer&lt;/strong&gt;: See you cannot label that as curiosity. For example, take this wooden work (he pointed at the podium where he stood nearby), you may not be interested in how it was made, but you may be interested with how you can have creative ways of putting this to use. That's how you should see it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My take: I had to laugh myself. He defines what curiosity other people should have. How can someone decide for someone else what they should be curious about? A user can anytime become a developer, provided he had access to the knowledge and tools. Limiting what a user should think or do is nothing but controlling the thoughts of the users itself. I clearly mentioned him that I am posting this question from academics point of view and he gives an explanation from a naive end-users point of view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Immediate Statement&lt;/strong&gt;: I think, in this context an operating system like Linux and the community behind it is more open and democratic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;His Reply&lt;/strong&gt;: Well, there is no doubt about it. Linux is!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Statement&lt;/strong&gt;: Thanks for acknowledging that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally arrived at what I was looking for. In a crowd of around some 60+ people getting this statement from someone at director level of Microsoft, Mission Accomplished!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When FOSS pitches a new mode of production, distribution and consumption inclusive of all, the traditional monopoly giants doesn't want to change and thinks from the same old system. No surprise, why google surpassed microsoft through their Open Source Android Project. This is not to assume Google is not evil. The "Do No Evil" is evil as well. This post is just dedicated to MS.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="blog"></category><category term="proprietary"></category><category term="microsoft"></category></entry><entry><title>Learning Basics of Radio Physics for Meshnet</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/learning-basics-radio-physics-meshnet.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-02-12T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2016-02-12:blog/learning-basics-radio-physics-meshnet.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I don't exactly remember when &amp;amp; by whom I first came across the idea of meshnet, but I do remember the video that inspired me to work towards meshnet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/1tEkyLOh-tY?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From then on, I started to explore more and more links on the web about meshnet and this is how I aggregated the list of various resources, community knowledge base &amp;amp; community meshnet projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of these resources, I consider a book named &lt;a href="http://wndw.net/" target="_blank"&gt;WNDW - Wireless Network in Developing World&lt;/a&gt; to be one of the most important resource. The reason I consider it to be important is because this book is a practical guide to build a wireless network written by field experts covering every basics including radio physics, telecommunication basics, antennnas, networking, installation &amp;amp; maintenance. The digital copy of this book is available under &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/" target="_blank"&gt;CC-BY-SA&lt;/a&gt; and you can download the &lt;a href="http://wndw.net/book.html" target="_blank"&gt;free digital copy&lt;/a&gt; of this book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am finding this book extremely useful and have started learning Radio Physics since the meshnet that we are trying to build is a wireless meshnetwork using 802.11 (Wifi). WiFi signals are electromagnetic radiations (EMR) also known as Radio Signals that operate at 2.4GHz and 5GHz frequency (license exempt bands).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting up meshnet involves setting up wireless nodes, antennas that propogates the signals and in order to do that we need to understand the basics of radio physics not just computer applications &amp;amp; protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any node or host machine has to satisfy certain requirements in order to be able to join a network. These requirements are labelled traditionally as layers like in OSI Layering &amp;amp; TCP/IP Layering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter what layering model, the Physical layer forms the foundation which denotes the signal carrier &amp;amp; the medium of transmission. It is this physical layer that deals mostly with the property of radio physics namely frequency, bandwidth, wavelength, phases, etc., If we proceed without understanding these basics we might end up with a poor network infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="web"></category><category term="meshnet"></category><category term="radio physics"></category></entry><entry><title>The Internet As We Know</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/the-internet-as-we-know.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-02-02T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2016-02-02:blog/the-internet-as-we-know.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Links for community initiatives, projects, discussion, articles on meshnet are listed at the end of this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internet (இணையம்) as you know is defined as "network of networks". These networks are setup by users and communities. But inter-connecting these networks across street, cities, state, countries and the world are done by corporations. The corporation could be either a public corporation (driven by Government like BSNL in India) or private corporation (driven by private interests for profit, like Airtel, Reliance, Tata, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corporations who inter-connect these simple networks to global network are called Internet Service Providers (ISPs). There are also small scale ISPs who depend on the large corporations for lines and cover only smaller area (for example ACT in Bangalore &amp;amp; Chennai).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of creating a network is to communicate. This communication could be anything from  simple text message, real time chats, VOIP calls, sharing pictures, videos (or) any digital content. So if I have a network in my place and you have a network in your place, it is based on our interests to decide what to share between ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with the Internet starts here. I have understood 3 major flaws with the current network,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Censorship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mass Surveillance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Violation of Net Neutrality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem 1 (Censorship)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I already pointed out above, "it is based on our interests to decide what to share between ourselves" in a network. Since the ISPs are inter-connecting the networks, they automatically gain a power to decide whether to allow data from one network to reach the other network or not. If I send you anything and you are not able to receive only from me or some specific person, there is a lot of possibility that either the ISP that you are connected to or the ISP that I am connected to is censoring communication, thus preventing us from communicating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not just that, if you are not able to access any website which you have previously visited and you still know it is accessible from other parts of the world, then you can be very sure that your ISP is censoring you from accessing that website (or) content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When ISPs can do censorship, how does this statement of "it is based on our interests to decide what to share between ourselves" is true anymore?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This problem can be overcome by using tunnels like VPN, TOR, I2P, Psiphon, etc., But this doesn't remove the porblem. These are just an workaround. The problems still exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem 2 (Mass Surveillance)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we already have censorship, it's very clear that ISPs can also inspect or read what we are sending to others &amp;amp; the vice-versa (they can also read what we receive). We think our communications are happening only between ourselves, but since ISPs are in the middle of you and me, it means whatever we send &amp;amp; receive is also visible to the ISPs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If ISPs can listen and continuously monitor our communications they can also store it permanently in their servers. This is also true with proprietary web platforms like Facebook, Google, Amazon, etc., This is violation of an user's privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Privacy means whoever owns the data should decide when, where and to whom they should reveal that data (i.e the control is with the user). If ISPs (or) the proprietary platform can gain access to these data which you are actually sending it to your friend or relatives this is what we call surveillance. Instead of targeting suspicious users, if everyone are targetted then we call it as mass surveillance and this is a potential threat to Democrarcy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine a country or a world where everything you do, wherever you go, whoever you meet is monitored or surveilled, would you be the same? Won't the sense of someone monitoring affect your thought process? or how you do things? Is that really you? Are we trying to build a society based on fear instead of mutual consent? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There goes a famous dialogue from the movie &lt;strong&gt;V for Vendetta&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People should not be afraid of their governments. Governments should be afraid of their people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By monitoring (or) surveilling the institutions are enforcing obedience into our minds. Most of us won't even bother to point out the mistakes of institutions, there would be no freedom of speech. Everything will boil down to self-censorship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, like the previous case we can overcome this by protecting our online communications with the use of mathematics &amp;amp; encryption. The problem with the current Internet is that encryption &amp;amp; decryption are not embedded into the design, rather they have become the burden for the users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem 3 (Violation of Net Neutrality)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have seen this a lot in our country. We have seen how Facebook along with Reliance &amp;amp; Airtel  tried to build a walled garden in the name of Free basics (Internet.org) &amp;amp; Airtel Zero. The strategy they followed is termed as differential pricing / zero rating (i.e charging differently for different services like messenger, VOIP, etc., (or) allowing only certain sites registered with them for free). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most important thing to note here is how these mega-corporations tried to manipulate and mislead the people through their platforms. In fact, TRAI (Telecom Regulatory Authority of India) has condemned their act as "Platform Abuse".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above 3 problems are fair enough to destroy the democratic nature and therefore curtain the freedom of the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have identified the problems with the Internet, we need to think about solving these problems and to come up with a network design which will not have these problems in first place. People around the world are already into the research of designing such networks. It's called Mesh Networks. There are various communities online, especially the &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/darknetplan"&gt;darknetplan&lt;/a&gt; subreddit on reddit.com, the &lt;a href="http://hyperboria.net/"&gt;hyperboria&lt;/a&gt; community and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Articles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.wired.com/2014/01/its-time-to-take-mesh-networks-seriously-and-not-just-for-the-reasons-you-think/"&gt;It's time to take mesh networks seriously - Wired.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg21929294.500-meshnet-activists-rebuilding-the-internet-from-scratch"&gt;Meshnet activists rebuilding the Internet from Scratch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussions &amp;amp; Resources&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://discuss.fsftn.org/t/is-internets-centralized-architecture-a-problem/133"&gt;Problems with the Centralized Architecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://discuss.fsftn.org/category/engineering-programming/project-meshnet"&gt;FSFTN Discussion Forum on Meshnet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="discuss.fsftn.org/t/free-the-network-hackers-take-back-the-web/557/"&gt;Free The Network - Documentary on Meshnet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://p2pfoundation.net/Mesh_Networks"&gt;Introduction to meshnet - p2pfoundation.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wirelessafrica.meraka.org.za/wiki/index.php/DIY_Mesh_Guide"&gt;Mesh Guide - Wireless Africa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wndw.net/"&gt;Wireless Networking in the developing world&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://reddit.com/r/darknetplan"&gt;Darknetplan - Mesh community on Reddit.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community Initiatives &amp;amp; Projects&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://thefnf.org/"&gt;The Free Network Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://guifi.net"&gt;Guifi.net - Largest mesh network operating from Spain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://freifunk.net/en/"&gt;Freifunk - free radio networks group operating from Germany&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://project-byzantium.org"&gt;Project Byzantium - A live GNU/Linux distribution to create Ad-hoc mesh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://openwrt.org/"&gt;OpenWRT - Linux distribution for embedded devices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.dd-wrt.com/site/index"&gt;DDWRT - Fork of OpenWRT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://librecmc.org/librecmc/home"&gt;LibreCMC - Libre Embedded GNU/Linux distribution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://disruptedsystems.org"&gt;Rumble - Off the grid, Delay Tolerant Networking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://commotionwireless.net/"&gt;Commotion Wireless Mesh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://metamesh.org"&gt;Metamesh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://seattlemesh.net/"&gt;Seattle Meshnet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nycmesh.net/"&gt;NewYork Meshnet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="portlandmeshnet.org"&gt;Portland Meshnet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><category term="networks"></category><category term="Internet"></category><category term="meshnet"></category></entry><entry><title>Do You Have A URL?</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/revolt-against-free-basics.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-19T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2015-12-19:blog/revolt-against-free-basics.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;1. Do I have a (web)site / blog?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, I do. You are reading it and also I have some other blogs too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. Can you access it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answer 1: &lt;strong&gt;Yes&lt;/strong&gt;, if you are connected to the global network called Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answer 2: &lt;strong&gt;No&lt;/strong&gt;, if you are trying to access from Free Basics by Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. Why is my blog / site not accessible through Free Basics?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becuase to make my site / blog accessible through Free Basics, I need to register my site URL to them (Facebook).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. Why did I not add my URL to Facebook? Is it a paid service?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, it's not a paid service. Even though it's free to register my URL, I am not going to add there. &lt;strong&gt;Why should I add my site to them, when my URL is already on the Internet? There is only one Internet. Free Basics !== Internet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook is trying to take over the control of the global network in their hands and establish their empire in it. This is nothing short of Monopoly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Internet is always Free (Free as in Freedom) and Facebook is trying to put a chain on those free hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand the context better, there are two ways of Censoring in Internet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blacklisting - list of sites not to allow (blocked sites).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whitelisting - list of allowed sites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Free Basics is a WHITELIST CENSORSHIP&lt;/strong&gt; which divides / breaks the Internet into fragments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5. What do we need to do now?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revolt against Freebasics&lt;/strong&gt;! If you have a (WEB)site or blog take a Stand. Do not add your Website / Web-blog / Web Application / Web Service to Free Basics List.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Let us Stand for Internet Freedom.&lt;/h3&gt;</summary><category term="Internet"></category><category term="networks"></category><category term="censorship"></category></entry><entry><title>Students Practice Free Software. Yet, They Do Not Know</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/looking-for-free-software-yet.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-11-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2015-11-25:blog/looking-for-free-software-yet.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I started writing this post soon after I came out of the computer lab completing my lab internal exam. We are given 10 exercise to complete during our semseter lab sessions out of which a random of 2 exercise are given for this internal exam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title of these 10 exercises are given to us from our seniors and they also shared their code to us through email. Most of these code are downloaded from the Internet &amp;amp; are written in Java.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am someone who hates the verboseness of Java. Anyway I attempted to compile and execute those codes to see what output does the code produce. There were bugs, typos in the code. I debugged &amp;amp; compiled them successfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While discussing with my class peers, they said me they were not able to compile successfully for same reasons. Then I shared them the revised code with bugs and typos fixed. They used it to compile and got the lab record completed. I had the same experience during my under-graduate course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless I implemented some of the programs in python for my convinience and also gave the same for those who were looking for much simpler and non-verbose code. Another friend of mine in my class named &lt;code&gt;Dipankar&lt;/code&gt; also tried implementing the algorithms in the languages that he preferred. We both shared our code to our peers and asked them to pick the one they feel better (No, we both were not in a competition. Instead we co-operated with each other).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think, this is nothing short of the Free Software practice except the fact that the code are not licensed and might fall under public domain. The majority of student community today, when given a lab programming exercise to complete, searches for existing code online to reuse and to study the code. They are using it for their own purpose and some even modify the program to fit their requirements. Now this new version of code will be shared with the next batch of students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/"&gt;Free Software says&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the reciever, of the program code, can run the program for any purpose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the reciever, of the program code, can study the program to know how it works.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the receiver, of the program code, can redistribute the copies of the code to anyone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the receiver, of the program code, can improve / modify the code and share it with anyone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above practice by the student community is in par with what Free Software says. Yet, the student community is unaware of this philosophy and are failing to utilise it to study and improve. They fail to understand that this is the only potential source of knowledge for them. This free flow of knowledge is a gift for them by their predecessors. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of rewriting everything from scratch they can reuse them. When they attempt to study the code while reusing them, they can improve them. During this process they might get different ideas that could take their thinking (or) understanding to a new level which might even kindle them, to pursue researches (or) question the current practice of proprietary software development. By this they can set an example for their successors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope the student community will think about it and take this philosophy seriously for the betterment of it's own existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After having some discussion with my peers who are inspired by Free Software, we decided to setup a git repository of these codes and add Free Software Licenses to them and share it with everyone (I will update the post, when the git repository is ready).&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="free software"></category><category term="education"></category></entry><entry><title>புத்தக வாசிப்பு</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/book-reading.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-10-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2015-10-25:blog/book-reading.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;மூன்று வருடங்களுக்கு முன்னால் என்னுடைய வாழ்க்கை என்பது இன்றைய பெரும்பாலான இளைஞர்களின் வாழ்க்கையாகவே இருந்தது. கையில் ஒன்றும், காதில் இரண்டும், மேஜையில் ஒன்றுமாய் ஸ்மார்ட்ஃபோன், மடிக்கணினி என்று அதிலேயே மூழ்கிக் கிடந்தேன். நான் சுயமாகச் சிந்தித்து ஏற்றுக் கொண்ட கருத்து என்று எப்போதுமே இருந்ததில்லை. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;காரணம், சமூக வலைதளங்களில் முகம் தெரியாத, தெரிந்த நபர்கள் என்ன பகிர்கிறார்களோ அதுவே பெரும்பான்மை கருத்தாக மாறி மாறிப் பலரைப் போல் என் மூளைக்குள்ளும் புகுந்துவிடும். அதை என் நட்பு வட்டங்களுக்கும் பகிர்ந்துவிடுவேன். அதைப் பற்றி ஒன்றுமே தெரியவில்லை என்றாலும் (அது உண்மையா பொய்யா என்று தெரியாமலும்) படித்த நேரத்தில் பிடித்திருப்பது போல் தோன்றினால் பகிர்ந்துவிடுவேன்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ஒருவர் ஒரு கருத்தைச் சரி என்பார், மற்றொருவர் தவறென்பார். சரி என்று சொன்னவரின் கருத்தைப் படித்தால் சரியாகத்தானே இருக்கிறது என்றும், தவறென்று சொல்பவரின் கருத்தைப் படித்தால் முன்னவர் சொன்னது தவறு என்பது போல் தோன்றும். யார் சொல்வது சரி, யார் சொல்வது தவறு என்று பகுப்பாய்வு செய்யும் திறனைச் சமூக வலைதளங்கள் வளர்க்கவில்லை. மாறாகத் தொடர்ந்து அடுத்தடுத்த கருத்துக்களையும், செய்திகளையும் நம் கண்முன்னே ஓடவிட்டுக் கொண்டே இருக்கும். &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;தன்னை சுற்றி நடக்கும் எந்த ஒரு விஷயத்தையும் 140 எழுத்துக்களில் சுருக்கிட விரும்புகிறான் (&lt;code&gt;திருக்குறள் 2 அடிதான் ஆனால் அதன் அர்த்தம் எவ்வுளவு பெரியது என்று நீங்கள் நினைக்கலாம். உண்மைதான். அதன் பெரிய அர்த்தத்தை நாம் புரிந்துக்கொண்டால் தானே அந்தச் சிறிய 2 அடியின் முக்கியத்துவம் நமக்குத் தெரியும்!&lt;/code&gt;).  இதன் விளைவு, ஒரு குழப்பமான மனிதன் உருவாக்கப்படுகிறான், யாரையும், எதன் மீதும் ஒரு நம்பிக்கை இல்லாமல் போகிறான். &lt;a href="https://ipfs.io/ipfs/QmWhpJ9Ptdsgapzh4gwiDnb5bN8mFDrtJ6TjTVgdZ64TSF"&gt;கேள்விகளை கேட்காமல் தகவல்களை கடந்து செல்லும் தகவல் நுகர்வு வெறி கலாச்சாரத்திற்கு அடிமையாகிறான்&lt;/a&gt;. சமூக வலைதளங்கள்மூலம் 1000 நண்பர்களோடு சோஷியலைஸ் (Socialize), அதாவது சமூகத்துடன் தொடர்பு வைத்திருப்பதாக ஒரு மாயையில் சிக்கி, தன்னைச் சுற்றியுள்ள உண்மையான சமூகத்திலிருந்து அறுத்தெரியப்படுகிறான்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;தன்னைச் சுற்றி வறுமையும், வேலைவாய்பின்மையும், சாதி, மதம் பெயரால் சமூக அநீதிகளும், சுரண்டல்களும், பாலின சமத்துவமின்மை, கடும் விலைவாசி உயர்வு என்று பல்வேறு அநீதிகள் நடந்துக் கொண்டிருக்கையில், &lt;code&gt;மதம் ஒரு அபின் (போதை) போன்றது&lt;/code&gt; என்று தத்துவஞாநி &lt;a href="https://ta.wikipedia.org/wiki/காரல்_மார்க்சு"&gt;கார்ல் மார்க்ஸ்&lt;/a&gt; அன்று சொன்னது போல இளைஞர்கள் மத்தியில் சமூக வலைத்தளங்கள் இன்றைய அபினாக மாறியிருக்கிறதோ என்று தோன்றுகிறது! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;இது போதாதென்று கமெர்ஷியல் சினிமா, ரியாலிட்டி ஷோ என்று தொலைக்காட்சிகளும் அதன் பங்கிற்கு மக்களை மிகவேகமாகத் திசைத்திருப்புகிறது. &lt;strong&gt;விளைவு?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code&gt;சிந்தனை என்பது மேலிருந்து கீழே மக்கள் மனதில் விதைக்கப்படுகிறது. எளிமையாகச் சொல்லவேண்டுமானால் நாம் அனைவரும் பொம்மாலாட்டத்தில் ஆடும் பொம்மைகள் ஆகிறோம்.&lt;/code&gt; சரி யார் மேலிருந்து மக்கள் மனதில் இவற்றை விதைக்கிறார்கள்? இது போன்ற கேள்விகளைக் கேட்காமல் இருப்பதற்காகத்தானே இவ்வுளவு திசைத் திருப்பலும்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;நானும் இவற்றிற்கான பதிலைத்தான் தேடிக் கொண்டிருக்கிறேன். முயற்சியில் முன்னேற்றமும் அடைந்திருக்கிறேன். காரணம், புத்தக வாசிப்பு. புத்தக வாசிப்பு என்றதும் குங்குமம், குமுதம், ஆனந்த விடகன் என்று நினைத்துவிட வேண்டாம். வேண்டுமானால் பொழுது போக்க இப்புத்தகங்களைப் படிக்கலாம். ஆனால் சமூகத்தின் மீதும், என்னச் சுற்றி நடக்கும் காரியங்கள் ஏன் நடக்கிறது, யாரால் நடத்தப்படுகிறது, எப்படி நடக்கிறது என்ற காரண காரணிகளைப் புரிந்துக் கொள்ள உதவியது புத்தகங்கள் தான். &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;முதலில் நாம் வாழும் சமூகத்தைப் புரிந்துக் கொண்டால் தான் நாம் அடுத்த செயல்களைத் திட்டமிட முடியும். அப்படி புரியாத காரணத்தால் தான், உதாரணத்திற்கு, வேலை கிடைக்கவில்லை என்றால் தனக்கு மட்டும் இந்த உலகம் இருண்டுவிட்டது போல் உணர்வதும், எதிர்காலத்தை நினைத்து ஒருவித கலக்கமும் பயமும் பற்றிக் கொள்கிறது. காரணம் தெரிந்துவிட்டால் தீர்வுகளை நோக்கிய அடியைத் தைரியமாக வைக்கலாம் அல்லவா! உலகின் வேறொரு பகுதியில் நடக்கும் ஒரு காரியத்திற்கும், நம் ஊரில் நடக்கும் ஒரு காரியத்திற்கும் தொடர்பில்லாதது போன்றும், அதனால் நமக்கு எந்தப் பாதிப்பும் இல்லை என்பது போன்றும் தோன்றலாம், ஆனால் எதார்த்தம் வேறு, நாம் ஒரு சங்கிலித் தொடராகச் செயல்பட்டுக் கொண்டிருக்கிறோம் என்பதே உண்மை. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;உதாரணத்திற்கு,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;சவுதியில் கச்சா எண்ணெய் விலை குறைந்தாலோ ஏறினாலோ நம் ஊரிலும் அதற்கேற்றாற் போல் மாறுதல் நிகழ்கிறதே! ஏன்?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;இந்தியாவின் முதுகெலும்பே விவசாயம் தான் என்று பாடத்தில் படித்தாலும், விவசாயிகள் ஏன் அதிக அளவில் தற்கொலை செய்துக் கொள்கிறார்கள் அல்லது நிலங்களை ரியல் எஸ்டேட் காரர்களிடம் விற்று விடுகிறார்கள்?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;முதலில் நாம் எதிர் கேள்விகளைக் கேட்கும் மனிதர்களாக மாற வேண்டும். அவற்றிற்கான பதில்களைத் தேட வேண்டும். அந்தத் தேடுதலில் தான், மக்கள் அனைவரும் busy-ஆகிப் போன இந்தக் காலத்தில் புத்தகம் நம்மிடம் நிறைய பேசும். அதுவும் காலம் நேரம் பார்க்காமல் தொடர்ந்து பேசிக் கொண்டே இருக்கும். நான் வாசித்த, வாசித்துக் கொண்டிருக்கும் புத்தகங்களைப் பற்றி, எனக்குப் பல காரணங்களை விளங்க வைத்த புத்தகங்களைப் பற்றியும் அதே நேரத்தில் எனக்குப் புத்தகம் வாசிக்கும் பழக்கதை கற்றுக் கொடுத்த தோழர்களைப் பற்றியும் எழுதி உங்களோடு பகிர்வது என்று முடிவு செய்துள்ளேன்.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="books"></category></entry><entry><title>Uncensored - Circumventing Censorship</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/uncensored.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-10-12T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2015-10-12:blog/uncensored.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's been 2 months since I have enrolled myself for the post graduate course in Networks &amp;amp; Internet Engineering (NIE) at Pondicherry University. The campus is a beautiful place to be and has rich bio-diversity preserved inside. It is also a Wi-Fi enabled campus scaling to various schools from engineering to management, Life Sciences to Performing Arts, Social Sciences to Medical Sciences, etc.,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I belong to Department of Computer Science which comes under School of Engineering &amp;amp; Technology and the funny part is our department receives very poor Wi-Fi signal at class rooms, sometimes not even that. As a student of NIE, I feel the classroom is powerless without even access to wireless networks (at times, we do form ad-hoc networks).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Problem (Status Quo)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, let's focus on the censorship part from here on. Even if one can get a strong wi-fi signal or access to the wired network, not all the websites over the internet are accessible through the network. Social networks like Facebook, Video streaming platforms like Youtube, etc., are blocked in a temporal manner (i.e these sites cannot be accessed during class hours). The problem here is, not everyone have uniform class hours. So if one set of people are inside classrooms, some other set of people at some other department will be idle and they won't be able to access websites that are blocked. These rules are applicable even on weekends when the university is not functioning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also other issues like,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;torrent downloads are blocked.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;downloading files more than a specific size are blocked (for eg, when the free software users group were preparing to organize a GNU/Linux installation fest inside the campus and we wanted to download the latest / stable iso images of distributions like Ubuntu, Fedora, Trisquel, Mint, etc., we were not allowed to download since the file size were large).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a GNU/Linux user could not use the package management tools like &lt;strong&gt;apt-get&lt;/strong&gt; (or) &lt;strong&gt;dnf&lt;/strong&gt; to update or download tools from the distributions repository which is really irritating, since this is the most preferred way of installing a package (or) software in gnu/linux distributions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Solution (Moving Forward)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With technology, there are always ways to circumvent blockades. I would like to remind you incidents like &lt;a href="http://mashable.com/2011/01/27/bypass-twitter-facebook-block-egypt/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.wired.com/2014/10/firechat-hong-kong-usage/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. Using web proxy seems to be a easy option for most of them to access sites that are blocked. But proxy sites will soon hit it's limitations, in our scenario described above, using web proxy one cannot download large files, web proxy sites has no connection with respect to torrent downloads &amp;amp; solving apt-get or package download problem. Also if certain sites are blocked in the country that the web proxy site is located, then that would be the dead end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our university uses a proxy server that sits in between the local networks (i.e the campus network) and the rest of the Internet and this proxy server is powered by a software named &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.squid-cache.org/"&gt;squid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; which is a &lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html"&gt;free software&lt;/a&gt;. Every request made from a computer connected to a university network will have to pass or go through the proxy server. The proxy server would inspect the packets header and match it against with the rules written to allow / drop the packets by the network administrator. They could write complex rules combining multiple parameters like the url pattern, response size &amp;amp; type, etc.,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like everyone else in the campus, I was also confronted with these problems, so I decided to share what works for me, so that you people could use it to circumvent it, especially gnu/linux users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have seen most of the people inside the campus are using an application in their android phones called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://psiphon.ca/"&gt;Psiphon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; which also is a free software. But Psiphon is limited to only Android and Windows currently and so other platforms are left out especially gnu/linux users. Since Psiphon is free software, we can attempt to build our own client for the platforms that are left out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://torproject.org"&gt;Tor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; network to bypass the censorship. Tor is a &lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html"&gt;free software&lt;/a&gt; project aimed to provide anonymity for users, journalists, activists, etc., around the world and also used to bypass the censorship. This &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JWII85UlzKw"&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; will better explain the idea behind tor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Psiphon and Tor's objective are completely different. Psiphon's objective is to &lt;code&gt;bypass censorhip&lt;/code&gt; while Tor's objective is to provide &lt;code&gt;anonymity&lt;/code&gt; and the fact that tor can also bypass censorship is just a &lt;strong&gt;side-effect of it's network architecture&lt;/strong&gt;. So with tor one can stay anonymous while circumventing censorship too. Moreover Tor is cross-platform. It has clients for GNU/Linux, Windows, Mac &amp;amp; Android. Tor also has got a &lt;code&gt;Tor browser&lt;/code&gt; for desktops which is a fork of Firefox browser and tweaked to be compatible for Tor and released.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am using Fedora 22 in my laptop and I have installed Tor daemon and have configured my existing firefox browers to use socks proxy. To install Tor in gnu/linux distributions we need access to uncensored internet at the first place, since apt-get (or) dnf yum won't be able to download through the censored network here. So if you visit your friends house with Internet access (or) if you have other means of connecting to internet like mobile data, you can use that to install tor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instructions to,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;install Tor in &lt;a href="https://www.torproject.org/docs/rpms.html.en"&gt;Fedora / CentOS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;install Tor in &lt;a href="https://www.torproject.org/docs/debian.html.en"&gt;Debian / Ubuntu / LinuxMint&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have installed tor successfully, also install another tool named &lt;code&gt;proxychains&lt;/code&gt; (usage is explained below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instructions to install proxychains,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fedora:&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sudo dnf -C install proxychains&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;debian / ubuntu / mint:&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sudo apt-get install proxychains&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow these instructions to set it up and start tor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;search for &lt;code&gt;terminal&lt;/code&gt; in applications and open it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if your network is behind a proxy server, we need to enter the proxy location in torrc file. In our university we are sitting behind a squid proxy server and the location is &lt;code&gt;http://10.10.80.11:3128&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;https://10.10.80.11:3128&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;copy both (http and https) url and enter the following in terminal which will open the torrc file in nano text editor&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sudo nano /etc/tor/torrc&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;scroll down to the end of the file and type the following&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HTTPProxy 10.10.80.11:3128&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HTTPSProxy 10.10.80.11:3128&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;press &lt;code&gt;ctrl+x&lt;/code&gt; then &lt;code&gt;Y&lt;/code&gt; and press &lt;code&gt;Enter&lt;/code&gt; to save and quit. The edited file should look like the image below&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://ipfs.io/ipfs/QmYdULp2HnNir4d9EUnr2pcQYLAiinZEdRKN4VTDn3RLJe"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have successfully configured &lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt; to use the network proxy, let's start using tor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt; will be started automatically in the background for ubuntu / debian / mint. Let's stop it first through terminal.&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sudo service tor stop&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now let's start the &lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt; again. This is a common step for both fedora and debian based distributions.&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tor&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should be seeing some outputs in number of lines like Bootstrapped 0% (refer the image below). When tor reaches &lt;code&gt;Bootstrapped 100%: done&lt;/code&gt; it means our computer can now participate in the tor network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt; is pre-configured to run on port 9050 in your computer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://ipfs.io/ipfs/QmcJf5qhgDf9DMHU7N4qhJ5vYPyxum6AHKc5YWyiDrcqsD"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: The reason why stopped and started tor is that, by default tor will be running in the background if started automatically, when we invoke &lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt; via command line manually, we will be able to see the logs and can check if tor is successfully establishing the connection or struck somewhere so that we can try to debug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just leave the terminal open with tor running and let's open &lt;code&gt;firefox&lt;/code&gt; browser to use tor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in firefox, go to &lt;code&gt;Edit&lt;/code&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;preferences&lt;/code&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;Advanced&lt;/code&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;Network&lt;/code&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;Settings&lt;/code&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;Manual Proxy configuration&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;find &lt;code&gt;SOCKS Host&lt;/code&gt; and enter &lt;code&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt; in the first field and &lt;code&gt;9050&lt;/code&gt; in the port field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;click on &lt;code&gt;ok&lt;/code&gt; and now you should be able to visit websites that are blocked previously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website censorship is solved, now let's focus on package manager. Remember we installed &lt;code&gt;proxychains&lt;/code&gt;? This is where we will make use of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open &lt;code&gt;/etc/proxychains.conf&lt;/code&gt; file using &lt;code&gt;nano&lt;/code&gt; editor like how we opened the &lt;code&gt;/etc/tor/torrc&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;scroll down to the end of the file and you could find &lt;code&gt;#socks4 127.0.0.1 9050&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if there is a &lt;code&gt;#&lt;/code&gt; like above, just delete that character alone, save and quit the editor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt; running in the background, now if we invoke any program from the &lt;code&gt;terminal&lt;/code&gt; using &lt;code&gt;proxychains&lt;/code&gt; we can make that program to redirect the traffic through &lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt;. For example,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sudo proxychains apt-get install uget&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;will install uget download manager and install it in your debian based machines. I hope you got the key point here. If you want to redirect any application to use tor, you will have to set &lt;code&gt;SOCKS proxy&lt;/code&gt; for the application. the proxy address would be &lt;code&gt;localhost:9050&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;127.0.0.1:3128&lt;/code&gt; where &lt;code&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;127.0.0.1&lt;/code&gt; is the address and &lt;code&gt;3128&lt;/code&gt; is the port number. For applications which doesn't support SOCKS proxy yet, you can use &lt;code&gt;proxychains&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also you can use &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://ugetdm.com/"&gt;uGet Download Manager&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to download files (uget has support for SOCKS proxy, so remember to start tor and set socks 4 proxy in uget preferences before starting your download).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above chain of solutions solves the following problems that I already mentoned above:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bypassing website censorship.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;downloading and installing software (or) package management in gnu/linux distributions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;downloading large files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only problem that relies unanswered is &lt;code&gt;torrent downloads&lt;/code&gt;. Using &lt;code&gt;torrent&lt;/code&gt; downloads via &lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt; traffic is a &lt;a href="https://blog.torproject.org/blog/bittorrent-over-tor-isnt-good-idea"&gt;bad idea&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Endnote&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the State exists there can be no freedom; when there is freedom there will be no State - V.I. Lenin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right from the beginning we have been encountering names of software like &lt;code&gt;squid&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;psiphon&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;proxychains&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;uget&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;fedora&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;debian&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;ubuntu&lt;/code&gt;, etc., all of them are &lt;strong&gt;Free Software&lt;/strong&gt;. Amidst the fact that &lt;code&gt;free software&lt;/code&gt; stresses the freedom of user, it doesn't completely libreate or free the masses from oppression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we are seeing two classes of people, one is the &lt;code&gt;oppressing&lt;/code&gt; class and the other is the &lt;code&gt;oppressed&lt;/code&gt; class both are using Free Software for their purposes. In our case &lt;code&gt;squid&lt;/code&gt;, a free softwrae is used to enforce censorship and &lt;code&gt;psiphon&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;proxychains&lt;/code&gt;, etc., which are free softwrae too, are used to fight back. But not everyone are liberated. &lt;code&gt;You and I&lt;/code&gt; can be exceptions, but exceptions cannot become mainstream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Science &amp;amp; Technology&lt;/strong&gt; can be used as tools and catalyst while fighting for freedom, but they alone cannot bring about freedom or revolution. We also need to be &lt;strong&gt;politically aware&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="tor"></category><category term="tech"></category><category term="free software"></category><category term="proxy"></category><category term="internet"></category><category term="web"></category><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Hello World</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/hello-world.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-10-11T23:55:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2015-10-11:blog/hello-world.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello World! Welcome to my blog. I previously owned a domain named "impras.in" and had written my own &lt;a href="https://github.com/PrasannaVenkadesh/blogster"&gt;blog engine&lt;/a&gt; powered by python. Now I no longer own the domain due to financial constraints. Also I have been writing in places like Diaspora, Discourse, etc., But then I have stopped blogging even though I have wordpress blogs. Somehow I got bored writing with Wordpress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.getpelican.com/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to be interesting, also writing a blog in a text-editor like vim &amp;amp; using markdown syntax for content makes me excited. Typing down my thoughts without the need for in-browser editor and web connectivity keeps me away from distractions online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think Pelican + Git + Github-Pages is more convinient than traditional blogging platforms for multiple reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No worries about managing / maintaining Database (just markdown, html)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Absence of db means the data is distributed. Git is tracking and so the copy of files stays in my local hard disk as well as on github repository. So need not worry about data loss / disk corruption.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple markdown syntax helps in focusing on contents for blog post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can always move the site to other providers / host my own, if I at some point needed to abandon github (it's already a proprietary platform).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="blog"></category><category term="pelican"></category></entry></feed>