<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Towards Freedom</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/</id><updated>2020-05-27T00:00:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Lockdown Diaries - 1</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/lockdown-diary-1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-27T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-05-27T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2020-05-27:/blog/lockdown-diary-1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lockdown is not the same for all. Thousands of migrant workers across India especially from the North are forced to walk thousands of kilometers to reach their natives when the Govt. did not consider about them before announcing the lockdown. If I am not wrong, it happened only in India …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lockdown is not the same for all. Thousands of migrant workers across India especially from the North are forced to walk thousands of kilometers to reach their natives when the Govt. did not consider about them before announcing the lockdown. If I am not wrong, it happened only in India. The rest of the world can best understand this fascist neo-liberal govt. of India under BJP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working From Home has it's own postivies and negatives. I have been working From Home 2 days in a week for past 1 year before COVID-19 lockdown. With lockdown it's continuous. All day from morning 9:30am to evening 5:30 or 6:00pm I would be spending more time in front of my laptop than doing any physical work. When it's evening I have an urge to stop working and do something physical like going out and not be constrained within the walls. Stop consuming too much information from social media, exercise, cycling etc.,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feeling would be the opposite for those who work at the office and come back home in the evening. They would want to be rested. To check social media, consume information etc., This dialectics exist between working from office and working from home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this lockdown, my apartment terrace is the goto place for me to breathe fresh air and not constrained by walls. I enjoy the winds and watching other people on their terraces kiteflying. Kiteflying has become a pass time for many in our locality post lockdown. People come up with creative shapes for the kites. It's funny to watch them flying it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once it's dark, one after the other brighter objects starts to appear in the sky. The first thing that I observe is the planet Venus on the North West somewhere around 40 degree altitude. Then the rest of the stars Sirius, Procyon, Capella, Betelgeuse, Orion constellation around Venus on the west and Arcturus and Azimech on the East and more on the North and South. East and West are what I observe due to less light pollution on those sides compared to North or South.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use the famous Free and Open Source Planetarium Software &lt;a href="https://stellarium.org/"&gt;Stellarium&lt;/a&gt; to explore the night sky and figure out the details of the object that I am looking at. I used to come alone to the terrace before lockdown, but after lockdown most of them in the apartment started to join me as well. When I was using Stellarium in my phone to point at the Sky to spot something, others got curious to know what I am doing. I explained them and they got very excited to try it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I shared the apk with them (as stelliarum is a paid app in google play store). I obtained a basic build from &lt;a href="https://github.com/Stellarium/stellarium/releases/latest"&gt;github repository&lt;/a&gt;. Now I consider purchasing Stellarium from play store to support the couple of developers behind this FOSS project. Stellarium for desktop is free though. I taught them some basics of how to use and they picked up from there and started exploring on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What started as star gazing, quickly turned into spotting Satellites. I know we can spot &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Space_Station"&gt;International Space Station (Zarya)&lt;/a&gt; at specific time on specific days. I checked at &lt;a href=""&gt;NASA's Spot The Station website&lt;/a&gt; to get the ISS sighting timings for my location. Fortunately, for the week, we had the opportunity to spot it. People were execited to see a bright light moving faster for the first time and they caputred video in their phones and shared in their social networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to check, what else could be spotted apart from ISS and jumped into Stellarium. I took my laptop with me to terrace. I will sit down facing west and figure out if any other satellite could be spotted. The latest version of Stellarium comes with &lt;strong&gt;realistic mode&lt;/strong&gt; enabled by default. It means it will take into account the light pollution and the brightness of celestial objects into account for our location and simulate them. This means it only show what will be really visible for our eyes on the sky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figured out that we could turn off this realistic mode. When I did that, I was awe struck at the congestion of geo-stationary satellites parked (not really, their orbital speeds are in sync with earth's speed so they appear stationary) from East to West and vice versa. With Stellarium we can adjust the time to move backdward and forward and see what was there or what would be there in the sky at that time. I used this to spot &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hubble_Space_Telescope"&gt;Hubble Space Telescope&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neil_Gehrels_Swift_Observatory"&gt;SWIFT&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="screenshot from stellarium show parked geo stationary satellites" src="images/stellarium-sats.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It became a routine for us. People started to show up daily with a new question. It was a good opportunity to communicate science to them. We talked about the International Space Station, other statellites and their purpose. I shared videos and movies with them on science fiction. We have some 4 dish antennas mounted at our terrace pointed to a specific direction. I explained them how there is a geo stationary satelitte out there in the direction that the dish is pointing and it is signals from such satellites that they receive signals which they watch in their TVs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post has already grown long. I will end it here and continue the rest in part 2.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="tech"></category><category term="astronomy"></category><category term="lockdown"></category></entry><entry><title>Metaprogramming Elixir Notes - 1</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/meta-elixir-notes-1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-04-11T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-04-11T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2020-04-11:/blog/meta-elixir-notes-1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the past 6 months, I have been exploring Elixir language and it's ecosystem. Elixir is a dynamic functional language. It compiles to bytecode to run on BEAM (Erlang's Virtual Machine) similar to how Java code is compiled to bytecode to run on JVM. There are fundamental &lt;a href="jvm-beam-differences.html"&gt;differences between BEAM …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the past 6 months, I have been exploring Elixir language and it's ecosystem. Elixir is a dynamic functional language. It compiles to bytecode to run on BEAM (Erlang's Virtual Machine) similar to how Java code is compiled to bytecode to run on JVM. There are fundamental &lt;a href="jvm-beam-differences.html"&gt;differences between BEAM and JVM&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elixir is relatively a new language compared with Java and Python. Development of this language started in 2012 and as of writing it we have Elixir v1.10. Almost all functional languages are declarative in style. This is the first time, I am learning to write programs in declarative style rather than imperative style even though Python also has some declarative and functional approach here and there but it really doesn't enforce a particular style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, the word &lt;strong&gt;Metaprogramming&lt;/strong&gt; has been fascinating to me since I came across the phrase &lt;strong&gt;code that writes code&lt;/strong&gt;. Learning to program with Elixir and learning all other new terminologies of Erlang ecosystem so far has been very pleasant for me. Thanks to Sasa Juric's book. That said, I am also learning the only web framework as of today available for Elixir, &lt;a href="https://www.phoenixframework.org/"&gt;Phoenix&lt;/a&gt;. The author of Phoenix had leveraged Elixir's metaprogramming abilities using macros and has also published a book titled &lt;a href="https://pragprog.com/book/cmelixir/metaprogramming-elixir"&gt;Metaprogramming Elixir&lt;/a&gt;. I have started to read this book too and this blog post is the notes that I took for Chapter 1 of the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Notes 1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Metaprogramming allows us to do more by writing less code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Macros facilitate metaprogramming in Elixir.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract Syntax Tree (AST)&lt;/strong&gt; is how compilers represent the code we write before processing them and converting to bytecode.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Macros are language feature that allows us to write code that writes code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;quote&lt;/code&gt; is a macro in Elixir that will give us the AST representation of our Elixir code using Elixir's native data structure called tuple {}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any expression in Elixir, represented in AST will be a tuple with three units. &lt;code&gt;{:atom, [context], [arguments]}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;:atom&lt;/code&gt; will be mostly function names, &lt;code&gt;[context]&lt;/code&gt; is a list of contexts required to perform the operation, last one is list of arguments passed to the function.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Macro's in Elixir taskes AST representation as input and returns either the modified or unmodified version of the AST thus allows us to inject code into code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Metaprogramming turns us from being a &lt;strong&gt;language consumer to language creator&lt;/strong&gt;, because Macro's allows us to extend the language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Metaprogramming in Elixir asks us to throw away the notion of rigid keywords &amp;amp; opaque langugage internals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;unquote&lt;/code&gt; is a macro used within &lt;code&gt;quote&lt;/code&gt; block that allows us to perform the inverse operation of quote that is to inject the expressions into the AST. They cannot be used outside &lt;code&gt;quote&lt;/code&gt; macro.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chris McCord, the author of Phoenix framework and this book gives us 2 cautions or rules while trying to learn Metaprogramming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, &lt;strong&gt;Don't Write Macros&lt;/strong&gt;. When taken too far in depth, macro's can make programs difficult to debug and reason about. Think about the movie Inception. Which dream are they in?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Second, don't let the first rule demotivate you to learn it. Approach and Explore Macros and Metaprogramming with open and curious mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One can think &lt;code&gt;quote&lt;/code&gt; is like enclosing a variable with double quotes and &lt;code&gt;unquote&lt;/code&gt; as, removing it thus depicting the value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ex: age = 2, &lt;code&gt;quote&lt;/code&gt; means, "age", while &lt;code&gt;unquote&lt;/code&gt; means age&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elixir also provides us a module called Macro to playaround with macros within the language. &lt;code&gt;Macro.expand&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Macro.expand_once&lt;/code&gt; can be used to explore how compiler expands the Macro's at compile time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code can be injected in two contexts. One is Macro's definition context (outside quote) and the other is the macro's caller invocation context (within quote).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elixir also provides a concept of &lt;strong&gt;Hygine&lt;/strong&gt;. i.e keeping pollution-free contexts. By default, elixir prevents access to caller scope variable inside the macros, but if needed, they can be polluted explicitly by using &lt;code&gt;var!(variable_name)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is to be noted that most of the language constructs of Elixir itself is written as macros with a small set of core native types.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Macros also allows us to create Domain Specific language terminologies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example Macro &amp;amp; Usage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;defmodule MyMacro do
  defmacro debug({:+, _context, [lhs, rhs]}) do
    IO.puts &amp;quot;Macro definition Context&amp;quot;
    quote do
        IO.puts &amp;quot;Caller&amp;#39;s context&amp;quot;
        lhs = unquote(lhs)
        rhs = unquote(rhs)
        result = lhs + rhs
        IO.puts &amp;quot;#{lhs} plus #{rhs} equals to #{result}&amp;quot;
        result
    end
  end
end

iex&amp;gt;require MyMacro
iex&amp;gt;MyMacro.debug(2 + 3)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Notes for Chapter 1 ends here. Will share notes for Chapter 2 when I finish it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="elixir"></category><category term="code"></category></entry><entry><title>JVM vs BEAM Architecture Differences</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/jvm-beam-differences.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-01-03T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-01-03T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2020-01-03:/blog/jvm-beam-differences.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recently read &lt;a href="http://ds.cs.ut.ee/courses/course-files/To303nis%20Pool%20.pdf"&gt;a study&lt;/a&gt; comparing the design of widely used Oracle's implementation of JVM (aka. HotSpot VM) and Erricson's implementation Erlang VM (BEAM) with respect to concurrency and parallelism. This study was published in May 2015.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is not about comparing two languages (i.e java vs erlang/elixir) or …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recently read &lt;a href="http://ds.cs.ut.ee/courses/course-files/To303nis%20Pool%20.pdf"&gt;a study&lt;/a&gt; comparing the design of widely used Oracle's implementation of JVM (aka. HotSpot VM) and Erricson's implementation Erlang VM (BEAM) with respect to concurrency and parallelism. This study was published in May 2015.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is not about comparing two languages (i.e java vs erlang/elixir) or programming paradigms (Object Oriented vs Functional). This is more about the design of the virtual machine themselves which ultimately is responsibile for interpreting the bytecode into machine level instructions and runs the applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;JVM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JVM's internal representation has a stack, shared heap and garbage collector.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The garbage collector has two sections within it to identify objects that die too young and those live long.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be a global pause (all world pause) to clean up garbage values.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The responsibility of avoiding deadlock for critical sections for concurrency falls to the programmer due to underlying shared heap (shared state).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Akka framework brings the Actor model to Java applications, but underlying shared heap means block in one component means entire application thread blocks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VM Threads are one-to-one mapping with os level threads. Therefore scheduling is relied on os level schedulers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JIT Compiliation strategy is a strength.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Irrespective of it's implementation, JVM also employs a lot of optimization strategies to garbage collection, scheduling, etc., that counters the design limitations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;BEAM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BEAM is implemented with Actor Model. With processos as Actors and Message passing among processes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each process has it's own stack and heap. No global pause for garbage collecting, since each processes has it's own memory scope isolated from others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Has number of schedulers as per the cpu core and schedulers can load-balance based on strategies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VM threads are many-to-many mapping with os level threads therefore no need to entirely depend on os level schedulers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no JIT compilation strategy with BEAM. A project called BEAMJIT was started some years back, but it's not complete.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, let us not jump to conclusions of which is better without matching them against the context and problem at hand. Here is &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=10027884"&gt;a discussion thread in Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; on the same topic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="tech"></category><category term="design"></category></entry><entry><title>Dead Labour என்றால் என்ன?</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/what-is-dead-labour.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-03-03T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-03-03T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2019-03-03:/blog/what-is-dead-labour.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;மார்க்ஸ் மூலதனத்தை (Capital) "&lt;strong&gt;Dead Labour&lt;/strong&gt;" அதாவது &lt;strong&gt;உயிரிழந்த&lt;/strong&gt; (அல்லது) &lt;strong&gt;உயிரற்ற உழைப்பு&lt;/strong&gt; என்கிறார். அவர் ஏன் இதனை அப்படி அழைக்கிறார்? அப்படியானால் &lt;strong&gt;உயிருள்ள உழைப்ப …&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;மார்க்ஸ் மூலதனத்தை (Capital) "&lt;strong&gt;Dead Labour&lt;/strong&gt;" அதாவது &lt;strong&gt;உயிரிழந்த&lt;/strong&gt; (அல்லது) &lt;strong&gt;உயிரற்ற உழைப்பு&lt;/strong&gt; என்கிறார். அவர் ஏன் இதனை அப்படி அழைக்கிறார்? அப்படியானால் &lt;strong&gt;உயிருள்ள உழைப்பு&lt;/strong&gt; என்று ஒன்று உள்ளதா?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;இதனை புரிந்துக் கொள்ள முதலில் மார்க்ஸ் முன்வைக்கும் "&lt;strong&gt;Labour Theory of Value&lt;/strong&gt;" என்பதை நாம் புரிந்துக் கொள்ள வேண்டும்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ஒரு பண்டத்தை உற்பத்தி செய்ய வேண்டும் என்று வைத்துக் கொள்வோம். முதலில் என்ன தேவை?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;அதற்கான &lt;strong&gt;மூலப் பொருட்கள்&lt;/strong&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;உற்பத்திக்கு உதவும் &lt;strong&gt;கருவிகள் மற்றும் சாதனங்கள்&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;இடம், மின்சாரம், மேலும் சில.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;இவை பண்டத்தை உற்பத்தி செய்வதற்கு முன்பே இருந்தால் மட்டுமே பண்டத்தை உற்பத்தி செய்யும் பணியில் இறங்க முடியும். எனவே இந்த மூலப்பொருட்களும், கருவிகளும், சாதனங்களும் &lt;strong&gt;கடந்த காலத்திலிருந்து நிகழ்காலத்திற்கு தேவைப்படும் ஒன்றாக மாறுகிறது&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;கடந்த கால உழைப்பாளிகளின் உழைப்பால் உண்டான இந்த மூலப்பொருட்களும், கருவிகள் மற்றும் சாதனங்களைத் தான் ஒரு முதலாளி மூலதனம் என்ற பெயரில் பணப்பரிவர்தனை மூலம் நிகழ்காலத்திற்கு கொண்டு வருகிறார். இந்த பரிவர்தனை மூலம் இன்றைய முதலாளிக்கு எந்த ஒரு புதிய மதிப்போ, இலாபமோ உருவாகவில்லை, ஆனால் கடந்தகால உழைப்பை சந்தையில் விற்கும் அந்த முதலாளிக்கு இலாபம் உண்டாகியிருக்கும். இது ஏன் என்று பிறகு பார்ப்போம்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;தற்சமயம் நாம் புரிந்துக் கொள்ள வேண்டியது, பண்டத்தை இனிமேதான் உற்பத்தி செய்ய வேண்டிய முதலாளியை பொருத்த வரை கொடுத்த பணத்திற்கு ஈடான சிலவற்றை பெற்றுக்கொண்டாரே தவிர, அதற்கு அதிகமாக அவரிடம் எதுவும் வந்து சேரவில்லை.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;இந்த மூலப்பொருட்களும், கருவிகளும், சாதனங்களும் கடந்த கால உழைப்பை உள்ளடக்கிக் கொண்டிருப்பதால் அதுவே அப்பொருட்கள் மற்றும் சாதனங்களின் மதிப்பாக (value) மாறியது. உழைப்பே இங்கு மதிப்பை உருவாக்குகிறது. இந்த மதிப்பின் மேல் தான் பயன் மதிப்பு (use-value) மற்றும் பரிவர்தனை மதிப்பு (exchange-value) என்ற பிற மதிப்புகள் சந்தையில் தங்களை வெளிப்படுத்திக் கொள்கின்றன. இதுவே "Labour Theory of Value" எனப்படுகிறது.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;இந்த கடந்தகால அல்லது உயிரற்ற உழைப்பை பயன்படுத்தி ஒரு பண்டத்தை உற்பத்தி செய்ய ஒரு முதலாளிக்கு, &lt;strong&gt;தொழிலாளிகள் தேவைப்படுகிறார்கள்&lt;/strong&gt;. இத்தொழிலாளிகளின் உழைப்பே "&lt;strong&gt;living labour&lt;/strong&gt;" அல்லது &lt;strong&gt;நிகழ்கால உழைப்பு&lt;/strong&gt; (அல்லது) &lt;strong&gt;உயிருள்ள உழைப்பு&lt;/strong&gt; எனப்படுகிறது. வெறும் கடந்தகால உழைப்பை பணத்திற்கு பரிவர்தனை செய்து வாங்கிவிட்டால் மட்டும் புதிய பொருட்களோ, மதிப்புகளோ உருவாகிவிடாது. தொழிலாளர்கள் உழைப்பினால் தான் புதிய மதிப்புள்ள பொருட்களாக அவை மாறுகின்றன.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;இப்புதிய பண்டம் அல்லது பொருளானது சந்தைக்கு எடுத்துச் செல்லப்படும். அது மீண்டும் வேறொரு முதலாளிக்கு தேவைப்படும் ஒரு மூலப்பொருளாக இருக்கலாம் (அல்லது) அவற்றை மீண்டும் உழைக்கும் மக்களிடமே விற்றாக வேண்டும். இப்படி சந்தையில் அதனை விற்கும் போதுதான் அதற்கு என்ன விலை இந்த முதலாளி நிர்ணயிக்கிறார் என்பதைப் பொறுத்து, உபரி மதிப்பு (surplus value) என்பதை அவரே உணர முடியும்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;எடுத்துக்காட்டாக, இந்த பண்டத்தை உற்பத்தி செய்ய ஆகிய மொத்த செலவு (தொழிலாளியின் சம்பளம் உட்பட) ரூ. 10 என்றால், அவர் அதனை அதே விலைக்கு சந்தையில் விற்க முடியாது. அப்படி அவர் அதே விலைக்கு விற்றால் அது அந்த பண்டத்திலிருக்கும் உழைப்பின் மதிப்பை அதே அளவில் பரிமாறிக் கொண்டதாக அர்த்தம், அதனால் முதலாளிக்கு கூடுதலாக எதுவும் கிடைக்கவில்லை. அல்லது முதலாளிக்கு சம்பளம் வரவில்லை என்று கூட எடுத்துக்கொள்ளலாம்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;எனவே இந்த பண்டத்தின் பரிவர்தனை மதிப்பு சந்தையில் கூடுதலாகவே முதலாளி விற்கிறார். ரூ.12 என்று வைத்துக்கொள்வோம். இப்படி 2 ரூபாய் அதிகமாக ஒவ்வொரு பண்டத்திலிருந்தும் எடுத்துக்கொள்ளும் முதலாளி, இதை தனக்கான வரவாக கைப்பற்றிக் கொள்கிறார்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;இவரிடம் 5 தொழிலாளிகள் வேலை செய்கின்றனர், 5 தொழிலாளிகள் ஓவ்வொருவரும் தலா 1 பண்டத்தை உற்பத்தி செய்தார்கள் என்று எடுத்துகொண்டால்... 5 பண்டம் உருவாகியிருக்கிறது.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;விற்பனைக்கு முன்&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;முதலாளியின் செலவு (நிகழ்கால உழைப்பிற்கு மட்டும்)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 தொழிலாளிக்கு கூலி = ரூ. 2/-&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 தொழிலாளிக்கு கூலி = ரூ. 10/-&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ரூ. 8/- கடந்தகால உழைப்பான மூலப்பொருட்களுக்கும், சாதனத்திற்கும்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;முதலாலியிடம் இருப்பு&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ரூ. 50/- மதிப்புள்ள 5 பண்டங்கள்&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;தொழிலாளியின் செலவு&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;தங்கள் வாழ்நாளில் ஒரு நாளின் 'x' மணி நேரம் மற்றும் உழைக்கும் சக்தி.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;தொழிலாளியிடம் இருப்பு&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 தொழிலாளியிடம் ரூ. 2/-&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 தொழிலாளியிடம் ரூ. 10/-&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;சந்தையில் விற்பனை&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ரூ. 2/- ஏற்றி விற்கிறார் முதலாளி&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 பண்டத்தின் சந்தை விலை = ரூ. 12/-&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 பண்டத்தின் சந்தை விலை = ரூ. 60/-&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;விற்பனைக்கு பின்&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;முதலாளியின் வரவு&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 பண்டத்தால் = ரூ. 2/-&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 பண்டத்தால் = ரூ. 10/-&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; முதலாளியிடம் இருப்பு &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ரூ. 10/-&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ஒரு தொழிலாளியின் வரவு&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 பண்டத்தை தான் உருவாக்கியிருப்பார் = ரூ. - 2/-&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;தொழிலாளிகளின் மொத்த வரவு&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 பண்டம் கூட்டாக = ரூ. - 10/-&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; ஒரு தொழிலாளியிடம் இருப்பு &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ரூ. 2/-&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;விற்பனைக்கு முன்னும் பின்னும், தொழிலாளர்களின் இருப்பு மாறாமல் இருக்கிறது, ஆனால் முதலாளியின் இருப்பு மட்டும் அதிகரித்துள்ளது. எப்படி? இந்த அதிகரிப்பு எங்கிருந்து வந்திருக்க முடியும்? முதலாளி ஓவ்வொரு தொழிலாளிக்கும் சேர வேண்டிய ரூ. 2/-, 5 தொழிலாளிகளிடமிருந்து கைப்பற்றி ரூ. 10/- வரவு பெற்றார். அப்படியெனில் ஒரு தொழிலாளிக்கு சேர வேண்டிய உண்மையான கூலி என்பது ரூ. 2/- அல்ல, ரூ. 4/-.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ரூ. 10/- ல் முதலாளி ரூ. 2/- எடுத்துக்கொண்டு, மீதமுள்ள ரூ. 8/- மறுமுதலீடு செய்தோ அல்லது, வேறு வழிகளில் பெருக்கும் வாய்ப்பு இருக்கிறது. ஆனால் ரூ. 2/- மட்டுமே இருப்பு வைத்திருக்கும் தொழிலாளிக்கோ சுதந்திரமாக செயல்படும் மாற்று வழி இல்லாததால் கூலி அடிமை முறையில் சிக்கிக் கொள்கிறார். ஒரு முதலாளி மனதளவில் நல்லவராக இருக்கலாம் என்றாலும் மூலதனம் விடாது, ஏனெனில் இங்கே அவர் ஒருவர் மட்டும் இத்தொழிலில் ஈடுபடவில்லை, போட்டிக்கு மேலும் சில முதலாளிகளும் உள்ளனர். எனவே முதலாளி வர்க்கத்திர்க்கு தொழிலாளியை சுரண்டி வாழ்வதை தவிர வேறு வழியில்லை.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;இங்கே கடந்தகால உழைப்பை, நிகழ்கால மதிப்பாக மாற்றியது எது? நிச்சயமாக மூலதனம் இல்லை, ஏனெனில் மூலதனம் தான் அந்த கடந்தகால மதிப்பே! அது மதிப்பை கூட்டவும் இல்லை, குறைக்கவும் இல்லை. தொழிலாளிகள் உற்பத்தியில் ஈடுபடும் போது தான் புதிய மதிப்பே உருவாகிறது. ஆனால் அதனை சந்தையில் நடக்கும் பரிவர்த்தனை மூலம் தான் அந்த முதலாளியே உணர முடியும்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;கடந்தகால உழைப்பை சந்தையில் விற்கும் அந்த முதலாளிக்கு இலாபம் உண்டாகியிருக்கும். இது ஏன் என்று பிறகு பார்ப்போம்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;முன்பு மேலே குறிப்பிட்ட இந்த வாக்கியத்திற்கு இப்போது பொருள் புரிந்திருக்கும் என்று நம்புகிறேன். கடந்த கால உழைப்பின் சந்தை விலையை அந்த முதலாளி இந்த முதலாளிக்கு ரூ. 2/- அதிகமாக விற்றிருக்கிறார். நிகழ்கால உழைப்பை பயன்படுத்திக் கொண்ட இந்த முதலாளி அவரிடம் இழந்த ரூ. 2/- மீண்டும் சந்தையிலிருந்தே பெற்றிருக்கிறார். இது எதைக் குறிக்கிறது? -2 + 2 = 0. சந்தையில் ஒரு பணடத்தின் மதிப்பு மாறவே இல்லை. ஆனால் பரிவர்த்தனை மதிப்பு (அல்லது) சந்தையில் பண்டத்தின் விலை மற்றும் உயர்ந்துள்ளது. இது தான் பணவீக்கம் (inflation) எனப்படுவது.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;நீங்கள் சொல்வது படி பார்த்தால் முதலாளிக்கு எதுவுமே கிடைக்காதே! ஆம், கடந்தகால உழைப்பை நிகழ்காலத்திற்கோ (அல்லது) எதிர்காலத்திற்கோ தேவையான ஒன்றாக மாற்றியதில் முதலாளியின் உழைப்பு என்ன?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;கடந்த கால உழைப்பை கைப்பற்றி வைத்திருந்த ஒரு முதலாளியிடமிருந்து இவர் கைப்பற்றி வைத்துக் கொண்டார். ஏன்? ஏனெனில் மீண்டும் தொழிலாளர்களின் உழைப்பால் உண்டாகும் மதிப்பை சந்தையிலிருந்து கைப்பற்றத் தான். இது இரத்தத்தை மெல்ல உரிஞ்சும் அட்டைப் பூச்சி செயல் தானே? ஒவ்வொரு தொழிலாளியும் தான் பெறும் சம்பளம் அல்லது கூலியோடு சேர்த்து உட்கார்ந்து சாப்பிடும் முதலாளியின் கூலிக்கும் சேர்த்து உழைக்கிறார்கள்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;முதலாளியும் தொழிலாளர்களோடு சேர்ந்து பொருள் உற்பத்தியில் ஈடுபட்டிருந்தால், கைப்பற்றிய கடந்தகால உழைப்பு என்பது முதலாளிக்கு மட்டும் சொந்தமில்லை, உழைக்கும் நிகழ்கால தொழிலாளர்களுக்கும் சொந்தமென்றால், சந்தையிலிருந்து வரும் உபரி மதிப்பு என்பது மீண்டும் அனைத்து தொழிலாளர்களுக்குமே செல்லும். இதுவே கூட்டுறவு முறையிலான உற்பத்தி என்பது. உற்பத்தி முறையை மாற்றியமைக்காமல் சுரண்டலை ஒழிக்க முடியாது.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="cooperatives"></category><category term="capital"></category><category term="economy"></category></entry><entry><title>Clojure Notes 1</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/clojure-notes-1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-02-19T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-02-19T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2019-02-19:/blog/clojure-notes-1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Started learning another general purpose programming language called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://clojure.org/"&gt;Clojure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; which speaks &lt;strong&gt;lisp&lt;/strong&gt; dialect and runs on top of &lt;strong&gt;JVM&lt;/strong&gt;. Thanks to Kamalavelan for creating an interest for me to learn clojure and particularly the book titled, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://nostarch.com/clojure"&gt;Clojure For The Brave and True&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; by David Higginbotham is very enjoyable.
https://nostarch …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Started learning another general purpose programming language called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://clojure.org/"&gt;Clojure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; which speaks &lt;strong&gt;lisp&lt;/strong&gt; dialect and runs on top of &lt;strong&gt;JVM&lt;/strong&gt;. Thanks to Kamalavelan for creating an interest for me to learn clojure and particularly the book titled, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://nostarch.com/clojure"&gt;Clojure For The Brave and True&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; by David Higginbotham is very enjoyable.
https://nostarch.com/clojure
As a matter of taking notes of what I learn from the book, I share the notes here chapter wise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Chapter 1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Installing Clojure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Installing &lt;a href="https://leiningen.org/"&gt;leiningen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;lein new app &amp;lt;folder-name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;()&lt;/code&gt; based syntax, namespaces, -main function, &lt;code&gt;println&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;lein run&lt;/code&gt; =&amp;gt; to build and see the output&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;lein uberjar&lt;/code&gt; =&amp;gt; to build standalone jars&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;lein repl&lt;/code&gt; =&amp;gt; to start a repl&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Chapter 2 - Emacs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have largely ignored emacs tutorial.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But installed gnu emacs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Downloaded clojure configuration for emacs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Downloaded and installed &lt;a href="https://sekao.net/nightcode/"&gt;Nightcode IDE&lt;/a&gt; for clojure and I prefer it for now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also using lein repl to practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Chapter 3 - Language Fundamentals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;started using NightCode with REPL.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;FORMS&lt;/code&gt; are expressions that clojure evaluates to produce a value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ex: &lt;code&gt;1 "a string" ["a" "string" "vector]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;basic syntax: &lt;code&gt;(operator operand1 operand2 ... operandn)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the above syntax is unifrom throughout LISP dialect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;(str "string1" "string2)&lt;/code&gt; =&amp;gt; string1string2 =&amp;gt; concatenates strings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;control flow =&amp;gt; if do when&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(if boolean-form then-form optional-else-form)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;(if true
&amp;quot;Sucess&amp;quot;
&amp;quot;Failure&amp;quot;)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;note that if..else can execute only one form. to overcome this we can use do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;(if true
    (do (println &amp;quot;Success&amp;quot;)
        &amp;quot;succesS&amp;quot;)
    (do (println &amp;quot;Failure&amp;quot;)
        &amp;quot;failure&amp;quot;))
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;when&lt;/code&gt; operator is like both if and do together but without else part and returns nil when the condition is false.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt; boolean operators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;nil&lt;/code&gt; represents no value in clojure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;binding value to variables are done using &lt;strong&gt;def&lt;/strong&gt; keyword&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;(def name &amp;quot;prasanna&amp;quot;)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ratio can be directly represented in clojure. &lt;code&gt;1/5&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maps&lt;/strong&gt; are key, value store. &lt;strong&gt;Hashmap&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Sorted maps&lt;/strong&gt; are present in clojure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;(def sampleMap {:first_name &amp;quot;Prasanna&amp;quot; :last_name &amp;quot;Venkadesh})
(get sampleMap :first_name)
(sampleMap :first_name)
(:first_name sampleMap)

(def sampleHashMap (hashmap :a 1 :b 2))
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maps can also be nested and &lt;code&gt;get-in&lt;/code&gt; function is used to retreive nested map values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;(get-in {:a 0 :b {:c &amp;quot;1}} [:b :c])
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vectors&lt;/strong&gt; are like 0 indexed arrays and can be heterogenous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;[1 2 3 4]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;(def vecData [1 2 3 4])&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;(get vecData 2)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;(conj vecData 10)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;conj&lt;/code&gt; function is used to append value at to vector and &lt;code&gt;vector&lt;/code&gt; function is used to create a new vector with supplied values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;(vector &amp;quot;test&amp;quot; 1 &amp;quot;testing&amp;quot;)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;list&lt;/strong&gt; in clojure is similar to vector, but &lt;code&gt;get&lt;/code&gt; function will not work with list. &lt;code&gt;nth&lt;/code&gt; function has to be used instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#39;(1 2 3 4)
(list 1 2 3 4)
(def listData &amp;#39;(1 2 3 4))
(def listData (list 1 2 3 4))
(nth listData 0)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;conj&lt;/code&gt; function with list will add elements to the &lt;strong&gt;beginning&lt;/strong&gt; of the list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;(conj listData 10)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fetching elements from list using &lt;code&gt;nth&lt;/code&gt; function will be slower than &lt;code&gt;get&lt;/code&gt; in vector. When to use what depends on whether we want to add elements to end or beginning of the data structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clojure supports &lt;strong&gt;higher-order functions&lt;/strong&gt;, i.e a function that can take another function as argument or can return another function. Programming languages with higher-order functions are said to support &lt;strong&gt;first class functions&lt;/strong&gt; because we can treat functions as values in the same way we treat other data types like number, string, etc., &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;inc&lt;/strong&gt; function can increment a numeric value. &lt;strong&gt;map&lt;/strong&gt; function can operate over a collection and can return a list as result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;(inc 20)
(map inc [1 2 3 4])
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[]&lt;/strong&gt; is used to pass arguments to functions. function parameters can be used to overload and can be used for multiple purposes. Those are called &lt;strong&gt;Arity&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kd"&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;myFunction&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;([]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;println&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;no arguments supplied&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="nv"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;println&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;two arguments supplied&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt; ampresand is used to denote rest of parameters. Like *args in &lt;code&gt;python&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kd"&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;myFunction&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(str "Hi. I am " name))&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kd"&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;myFunc&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;names&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;map&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;myFunc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;names&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;myFunc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Prasanna&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Kamal&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anonymous Functions&lt;/strong&gt; are functions without names. They can be defined anywhere using &lt;code&gt;fn&lt;/code&gt; keyword.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;(fn [arguments] function-body)

((fn [x] (* x 3)) 8)

(map (fn [name] (str &amp;quot;Hi &amp;quot; name) [&amp;quot;Prasanna&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Kamal&amp;quot;])
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;anonymous functions can also be bound to variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;(def my-function (fn [name] (str &amp;quot;Hi, &amp;quot; name)))
(my-function &amp;quot;Prasanna&amp;quot;)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a much more shortcut way to define anonymous functions using &lt;code&gt;#&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;#(+ % 2)
(#(+ % 2) 8)
(#(str &amp;quot;Hi &amp;quot; %) &amp;quot;Prasanna&amp;quot;)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the anonymous function takes multiple arguments, then &lt;code&gt;%1 %2 ... %n&lt;/code&gt; form can be used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Destructuring&lt;/strong&gt; is about binding names to values in a collection based on positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kd"&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;chooser&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;first-param&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;first-param&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;chooser&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Prasanna&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Kamal&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kd"&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;chooser&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;age&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;other&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;println&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;str&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Hi, &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;println&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;str&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Your age: &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;age&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;prinln&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;str&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Other info: &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;clojure.string/join&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;other&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))))&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;chooser&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Prasanna&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;28&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;test@testing.org&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;B+&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clojure has &lt;strong&gt;closures&lt;/strong&gt;. Yes. closures are those functions that are returned by another functions. closure by itself is a design pattern to indicate state maintanence or scope of variables. To be frank, I haven't grasped this design well yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kd"&gt;defn &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;inc-maker&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Create a custom incrementor&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;inc-by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="o"&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;inc-by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kd"&gt;def &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;inc3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;inc-maker&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;inc3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;End of Chapter 3. Will continue further notes in separate post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="books"></category><category term="code"></category></entry><entry><title>Reading Building Alternatives - Introduction</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/building-alternatives-intro.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-02-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-02-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2019-02-10:/blog/building-alternatives-intro.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uralungal Labour Contract Cooperative Soceity (ULCCS)&lt;/strong&gt; is almost &lt;strong&gt;90 year old&lt;/strong&gt; (as of this writing in 2019) &lt;strong&gt;cooperative of construction workers&lt;/strong&gt; from the state of Kerala, India. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current finance minister of Kerala, Dr. T.M. Thomas Issac (CPIM) and Dr. Michelle Williams (Professor at University of Witswatersrand, South Africa …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uralungal Labour Contract Cooperative Soceity (ULCCS)&lt;/strong&gt; is almost &lt;strong&gt;90 year old&lt;/strong&gt; (as of this writing in 2019) &lt;strong&gt;cooperative of construction workers&lt;/strong&gt; from the state of Kerala, India. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current finance minister of Kerala, Dr. T.M. Thomas Issac (CPIM) and Dr. Michelle Williams (Professor at University of Witswatersrand, South Africa) had come together to tell us the story of this cooperative in a book titled, &lt;strong&gt;Building Alternatives - The story of India's Oldest Construction Workers' Cooperative&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book was published by LeftWord publishers and has a very good preface from the chief-editor of LeftWord, Mr. Vijay Prasad titled, &lt;strong&gt;Possible Communism&lt;/strong&gt; which can also be &lt;a href="https://indianculturalforum.in/2018/01/03/possible-communism/"&gt;read here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/note_taking.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this book was advertised through the social media accounts of LeftWord publishing house and May Day bookstore, I was so excited to get a copy of this book as I along with few more comrades were also pondering about the question of &lt;strong&gt;What alternatives to capitalist mode of production are possible today?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I along with my comrades went to attend a &lt;strong&gt;International Conference on "Cooperatives in The Changing World of Work"&lt;/strong&gt; organized at Indian Institute of Management - Kozhikode, Kerala by various organizations including &lt;strong&gt;International Cooperative Alliance - Asia Pacific&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;International Labour Organization&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Kerala Startup Mission&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://ulccsltd.com/"&gt;ULCCS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://ults.in/"&gt;ULTS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://nilenso.com"&gt;Nilenso&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, etc. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were very glad, each received a copy of this book as participants of this conference and the cooperative hackathon (Coopathon) that took place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have had debates and discussions with other people over the idea of worker-owned cooperatives (i.e workers owning and self-managing their companies instead being a employee working for wage/salary) and ULCCS is such a living example today. It is worth mentioning that, today ULCCS has built and owns an &lt;strong&gt;Information Technology Park&lt;/strong&gt; at Kerala and it has also given birth to &lt;strong&gt;Uralungal Labour Technology Solutions (ULTS)&lt;/strong&gt; which is a IT firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly it is also important to mention, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://nilenso.com"&gt;Nilenso&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; based out of Bengaluru is also India's first worker-owned software cooperative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I started reading the book, I have highlighted and took note of points which I felt are important take aways from ULCCS' experience of successfully driving a cooperative for 9 decades. Hence, I would like to also consolidate those key take-aways as a series of blog post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="books"></category><category term="alternatives"></category><category term="economy"></category><category term="cooperatives"></category></entry><entry><title>Contributions to OpenStreetMap</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/osm-contributions.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-06T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-10-06T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2018-10-06:/blog/osm-contributions.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote this post to document my contributions to OpenStreetMap and to enrich the ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://openstreetmap.org"&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt; (OSM) is the map built by the people, for the people and of the people. In other words, it is the democratic process of creating the map of the earth together. Simultaneously anyone can …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote this post to document my contributions to OpenStreetMap and to enrich the ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://openstreetmap.org"&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt; (OSM) is the map built by the people, for the people and of the people. In other words, it is the democratic process of creating the map of the earth together. Simultaneously anyone can also download all the geographical inforamtion from OpenStreetMap and use it for their own purposes. If Wikipedia is the encyclopedia commons, then OSM is the commons for geographical data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I joined OpenStreetMap by the end of 2011 but made my first drawing in OSM only by the mid of 2012. You can see my participation &lt;a href="https://hdyc.neis-one.org/?Prashere"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. There is a graph titled &lt;strong&gt;Amount of mapping days per year&lt;/strong&gt; in that link, if you observe that graph you can find that it was only in 2017 I took a serious participation in contributing to OSM. I did not even care about contributing to OSM during 2015 &amp;amp; 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="contribution graph" src="images/contribution-graph.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I joined OSM, I was carried away by the idea of Open Source and the Linux ecosystem. I don't know anything about the licenses or GNU project or Free Software itself. Over the years I was exposed to the idea of Free Software, it's principles and philosophy. This is where everything started to change. It took 4 years for me to understand the idea of knowledge commons (or) digital commons. By the end of 2017, at &lt;a href="https://fsftn.org"&gt;FSFTN&lt;/a&gt; we organized a OSM mapathon for celebrating &lt;a href="http://osmgeoweek.org/"&gt;#osmgeoweek&lt;/a&gt;. This is when my contribution to OSM also got serious. That is why in the above graph, there is a rise in my contribution during the period of 2017-18.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a part of the week long mapathon, I built a &lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/prashere/osm-leaderbooard/"&gt;web based leaderboard software in python&lt;/a&gt; that will rank the participants based on the number of edits they made during that period. Nearly 50 participants from Pondicherry and Tamilnadu took part in this mapathon and the &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.1902578996436104&amp;amp;type=1&amp;amp;l=375930f529"&gt;top 10 contributors were honoured by FSFTN&lt;/a&gt; for their contribution to the commons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="screenshot of leaderboard" src="images/leaderboard.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I released this &lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/prashere/osm-leaderbooard/"&gt;leaderboard software&lt;/a&gt; under a Free Software license, so that anyone around the world could make use of this software to run a local mapathon in their place. Sooner, &lt;a href="https://swecha.org"&gt;Swecha&lt;/a&gt;, a sister organization of FSFTN from Andhra Pradesh and Telengana forked the leaderboard program and started to remix for their purpose. The forked version can be found &lt;a href="https://code.swecha.org/sripathroy/osm-leaderboard"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It was moments like these that motivates people like me to write program and release them under FOSS license. The gratification that I receive when I create a socially necessary or useful program for myself and others is all that matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By early 2018, some of us at Pondicherry got interested into &lt;a href="http://www.rosalux-nyc.org/platform-cooperativism-2/"&gt;Platform Cooperativism&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;Trebor Scholz&lt;/strong&gt;, especially building an open and alternative platform for Uber and Ola. This means not depending on google maps or any proprietary maps as well. Obviously without doubt, our choice would be to use OSM (in fact Uber relies on OSM data for routing I suppose). We wanted to prototype it and for that we chose a OpenGL based android library called &lt;a href="https://github.com/mapsforge/vtm"&gt;VTM&lt;/a&gt; Vector Tile Maps for rendering the map. We took the map raw data from OSM and converted into Mapsforge Binary format using a tool called Osmosis and for routing we used a android library called graphhopper. The raw data from OSM would be in XML format and this needs to be converted into respective formats for both rendering and routing. I came up with a &lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/coopon/uauto/backend/map-preparation"&gt;shell script&lt;/a&gt; that can automate all this process of downloading the raw data from OSM and converting them into respective formats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the application that we are attempting to build itself is far from complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/tm-it-6-h68?rel=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond these I took 2 sessions on getting started with OpenStreetMap and drawing roads, buildings and point of interests at a local meetup organized by FSHM Puducherry. One of the session is recorded and uploaded to youtube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far my contributions to OSM include &lt;strong&gt;mapping&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;osm-leaderboard&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;map preparation process&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;tutorial&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="osm"></category><category term="mapping"></category></entry><entry><title>லிவ் இன்?</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/live-in.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-05T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-10-05T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2018-10-05:/blog/live-in.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;குடும்பம் என்றால் என்ன என்று நம் அனைவருக்கும் நன்றாகத் தெரியும். சமூகத்தில் ஒரு காலக்கட்டத்தில் உருவாகிய அமைப்பு முறை. மனித சமூகத்தில …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;குடும்பம் என்றால் என்ன என்று நம் அனைவருக்கும் நன்றாகத் தெரியும். சமூகத்தில் ஒரு காலக்கட்டத்தில் உருவாகிய அமைப்பு முறை. மனித சமூகத்தில் குடும்பம் என்னும் அமைப்பு எப்போது தோன்றியது என்பதை காலத்தால் நம்மால் இந்த தேதி, இந்த இடம், இந்த நேரம் என்று துல்லியாமாக கூறமுடியாது. ஆனால் அது ஏன் தோன்றியிருக்க வேண்டும் என்பதை வேண்டுமானால் நாம் அறிந்துக் கொள்ள முடியும். அப்படி அறிந்துக்கொள்ள வேண்டுமாயின் இன்றைய நவீன தொழில்நுட்பமும், தலைமுறை தலைமுறையாய் வளர்ந்து வந்திருக்கும் நம் அறிவுக்களஞ்சியமும் இல்லாத காலத்திற்கு செல்ல வேண்டும்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ஏனெனில், நாம் இன்றைக்கு ஒரு முடிவு எடுத்தால் கூட நாளை அது எப்படி இருக்க வேண்டும் என்று சிந்தித்து எடுக்கிறோமோ, அப்படித்தான் அன்றைக்கும் அவர்கள் நினைத்திருக்க வேண்டும். அன்றைக்கு சமூகத்தில் நிலவியிருந்த ஒரு மாபெரும் தேவையை பூர்த்தி செய்யவே குடும்பம் தோன்றியிருக்க வேண்டும். அத்தேவை இன்றும் நீடிப்பதால் தான் நாம் இன்னும் குடும்பம் என்னும் அமைப்பில் இருந்து வருகிறோம். (இதைப் பற்றி மேலும் படிக்க, ஏங்கல்ஸ் எழுதிய "குடும்பம், தனிச்சொத்து மற்றும் அரசின் தோற்றம்" என்ற நூலை அணுகவும்).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;இது என்றென்றைக்கும் நீடித்து இருக்கும் என்று நீங்களும், நானும் ஆசைப் பட்டாலும், அடம்பிடித்தாலும் அதன் தேவை குறையும் போதோ அல்லது எப்படி சமூகத்தின் அடுத்த பரிணாம வளர்ச்சிக்கு அன்று தேவைப்பட்டதோ, அதேபோல் அடுத்தக்கட்ட வளர்ச்சிக்கு அது முட்டுக்கட்டையாக இருக்கும் பட்சத்தில் அது நீர்த்துபோகும். அது எப்படி தானாக உருவாகி வளரவில்லையோ, அதேபோல் தானாக நீர்த்தும் போகாது. அது உருவானதற்கும், நீர்த்துப்போவதற்கும் ஏற்ற சூழல்களும், சமூகத் தேவைகளும், சமகால சிந்தனைகளும், அதில் இயங்கும் மனிதர்களும் இணைந்து கூட்டாகவே இவற்றை நிர்ணயிக்கின்றன.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;குடும்பம் என்கின்ற அமைப்புமுறை, கடந்து வந்த பண்ணை அடிமை முறை, நிலப்பிரபுத்துவம், மற்றும் நாம் வாழ்ந்துக் கொண்டிருக்கும் முதலாளித்துவம் ஆகிய அமைப்புகளுக்கள் எப்படி வெவ்வேறாக மாறி வந்திருக்கிறது, இதில் ஆண்களின் இடமும், பெண்களின் இடமும் எவ்வாறு மாறி வந்திருக்கிறது, எந்த அமைப்பு முறையில் யாருக்கு ஆதிக்கம் இருந்துவந்துள்ளது போன்ற விவாதம் நாம் அறிந்ததே. அதிலும் இடதுசாரி இயக்கங்களில் தொடக்கம் முதலே இவ்விவாதங்களும், நேற்றைய, இன்றைய குடும்பத்தில் நிலவி வந்துள்ள, வருகின்ற அசம்த்துவத்தையும் அகற்றி எப்படி சமத்துவமான குடும்பத்தையும், சமூகத்தையும் கட்டமைப்பது போன்ற கருத்துக்கள் இங்கே கொட்டிக் கிடக்கின்றன. Alexandra Kollantai எழுதிய "கம்யூனிசமும் குடும்பமும்" (Communism and the Family) என்கிற கட்டுரை ஒரு சிறந்த எடுத்துக்காட்டு.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ஒரு ஆணையும் பெண்ணையும் இணைக்கும் திருமணம் என்னும் ஏற்பாட்டில் இருந்துதான் குடும்பம் என்னும் அமைப்பிற்கு அச்சாரம் போடப்படுகிறது. ஒன்று கூடும் ஆணும் பெண்ணும் மறுஉற்பத்தியில் ஈடுபட்டு அக்குடும்பத்தை உயிர்ப்போடு வைத்திருக்க வேண்டும் என்பதே சமூக விதி. அப்படி வைத்திருக்க வேண்டுமாயின், வாழ்வதற்கு தேவையான பொருள் ஈட்டும் முயற்சியில் ஈடுபட வேண்டும். இந்த இடத்தில் தான் தற்போது நிலவும் அரசியல் பொருளாதாரத்தின் தேவையும், அதன் வளர்ச்சிக்கு சமூகத்தில் உள்ள எந்த விதிகள் உதவுகிறது அல்லது முட்டுக்கட்டையாக இருக்கிறது என்பது தீர்மானிக்கப்படுகிறது. இவை ஒரு சிலரால் தீர்மானிக்கப்படுவதில்லை, ஓரிரு இரவில் மாறிவிடுவதும் இல்லை. இவை அனைத்தும் பண்பாடு மற்றும் கலாச்சார மாற்றங்கள், இவற்றிற்கு மக்கள் தயாராகாமல் யாராலும் இவற்றை நடைமுறைபடுத்திவிட முடியாது.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;இந்த மாற்றத்திற்கு மிகவும் உதவும் ஒரு வடிவம் தான் கலை மற்றும் இலக்கியம். குறிப்பாக சினிமா, நாடகங்கள், பாடல் வரிகள் போன்றவை. இம்மூன்றையும் கூர்ந்து கவனியுங்கள் உங்களுக்கு தானாகவே விளங்கும். நாளைய குடும்ப அமைப்பிற்கு அப்படி ஒரு மாற்றம் தேவை என்பதால் தான் சமீப காலமாக live-in together பற்றி நிறைய படைப்புகள் வெளிவரத் தொடங்கியுள்ளன. இந்திய அளவில் திருமணம் என்றால் பெண் தான் அவள் வீட்டைவிட்டு வெளியேறி, அந்த ஆணின் குடும்பத்தோடு சேர்ந்து வாழவேண்டும் என்ற சமூக விதி இருக்கிறது. பெண் விடுதலை பேச தொடங்கும் யாரும் எழுப்பும் முதல் கேள்வி இதுகுறித்து தான் இருக்கும். அப்படி கேள்வி எழுப்பவதற்கு ஏற்ற சூழலும் உருவாகியிருக்க வேண்டும், உதாரணத்திற்கு பெண்களுக்கு கல்வியறிவு, வேலைவாய்ப்பு, சொத்துரிமை போன்றவை அங்கீகரிக்கப்பட்ட பிறகு தான் இப்படி கேள்வி எழுப்ப முடியுமே தவிர அவை அங்கீகரிக்கப்படாத சமூகத்தில் இக்கேள்விகளை எழுப்ப முடியாது.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;தினசரி வாழ்நாளை எப்படி கழிக்கிறோம் என்பதில் இன்றைய முதலாளித்துவத்தின் பங்கு மிகவும் அதிகம். முதலாளித்துவ பொருளாதாரம் அதன் தேக்கநிலையை கடக்க ஏற்கனவே பல மாற்றங்களை செய்யத் துவங்கி விட்டது. அதன் saturated நிலையிலிருந்து, அடுத்த நிலைக்கு செல்ல யார் அதற்கு உதவுகிறார்களோ அவர்களை மட்டும் வளர்த்தெடுப்பதுதான் venture capital / angel investor backed startups. ஆனால் நிலவி வரும் குடும்ப அமைப்புகளோடு venture capital startups-யும் ஒருசேர வளர்த்தெடுப்பதில் முதலாளித்துவவாதிகளுக்கும் சவாலாக இருக்கிறது. "நான் ஒரு Startup தொடங்கியிருக்கேன், அல்லது தொடங்கப்போகிறேன்" என்று சொல்லும் இளைஞர் இளைஞிகளிடம் அவர்கள் பெற்றோர்களின் எதிர்வினை என்னவாக இருக்கிறது என்று கேட்டுப்பாருங்கள். ஒருசில விதிவிலக்குகள் இருக்கலாம். ஆனால் அவை பொதுவான எதிர்வினையாய் ஆகிவிடாது. குடும்பம் திருமணம் என்று வரும்பொழுது பொருளாதார, சமூக பாதுகாப்புக்கே முன்னுரிமை அளிக்கப்படுகிறது. ஆனால் முதலாளித்துவம் அதன் நெருக்கடியிலிருந்து மீண்டு வர அடுத்த நிலையை அடைய ரிஸ்க் எடுக்கும் ஆட்கள் அதிகம் தேவைப்படுகிறார்கள். இதனாலேயே இந்த முரண்பாடு நிலவுகிறது.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;live-in என்றால் வெறும் காமத்தோடும், உடலுறவுகளோடு மட்டும் சுருக்கிவிட வேண்டாம். அப்படி வேண்டுமானால் அது தோற்றமளிக்கலாம், ஆனால் முற்போக்காக அணுக வேண்டுமென்றால் ஏற்கனவே பெற்றோர்கள் ஓரிடத்திலும், பிள்ளைகள் வேரிடத்திலும் படிக்கவும், வேலை செய்யவும் மறுப்புத் தெரிவிக்காத சமூகம், பெண் வீட்டிற்கு ஆண் போவதா, இல்லை ஆண் வீட்டிற்கு பெண் போவதா என்பதை அவரவர் இருக்கும் இடத்திலேயே இணைந்து துணையாய் வாழ தொடங்குவதாய் எடுத்துக் கொள்ளலாம். ஒரு படைப்பு அதை வெறும் இச்சை தீர்த்துக் கொள்வதாய் சித்தரிக்கலாம், மற்றொரு படைப்பு நுணுக்கமான ஆண்-பெண் உறவு குறித்து அழகாக சித்தரிக்கலாம் (ஓகே கண்மனி). அதற்கு ஏற்ற சூழலும் cosmopolitan நகரங்கள் உருவாகி மெட்ரோ என்கிற அவசரமான, நவீனமான, பிசியான இடம் இல்லாமல் இதுவும் சாத்தியமில்லை. இது இடது, வலது என்று பேரமில்லாமல் இரண்டு தரப்புகளுக்கும் தேவைப்படும் ஒரு மாற்றமாக நான் கருதுகிறேன். குடும்பம் என்கின்ற அமைப்பு காணாமல் போகிறது என்று எடுத்துக்கொள்ளவில்லை, ஆனால் அதில் அமைப்பு ரீதியான மாற்றங்கள் நிகழ்ந்துக் கொண்டிருக்கிறது என்று தான் கூற விரும்புகிறேன்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;பண்பாடு, கலாச்சாரம், கலை, இலக்கியம், பொருளாதாரம், அரசியல், அறிவியல், ஆன்மீகம் இவற்றில் எது எதை தீர்மானிக்கிறது எது முதலில் செயல்படுகிறது என்று நிறுத்திவைத்து பார்க்க இயலாது. இவை அனைத்துமே அனைத்தின் மீதும் தாக்கம் செலுத்துகிறது, அதே நேரம் அவற்றால் தாக்கம் அடைகிறது. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"இவ்வுலகத்தில் எதுவும் நிலையானதும், இறுதியானதும் அல்ல. அனைத்துமே மாற்றத்திற்கு உட்பட்டதே!" &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;இயக்கவியல் பொருள்முதல்வாதத்தின் (Dialectical Materialism) ஒரு விதி.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="சமூகம்"></category><category term="குடும்பம்"></category><category term="பொருளாதாரம்"></category></entry><entry><title>The Left, Religion and Change</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/left-religion-and-change.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-18T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-07-18T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2018-07-18:/blog/left-religion-and-change.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Both the Communists and Anarchists works are centered around the following questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why are there miseries in this world?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What causes these miseries?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can humans be truly human and develop themselves to full potential thus expressing themselves in whatever way they prefer?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the condition of current setup …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Both the Communists and Anarchists works are centered around the following questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why are there miseries in this world?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What causes these miseries?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can humans be truly human and develop themselves to full potential thus expressing themselves in whatever way they prefer?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the condition of current setup we currently live in and how does it prevents us from being human?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to get rid of current situation and transition to next level?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every domain out there in this world, can be brought inside these few questions. That is why both of their works focus on&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Philosophy &amp;amp; Science.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Political Economy and Social Relations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all, but religion also tries to answer most of these questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Religion itself is not bad, but religion that maintains status quo by giving temporary relief through false promises (opium) and a religion that denies equality is bad. Don't forget that it was Lenin who &lt;a href="https://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1905/dec/03.htm"&gt;announced that the citizens should have the freedom to practice religion and it has to be a private affiar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Buddha said, religion should not be centered around the idea of God or the self (soul), but it has to put around humans and the society at it's center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Religion first has to come out of the subject of God. It is in this name of this authority they justify all destructive things and consider them holy or sacred which punishes people when questioned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans need to get rid of the labels of the religion they subscribe to and instead should mix the constructive elements of each religion. Constructive as not to sustain that religion, but constructive towards a free society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is the collective understanding &amp;amp; actions of the people currently living at any given moment that determines the outcome for next century. That is why today's capitalism also wants to control our thoughts and actions by engaging in mass surveillance. It serves 2 purpose for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Controlling our thoughts and actions (consumerism and consent) like how a drug keeps people forget their real sufferings and be in a fantasy world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reproducing itself. Capturing value from our actions and using that capital to reproduce itself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What most people attribute to the failure of communism is actually the experiments of 20th century State Capitalism / State Socialism / Centralization towards State. Just 1 century of experiments and they claim failure. It took 2 centuries for what is today's Capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If one has to stay truly scientific and rational, then one can understand that failure of few experiments doesn't mean the objectives listed cannot be achieved at all, and at the same time, not repeating the mistakes of previous attempts and failures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to re-inventing itself, Anarchists have been very open to new experiments and practices. This is where the traditional communists (20th century communists in today's context) needs to catch up.
This is also the reason why I find anarchists critique on the traditoinal left to be meaningful. If I have to take a stand on what principles I subscribe to, it would be &lt;strong&gt;Anarcho-Communism&lt;/strong&gt;, because the objectives of both anarchism
and communism are same, and the anarchists methods are lively (federation, solarpunks, cyberpunks, etc.,)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supporting Capitalism doesn't make you a Capitalist. On the contrary opposing capitalism makes you Anti-Capitalist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For More Detailed reading&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;http://theoriesofmarxism.pen.io/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://roarmag.org/magazine/anti-capitalist-politics-21st-century/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>On Microsoft Acquiring GitHub</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/microsoft-github-gitlab.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-09T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-06-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2018-06-09:/blog/microsoft-github-gitlab.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Richard Mathew Stallman (RMS) who is widely known as the founder of Free Software Foundation (FSF) and GNU is Not Unix (GNU) project, wrote an email [1] to GNU mailing list 3 years back, asking developers not to use GitHub for hosting their source code and instead asks them to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Richard Mathew Stallman (RMS) who is widely known as the founder of Free Software Foundation (FSF) and GNU is Not Unix (GNU) project, wrote an email [1] to GNU mailing list 3 years back, asking developers not to use GitHub for hosting their source code and instead asks them to find a better alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why did he say that? Because, is he some kind of prophet who knows that Microsoft will acquire a platform like GitHub in the future? No! The primary contradiction in this case is that, Github which started as a platform to help developers of Free/Libre &amp;amp; Open Source Projects itself is neither a Free Software nor Open Source Software!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they started attracting various FOSS communities including Mozilla, The Linux Kernel (maintains their mirror there), etc., All of the sudden, it become a place for developers to figure out FOSS projects, start contributing and host their own. I remember reading an article on CNET titled, "Forget LinkedIn, Companies turn to Github to find Tech Talent"[2] back in 2012. A developers profile on GitHub along with their contributions towards public projects was valued (and still being) more than the information that they have provided in their Resume when they applied to software development jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even a company like Google, who had their own code hosting platform [3], had shutdown it's service and moved some of their projects to GitHub as well. There was even a popular trend among developers who understood that FOSS is empowering their skills and knowledge started ignoring tools or services which are proprietary and comes from organizations that promote proprietary software rather than a FLOSS. This in-turn created another trend among the companies who started publishing some of their projects source code under a FLOSS license and wanted to stay alive among developers. It's a strategic move by these companies based on market conditions and not based on the principles or philosophy behind FLOSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It includes Microsoft as well! Back in the early 2000-2001 Microsoft's Steve Ballmer called GNU/Linux and the Free Software ecosystem as Cancer and even attributed the nature of GNU GPL to Communism! [4]. And 12 years later, they ridiculed themselves being one of the Top 20 contributors to the Linux kernel itself! [5] The market trends started changing in those decades. The Internet, Web and FLOSS had grown together. It was evident that the connectivity the Internet and Web provided had brought developers together crossing national boundaries and changed the way they develop and produce software. From that point, software production was in a sense democratized that they are no longer constrained within the walls of tech corporations but was out in the open. Soon after this another trend started emerging in the name of Cloud Computing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to keep pace with the fast changing domain, Microsoft and similar companies had to restrain from their previous stands. The market forces compelled them for a change. Soon after Satya Nadella was made CEO of Microsoft he made announcements like "Microsoft Loves Linux". This announcement again comes in the background of Microsoft's launching of it's own cloud platform called Azure where GNU/Linux was the primary operating system demanded by developers who operate in the cloud. Steve Ballmer, once again came out and said "I may have called Linux a cancer but now I love it" as quoted in ZDNET[6].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the sudden Microsoft started embracing Open Source (not Free Software) not because of the principles again, but because of the demand by capital and market conditions for profit and for their survival. Today, Microsoft has announced that they are acquiring the proprietary source code hosting and development platform GitHub and more than surpise, it had come as shock to a lot of developer communities. The developers seems to be disappointed and worried about this move and it was evident by the trended hashtag #movingtogitlab on Twitter [7] and Fediverse [8]. Gitlab is an FLOSS alternative to GitHub and developers started migrating to it as reported by GitLab [9].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were also creative memes that was trending [10]. It was also mentioned that GitHub has been valued at $7.5 billion in this acquisition and GitHub said they are happy about it. "They" here refers to the board members, venture capitalists and angel investors. They are happy about it while the developer community is raging aginst this move. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should be raising few questions on this moment. What would attract another company to acquire another companies product, if not for the value they see in? If it has a value, who and what had created that value? Is it just the developers and marketting folks at GitHub (or) is that the whole developer community who have their accounts and actively developing software in GitHub? Would a company buy a product of another company at higher price if there were no active users? If both the developers who built the platform and the users (in this case are also developers who uses the platform) are those who brought such value for this product, then it is certainly beaurocratic and undemocratic that their consents have never been sought and when it happens, the other side rages and starts their counter action. Moving to Gitlab is a political stance by the developer community. It is their way of resisting back. The developer community should have listened to the early warnings of RMS and shouldn’t have chosen a proprietary platform for development and hosting of FLOSS projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the past records and u-turns of Microsoft why would the community trust them, no matter how much they come in disguise? The Free Software movement is a bottom-up movement with the principles of Freedom at it's core, while the changes happening in these top tech companies are top-down and they both clash with each other. Because the top-down management can any time will make another u-turn if the capital profit and the market conditions demands them to do so. Therefore they cannot be trusted and the alternative lies on building a decentralized &amp;amp; federated solutions to these centralized platforms. The hacker and developer community needs to stay vigilant about the moves of these monopolies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from GitLab, Gogs, Gitea, GitTorrent and git-ssb are other examples for alternatives. Seek alternatives, if there is none, build many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://lists.gnu.org/archive/html/discuss-gnustep/2015-12/msg00168.html&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://www.cnet.com/news/forget-linkedin-companies-turn-to-github-to-find-tech-talent/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://opensource.googleblog.com/2015/03/farewell-to-google-code.html&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://www.theregister.co.uk/2000/07/31/ms_ballmer_linux_is_communism/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://www.theregister.co.uk/2012/04/03/microsoft_linux_kernel_contributions/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://www.zdnet.com/article/ballmer-i-may-have-called-linux-a-cancer-but-now-i-love-it/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://twitter.com/hashtag/movingtogitlab&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://mastodon.social/tags/movingtogitlab&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://about.gitlab.com/2018/06/03/movingtogitlab/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://twitter.com/cdrrazan/status/1003419271563628544&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="proprietary"></category><category term="microsoft"></category><category term="gitlab"></category></entry><entry><title>Books Read &amp; Reading</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/book-list.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-15T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-04-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2018-04-15:/blog/book-list.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h4&gt;In Progress&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;History, Society and Land Relations (Selected Essays)&lt;/strong&gt;, E.M.S. Namboodaripad, Leftword Publishers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Frontline Years Selected Essays&lt;/strong&gt;, E.M.S. Namboodaripad, Leftword Publishers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anarchism&lt;/strong&gt;, Daniel Guerin, Aakar Books&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building Alternatives&lt;/strong&gt;, T.M. Thomas Issac, Leftword Publishers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;இந்திய நாத்திகம் (Indian Atheism)&lt;/strong&gt;, தேப …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h4&gt;In Progress&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;History, Society and Land Relations (Selected Essays)&lt;/strong&gt;, E.M.S. Namboodaripad, Leftword Publishers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Frontline Years Selected Essays&lt;/strong&gt;, E.M.S. Namboodaripad, Leftword Publishers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anarchism&lt;/strong&gt;, Daniel Guerin, Aakar Books&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building Alternatives&lt;/strong&gt;, T.M. Thomas Issac, Leftword Publishers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;இந்திய நாத்திகம் (Indian Atheism)&lt;/strong&gt;, தேபிபிரசாத் சட்டோபத்யாயா (Debiprasad Chattopadhyaya)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;History of Indian Philosophy - Volume I&lt;/strong&gt;, Surendranath Dasgupta, &lt;a href="https://www.wisdomlib.org/hinduism/book/a-history-of-indian-philosophy-volume-1"&gt;Online&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lokayata: A Study in Ancient Indian Materialism&lt;/strong&gt;, Debiprasad Chattopadhyaya, &lt;a href="https://archive.org/download/LokayataAStudyInAncientIndianMaterialismDebiprasadChattopadhyaya/"&gt;Online&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weapons of Math Destruction&lt;/strong&gt; - Cathy O' Neil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Buddha's Way to Human Liberation&lt;/strong&gt;, A socio-historical approach, Nalin Swaris, Navayana Publications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Finished Reading&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DD Kosambi - Adventures Into The Unknown (Essays)&lt;/strong&gt;, Edited by Ram Ramaswamy, Three Essays Collective&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Principles of Communism, Friedrich Engels&lt;/strong&gt;, Online &lt;a href="https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1847/11/prin-com.htm"&gt;en&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.marxists.org/tamil/marx/1847/prin-of-com.htm"&gt;ta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annihilation of Caste&lt;/strong&gt;, Dr. B.R. Ambedkar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ten Days that shook the world (உலகை உலுக்கிய அந்த 10 நாட்கள்)&lt;/strong&gt;, John Reed, Bharathi Puthagalayam&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;எது நமக்கான குடும்பம்?&lt;/strong&gt;, பாரதி புத்தகாலயம்&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;பெண் ஏன் அடிமையானாள்?&lt;/strong&gt; (Why Were Women Enslaved?), பெரியார் (Periyar), திராவிட கழகம் வெளியீடு (Dravida Kazhagam)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why I am An Atheist?&lt;/strong&gt;, Bhagat Singh, Online &lt;a href="https://www.marxists.org/archive/bhagat-singh/1930/10/05.htm"&gt;en&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Interested in Reading&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breaking the spell of Dharma and other essays: A case for Indian Enlightment&lt;/strong&gt;, Meera Nandha, Three Essays Collective&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="books"></category></entry><entry><title>What Did I Learn From Free Software Movement?</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/learnings-from-fsm.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-21T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-06-21T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2017-06-21:/blog/learnings-from-fsm.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back in 2010-2011, when I was a under-graduate student of computer science, I got introduced to GNU/Linux operating system and then gradually got introduced to the free software movement through &lt;a href="https://fsftn.org"&gt;FSFTN&lt;/a&gt;. Since then, I have been active with the free software movement by doing activism (i.e asking people …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back in 2010-2011, when I was a under-graduate student of computer science, I got introduced to GNU/Linux operating system and then gradually got introduced to the free software movement through &lt;a href="https://fsftn.org"&gt;FSFTN&lt;/a&gt;. Since then, I have been active with the free software movement by doing activism (i.e asking people and helping them to switch to free software by explaining the values underlying it), &lt;a href="https://code.purambokku.me/prashere"&gt;releasing all the code and utility scripts&lt;/a&gt;, that I create, under a free software license.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So with all these activities, I have learned &lt;strong&gt;certain values&lt;/strong&gt; from the free software movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be Inclusive&lt;/strong&gt; - make sure everyone has option to take part in production as well as consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A software is free software, if it's license allows anyone to use, study, modify, distribute or redistribute the code to anyone for any purpose. It invites everyone to use and it doesn't stop there, it even invites them to study and modify the code based on their needs and promotes them to share their modification to others as well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's say we buy a bike. A bike is useless without fuel for it's engine, therefore we need fuel to run bikes. Fuel production is a separate industry on a large scale by itself. We cannot produce fuel with bike, we can only consume or use fuel with bike. If we substitute bike for a computer here, then a computer hardware is also useless without a software. If software is the fuel for computer hardware, then software is both produced and used in computers. The means used to produce and use are the same. This invites a new question, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Why can't a user with a knowledge or a user with a friend who has knowledge on how to study and modify the software is unable to do so for their own computer?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is, we are able to do, but the proprietary software distributors have written their license that doesn't allow users to do so, instead puts a chain of dependency around the neck of the users.
&lt;img alt="" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/65/Roman_collared_slaves_-_Ashmolean_Museum.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By separating software production and software usage it has built an exclusive system. Free Software is trying to liberate users by breaking these chains and invites everyone to produce as well. It is designed to be inclusive. It doesn't restrict people from a particular race or gender or religion or caste or color or whatever from contributing to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collective progress &amp;gt; Individual Progress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is pretty straight-forward. In a group of people, if only one of them gets access to a resource, then all others have to depend on that one individual. Now that individual, based on their morals and values, may or may not exploit the others for their own profit. In case of collective progress, everyone gets access to the resource and everyone collectively frames a guideline on how to utilize and manage a resource. This is how any free software project is developed, initially a community is formed around it and based on their contribution and suggestions bugs are fixed, new features are added and this in turn used by everyone benefits everyone. Mailing lists, forums, irc channels, bug trackers, pull requests, this is how the community self-organizes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When contribution is to the collective, the resource should be managed as a commons&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drawing from the first two values of inclusiveness and collective progress, the outcome of such production cannot become a private property. The non-permissive free software licenses like GNU GPL, AGPL, etc., provides legal protection to the software produced in this manner from being appropriated or enclosed by private ownership. Similarly creative commons and PPL are doing the same for digital artistic creations like Music, Articles (wikipedia), Pictures, Videos, Audio, etc., This is why, I see permissive licenses as counter-forces which takes us back to the old system at the same time appropriating all the values created by the commoners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commons &amp;gt; Private Property&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commons as a social product promotes collaboration whereas private property promotes egoism and individual greed and thus exploitation. Private property pitches one individual against the other. This competition becomes more intensive and barbaric as the population grows. In this case, if people didn't bring resources under commons, then this inevitably leads to exploitation of one another. i.e one's cost of living depends on one's cost of suffering under private property regime. This is already true with wealth inequality &amp;amp; income inequality. It is this private property (specifically, Intellectual Property rights) that free software is questioning and proposes commons based organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Innovations doesn't rely on monetary benefits&lt;/strong&gt;, rather innovations are driven by necessity to overcome certain limitations. For example, when centralized infrastructure of a website or a webservice is prone to single point of failure or power abuse like fb or twitter, people come up with interesting solutions like &lt;strong&gt;decentralized&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;p2p alternatives&lt;/strong&gt; like torrents, &lt;a href="join-scuttleverse.html"&gt;ssb-patchwork&lt;/a&gt;, GNU social, diaspora, OStatus, Rumble, which are all free software or open protocols. It may or may not be later appropriated by private property regime like how skype was once p2p and then back to centralization again. For democratic control &amp;amp; ownership, distributed software run by different collectives is the way forward. And in order for the software to be run by different collectives, it has to be in commons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;privacy&lt;/strong&gt; for everyone cannot be guranteed by private property, instead it can only be guarenteed by being inclusive. When we have private property regime, we have competition among eveyrone to acquire the property for exclusive access, this automatically brings an insecure feeling about the future. What if someone steals or damages my property? Therefore, property owners promotes surveillance. In case of softwares, there is no way to make sure that a proprietary software spy or doesn't spy on you, because users have no access to the source code. It is a blind trust. With free software, access to the source code reveals any such malware practices and since free software also allows modification, anyone can get rid of such practices and can ensure security and privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now all these values of software production comes into conflict with the existing model. It is bascially a transition towards a commons oriented production. But the existing system based on private property, especially the contemporary owners of private property will not allow this transition to pass through easily. They will engage in all sorts resistance for the sake of their own profit and privilige in this system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A change proposed in how production happens, also demands a change in economy. This is how production, economy, politics and society are all inter-related. We need to transition to &lt;a href="http://p2pfoundation.net/"&gt;commons based peer production&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for the sake of our species and our planet, especially when the current system is polluting everything.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="free software"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="tech"></category><category term="Internet"></category></entry><entry><title>Join Scuttleverse</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/join-scuttleverse.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-18T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-06-18T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2017-06-18:/blog/join-scuttleverse.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;People are already speaking and writing about what is &lt;strong&gt;Scuttlebot&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Scuttleverse&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Patchwork&lt;/strong&gt;. If you have not read them or heard them or tried them already, you can explore the following links,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://staltz.com/an-off-grid-social-network.html"&gt;An Off-Grid Social Network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://theinitialcommit.com/2017/04/04/dominic-tarr/"&gt;An Interview with Secure-Scuttlebutt's Dominic Tarr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://softwareengineeringdaily.com/2017/05/26/off-grid-social-network-with-andre-staltz/"&gt;Audio Podcast - Off Grid Social Network with Andre …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;People are already speaking and writing about what is &lt;strong&gt;Scuttlebot&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Scuttleverse&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Patchwork&lt;/strong&gt;. If you have not read them or heard them or tried them already, you can explore the following links,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://staltz.com/an-off-grid-social-network.html"&gt;An Off-Grid Social Network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://theinitialcommit.com/2017/04/04/dominic-tarr/"&gt;An Interview with Secure-Scuttlebutt's Dominic Tarr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://softwareengineeringdaily.com/2017/05/26/off-grid-social-network-with-andre-staltz/"&gt;Audio Podcast - Off Grid Social Network with Andre Staltz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My intention in this post is to get you started with all these. Don't worry, it's going to be a cake-walk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download &lt;a href="https://github.com/ssbc/patchwork/releases/latest"&gt;Patchwork&lt;/a&gt; (if you are using GNU/Linux, right click the downloaded &lt;code&gt;AppImage&lt;/code&gt; file -&amp;gt; properties -&amp;gt; permissions -&amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;tick&lt;/code&gt; Allow executing file as program) and double click to start.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Edit your profile on the first run.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Join My Pub - paste the following invite code by clicking on &lt;strong&gt;Join a Pub&lt;/strong&gt; in patchwork. &lt;code&gt;pub.purambokku.me:8008:@hoLKNJ54bWYEFEnkUe2Mo7VdQfMbXCaJ/Pc1zrvHh/M=.ed25519~WdHOY+V+EqF1r1pEynaIYZsnhiMdJK+gZhVWspN5gNo=&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the invite code doesn't work or expired or invalid, do comment here, I will help you join.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="free software"></category><category term="Internet"></category><category term="networks"></category><category term="tech"></category><category term="web"></category></entry><entry><title>Learnings From Building Offline First Web App</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/offline-first-coops-map.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-24T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-04-24T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2017-04-24:/blog/offline-first-coops-map.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote a web app recently. The purpose of the web app is to map the &lt;strong&gt;cooperatives&lt;/strong&gt; around us. I'll speak about the intentions behind it in another post, for now let us focus on the &lt;strong&gt;Offline First&lt;/strong&gt;
approach of this app. The application is hosted here &lt;a href="https://prashere.gitlab.io/coop-demo"&gt;live&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Initial Version …&lt;/h3&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote a web app recently. The purpose of the web app is to map the &lt;strong&gt;cooperatives&lt;/strong&gt; around us. I'll speak about the intentions behind it in another post, for now let us focus on the &lt;strong&gt;Offline First&lt;/strong&gt;
approach of this app. The application is hosted here &lt;a href="https://prashere.gitlab.io/coop-demo"&gt;live&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Initial Version&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how I implemented it initially. Since it is a web application, users are going to access the app using web browser, therefore frontend is necessary. Similarly users are also going to mark/add new
coops to the map and this has to be stored somewhere. So taking a traditional web app approach, I have decided to write a backend in python which would receive data entered by users in frontend, process
them and store them in a database (preferred sqlite).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/traditional-client-server.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Frontend (client)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;html (defines the structure)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;css (for defining styles)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;js (handle user events like placing marker in the map and making XHR requests to talk with the backend server to store and retrieve data).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Backend (server)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;flask (a python based micro web framework)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sqlite3 (for storing and retreiving data)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So what does this traditional design mean?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The frontend depends on the availability of the backend to work. Without backend part the frontend part becomes useless. This is true for all traditional client/server web application and
this also means &lt;strong&gt;centralization&lt;/strong&gt; and therefore &lt;strong&gt;Single Point of Failure (SPoF)&lt;/strong&gt;. In case, if the data is lost at the server side either accidentally or intentionally, the data is lost forever and
all those user contributions are gone. poof. This is why we call them &lt;strong&gt;SPoF&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/fshm/coops-map/"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the source of the initial implementation in &lt;code&gt;flask&lt;/code&gt; + &lt;code&gt;sqlite3&lt;/code&gt; + &lt;code&gt;frontend&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I strongly believe in distributed, decentralized and peer-to-peer design practice, because these design practices empowers users and participants instead of the one who hosts it, for users and participants
are those who create values for themselves, while the one who hosts the application and data treats users as commodities and also appropriates the value created by users for their profit.
This is nothing short of labor theft. It's a classical problem inherent to capitalism and it's predecessors. i.e &lt;strong&gt;Who creates value and Who enjoys the fruits of the labour?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Provoked by this thought, I have been experimenting, studying and using various p2p and decentalized designs in whatever I come across. Therefore, it is natural for me to look for an alternative model
of this application. That is when I came across principles like &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://offlinefirst.org/"&gt;Offline First&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://nobackend.org/"&gt;noBackend&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://unhosted.org/"&gt;unHosted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moment I started to explore them is like... (I am falling short of words here to express), because of the movement world-wide and there are people with similar thoughts have demonstrated the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Offline First Version&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Offline First, noBackend and unHosted are all design principles. While digging deeper into these design principles a lot of Free Software and Open Source hacktivists were already developing frameworks and
libraries based on these principles. Among those, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="hood.ie"&gt;hoodie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.kinto-storage.org/"&gt;kinto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://remotestorage.io/"&gt;remoteStorage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; are worth mentioning. I started with
&lt;code&gt;hoodie&lt;/code&gt; but since it is not well documented at the moment, I found it difficult to put it to use and then I jumped into &lt;code&gt;remoteStorage&lt;/code&gt; and then eventually  settled with &lt;code&gt;kinto&lt;/code&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;Mozilla&lt;/strong&gt; since it is
very well documented right from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://prashere.gitlab.io/coop-demo"&gt;live&lt;/a&gt; version that you saw above is actually the offline first version written with the help of &lt;code&gt;kinto&lt;/code&gt;. This is how it the offline-first version is organized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/offline-first.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Frontend&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;html (defines the structure)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;css (defines styles)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;js (handles user events &amp;amp; XHR)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IndexedDB (a key, value JSON like data store within browser itself, which means data can be stored &amp;amp; retrieved on user's devices itself, Whoa!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Backend&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kinto-server (server side storage)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point you might be wondering, when data can be stored and retreived locally without backend or server, why did we store data at server side too. This is to allow synchronization of data to various
devices as well as to various users globally over the Internet. It depends on what your app tries to achieve. In our case, we need a site that is accessible over web where anyone can visit and take a look
at the coops marked already or can contribute by adding new coops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point here is that there is no single point of failure. Due to offline first approach, the data is stored on user devices. Even if the backend goes off or the data is lost at server side, users still
have the data with them. This data independence also open news possibilities like allowing users to choose their backend servers or go completely offline. &lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/prashere/coops-map-offline-first"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; 
is the source of the offline first implementation. When you look at it, it is a static web application with just html, css and js.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested with this approach, do explore the above design principles, libraries, frameworks as well as in-browser features like &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Service_Worker_API/Using_Service_Workers"&gt;Service Workers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; 
and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/IndexedDB_API/Using_IndexedDB"&gt;IndexedDB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/Apps/Fundamentals/Offline"&gt;This documentation&lt;/a&gt; from mozilla developer networks explains the offline workflow.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="code"></category><category term="Internet"></category><category term="tech"></category><category term="web"></category><category term="free software"></category></entry><entry><title>Self Hosting Guide - Part 1</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/self-hosting-guide.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-11T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-02-11T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2017-02-11:/blog/self-hosting-guide.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Quoting my own words from my &lt;a href="hello-world.html"&gt;very first post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can always move the site to other providers / host my own, if I at some point needed to abandon github (it's already a proprietary platform).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I am, self-hosting my blog and &lt;a href="https://code.purambokku.me"&gt;code&lt;/a&gt; as well. When I use the word …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Quoting my own words from my &lt;a href="hello-world.html"&gt;very first post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can always move the site to other providers / host my own, if I at some point needed to abandon github (it's already a proprietary platform).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I am, self-hosting my blog and &lt;a href="https://code.purambokku.me"&gt;code&lt;/a&gt; as well. When I use the word &lt;strong&gt;self-hosting&lt;/strong&gt;, I mean it. The server is sitting in a room at the place where I live currently connected to an ADSL Modem + Router which is in turn connected to Internet via my Internet Service Provider (&lt;strong&gt;ISP&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image of orangepi pc" src="http://files.linuxgizmos.com/orangepipc_angle.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Requirements&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;computer with GNU/Linux operating system&lt;/strong&gt; that has to run 24x7. When it has to run 24x7 think about power consumption. You don't need a GUI component to run a server, therefore get rid of Monitors or external displays. You can use it to setup, but beyond that avoind using a display. A SoC (System on Chip) like &lt;strong&gt;Raspberry Pi&lt;/strong&gt; (or) &lt;strong&gt;Beaglebone Black&lt;/strong&gt; (or) &lt;strong&gt;Orange Pi PC&lt;/strong&gt;, etc., can do well. I have mine setup using Orange Pi PC.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;Web Server&lt;/strong&gt; (or) a reverse proxy like &lt;strong&gt;Nginx&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Apache&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;httpd&lt;/strong&gt; to serve the applications on the Web through Internet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;DSL/ADSL modem&lt;/strong&gt; with support for &lt;strong&gt;port forwarding&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;DHCP IP Reservation for LAN&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dynanic DNS client&lt;/strong&gt; like &lt;strong&gt;ddclient&lt;/strong&gt; to install in the server so as to update the &lt;strong&gt;DNS&lt;/strong&gt; records everytime your public IP address changes. Our home connections often do not get static IP address instead our IP addresses are dynamic, which means there is no guarentee that I will get the same IP address tomorrow. IP address are required to reach any computer on Interent, if my IP address keeps on changing everyday or after every few hours, how would my friends or others on the Internet knows that it has changed to new address? This is where DDNS comes in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An &lt;strong&gt;account on DDNS service&lt;/strong&gt; like &lt;a href="https://nsupdate.info"&gt;nsupdate&lt;/a&gt; (or) &lt;a href="https://freedns.afraid.org"&gt;freeDNS&lt;/a&gt;. nsupdate is completely free to use, while freeDNS has a free plan as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Domain Name&lt;/strong&gt; (optional). A name for your site can be purchased from domain registrars like bigrock or godaddy or namecheap etc., This is completely optional. If you can't afford to buy a domain name (or) if you decide you don't need a domain name, both nsupdate and freeDNS provides subdomains. It is like some people would have purchased a domain name and then added it to freeDNS or nsupdate like how I have added &lt;strong&gt;purambokku.me&lt;/strong&gt; to freeDNS and also allow others to create a subdomain using this domain for them. Like for example, you can create yourname.purambokku.me or using any public domain name. This is more or less a gift economy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Cost of Self-Hosting (approx.)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Am not including the cost of modem + Internet connection here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.crazypi.com/single-board-computers-india/orange-pi-india/orange-pi-pc-india"&gt;Orange Pi PC&lt;/a&gt; - Rs. 2000/-&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RJ45 Ehternet Cable 1 - usually around Rs.70-100/-&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Class 10 32Gb MicroSD card 1 - Rs. 600-800/-&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Domain Name (optional) - starting from Rs. 70/-&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from optional domain name, the above are one time cost, not something like paying monthly rent to someone. In the next part, I will be writing about preparing your computer for self-hosting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="networks"></category><category term="Internet"></category><category term="data"></category></entry><entry><title>கொரில்லா ஓப்பன் ஆக்சஸ் அறிக்கை</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/guerilla-open-access-manifesto.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-20T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-01-20T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2017-01-20:/blog/guerilla-open-access-manifesto.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.aaronsw.com/"&gt;Aaron Swartz&lt;/a&gt; published &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://archive.org/stream/GuerillaOpenAccessManifesto/Goamjuly2008#page/n0/mode/2up"&gt;Guerilla Open Access Manifesto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; back in 2008 when he was alive. This is my attempt to translate the english version to Tamil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;தகவல் அறியும் உரிமை என்பதும் ஒரு வித அதிகாரம். அனைத்து அதிகாரங்களைப் போலவ …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.aaronsw.com/"&gt;Aaron Swartz&lt;/a&gt; published &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://archive.org/stream/GuerillaOpenAccessManifesto/Goamjuly2008#page/n0/mode/2up"&gt;Guerilla Open Access Manifesto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; back in 2008 when he was alive. This is my attempt to translate the english version to Tamil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;தகவல் அறியும் உரிமை என்பதும் ஒரு வித அதிகாரம். அனைத்து அதிகாரங்களைப் போலவும், இதை பெற்றிருக்கும் ஒரு சிலர் அந்த அதிகாரத்தை தங்களுக்குள் வைத்துக் கொள்ள விரும்புகிறார்கள். இந்த உலகின் ஒட்டுமொத்த அறிவியல் மற்றும் கலாச்சார பாரம்பரியம் தொடர்பான புத்தகங்களும், இதழ்களும் தொடர்ந்து தனியார் நிறுவனங்களால் அதிக அளவில் எண்மருவியாக்கம் (டிஜிட்டல் வடிவில் மாற்றம்) செய்யப்பட்டு அவர்களிடம் சிக்குண்டுக் கிடக்கிறது. அறிவியலின் சிறந்த ஆராய்ச்சிகளின் முடிவுகளையும் அதன் ஆராய்ச்சி முறைகளையும் படிக்க வேண்டுமா? அப்படியானால் ரீடு எல்சீவியர் (Reed Elsevier) போன்ற தனியார் வெளியீட்டாளர்களுக்கு பெருந்தொகையை கட்டணமாக செலுத்து வேண்டும் முதலில்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;இந்த அவல நிலையை மாற்ற சிலர் போராடுகின்றனர். அதில் ஒன்று தான் ஓப்பன் ஆக்சஸ் (Open Access) இயக்கம். ஓப்பன் ஆக்சஸ் மூலம் ஒரு விஞ்ஞானி அல்லது ஆராய்ச்சியாளர் தனது உழைப்பின் பலனாக உருவாக்கிய ஆவணத்தின் பதிப்புரிமையை மொத்தமாக இந்த தனியார் வெளியீட்டாளர்களிடம் எழுதிக் கொடுக்காமல், இணையத்தில் அனைவராலும் இலவசமாக பதிவிறிக்கம் செய்யக் கூடிய வகையில் பதிவேற்றம் செய்யலாம். இது அனைத்தும், புதியதாக வெளியிடும் ஆவணங்களுக்கு மட்டுமே பொருந்தும். ஏற்கனவே, தனியாரிடம் சென்றுவிட்ட ஆவணங்களுக்கு இது பொருந்தாது என்பதால், பல இலட்சம் ஆவணங்கள் இதுபோல் சிக்குண்டுக் கிடக்கின்றன. இவை அனைத்தையும் மீட்டெடுக்க நாம் கற்பனை செய்து பார்க்க முடியாத அளவிற்கு பெருந்தொகையை செலவிட வேண்டும். அது சாத்தியமற்றதும் கூட.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ஆராய்ச்சியில் ஈடுபடுவோர், தன் சக ஆராய்ச்சியாளரின் முடிவுகளைப் படிக்க பணம் கட்டச் சொல்லி கட்டாயப்படுத்துதல் நியாயமானதா? ஒட்டுமொத்த நூலகத்தையும் எண்மருவியாக்கம் செய்து பின் கூகுளில் இருப்போருக்கு மட்டும் அனுமதி வழங்குதல் நியாமா? வளர்ந்த நாடுகள் என்று கருதப்படும் நாடுகளிலுள்ள மேட்டுக்குடி பல்கலைக்கழகங்களுக்கு அனுமதி வழங்கி, வளர்ந்துவரும் அல்லது மூன்றாம் தர நாடுகள் என்று கருதப்படும் நாடுகளில் உள்ள மாணவர்கள், ஆராய்ச்சியாளர்கள், பல்கலைக்கழகங்களுக்கு ஆவணத்தை அணுகும் அனுமதி மறுக்கப்படுவதை நாம் எவ்வாறு ஏற்றுக் கொள்வது?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"எனக்கு புரிகிறது, ஆனால் நாம் என்ன செய்ய முடியும்? இந்த தனியார் நிறுவனங்கள் பதிப்புரிமையை தங்களிடம் தக்கவைத்துக் கொண்டு அதன் மூலம் பெரும் தொகையை இலாபமாக சம்பாதிக்கின்றனர். அதுவும் சட்டபூர்வமாக. இவர்களை தடுக்க நம்மிடம் ஒன்றுமில்லை.", என்று பெரும்பாலானோர் சொல்கின்றனர். நம்மால் முடியும் என்கிறேன் நான். நாம் ஏற்கனவே அதை செய்துகொண்டும் இருக்கிறோம். நம்மால் இவற்றை மீட்டெடுக்க முடியும்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;இந்த தனியார் வெளியீட்டாளர்களிடம் சிக்குண்டு கிடக்கும் ஆவணங்களுக்கு அணுகல் பெற்றுள்ள மாணவர்கள், நூலகர்கள் மற்றும் ஆராய்ச்சியாளர்களே, உங்களுக்கு இந்த சிறப்புரிமை வழங்கப்பட்டுள்ள இதே நேரத்தில் உலகின் பல பகுதியுள்ள மக்கள் அணுகல் கிடைக்காமல் அறிவொளியற்ற இருட்டறையில் பூட்டப்பட்டிருக்கின்றனர். தார்மீக ரீதியில் உங்கள் மனசாட்சி உங்களை கேள்வி கேட்குமானால் நீங்கள் பெற்றுள்ள இந்த சிறப்புரிமையை நீங்கள் உங்களோடு மட்டும் வைத்திருக்க தேவையில்லை. இந்த அவல நிலையை மாற்ற நீங்கள் இந்த உரிமையை பிறருக்கும் பகிர வேண்டும். இந்த அணுகலுக்கான கடவுச்சொல்லை உங்கள் சக நண்பர்களோடு பகிர்ந்திருப்பீர்கள் அல்லது அவர்களுக்காக நீங்கள் பதிவிறக்கம் செய்து கொடுத்திருப்பீர்கள். உங்களுக்கு கிடைக்கும் வாய்ப்பைப் பயன்படுத்தி அதில் உள்ள ஓட்டைகளையும் கண்டறிந்து அவ்வப்போது ஒரு சிலருக்கு மட்டும் கிடைத்துள்ள இந்த சிறப்புரிமையை உடைக்க முயற்சி செய்கிறீர்கள். ஆனால் இம்முயற்சிகள் அனைத்தும் இருட்டில் நடப்பது போல் யாருக்கும் தெரியாமல் நடந்துக்கொண்டிருக்கிறது. தலைமறைவாக செய்வதுபோல் உள்ளது.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;இந்நிறுவனங்கள் யாவும் அறிவுசார் சொத்துரிமை என்னும் பெயரில், 'பைரசி' என்ற சொல்லாடல் மூலம் நம்முடைய இச்செயல்களை திருடர்களுக்கு, கொள்ளையர்களுக்கு இணையாக ஒப்பிடுகின்றனர். அறிவைப் பெருக்கும் இந்த ஆவணங்களை பகிர்தல் என்பது எப்படி திருட்டு அல்லது கொள்ளையோடு ஒப்பிட முடியும்? பிறரோடு பகிர்தல் என்பது சமூக விரோத செயல் அல்ல, மாறாக பகிர்தல் என்பது மனிதனின் தவிர்க்கவியலாத ஓர் தார்மீக குணமாகும். பேராசையினால் கண்கள் கட்டப்பட்டவர்கள் தான் இது போன்ற பகிர்தலை மறுக்க முடியம். பெரும் கார்ப்ரேட் நிறுவனங்களின் பேராசை அவைகளின் கண்களை குறுடாக்கியுள்ளது என்பதில் துளியும் சந்தேகத்திற்கு இடமில்லை. இந்நிறுவனங்களை இயக்கும் விதிகளுக்கு பேராசை அடிப்படை தேவையாகிறது, எனவே அதன் பங்குதாரர்கள், முதலீட்டாளர்கள் இந்த மாற்றத்தை விரும்பமாட்டார்கள். ஒரு சில அரசியல் பிரதிநிதிகளை விலைக்கு வாங்கி அவர்கள் மூலம் இவர்களின் இயக்க விதிகளை பொதுச்சட்டமாகவும் மாற்றுகின்றனர்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;அநியாயம் செய்வதில் யாரும் நியாயம் கற்பிப்பது ஏற்கமுடியாது. அதுபோல அநீதியான சட்டங்களை பின்பற்றுவதில் எந்த நீதியும் இருக்க முடியாது. இந்த அநீதியான சட்டங்களுக்கும் விதிகளுக்கும் கீழ்படியாமல், ஒத்துழைப்பு அளிக்காமல் நாம் இருட்டிலிருந்து வெளிச்சத்திற்கு வரவேண்டும். அனைவருக்கும் பொதுவான அறிவு சார்ந்த பொது கலாச்சாரத்தை கையகப்படுத்தி பூட்டி வைக்கும் இந்நிறுவனங்களை எதிர்க்கும் நமது நிலைப்பாட்டை வெளிப்படையாக, பகிரங்கமாக தெரிவிக்க வேண்டும்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;எங்கெல்லாம் அறிவுசார்ந்த ஆவணங்கள், தகவல்கள் பூட்டப்பட்டிருக்கிறதோ வாய்ப்பு கிடைக்கும் பொழுது அவற்றையெல்லாம் நாம் பிரதி எடுத்து இணையத்தில் இவ்வுலகத்தோடு பகிர வேண்டும். பதிப்புரிமை காலாவதியாகிப் போன அல்லது பொதுவுடைமை ஆக்கப்பட்ட ஆவணங்கள், புத்தகங்கள், இதழ்கள் என அனைத்தையும் நாம் எடுத்து இணைய காப்பகத்தில் (https://archive.org) இணைக்க வேண்டும்.  இரகசியமாகப் பூட்டப்பட்டிருக்கும் தரவுகளை வாங்கி இணையத்தில் இணைக்க வேண்டும். அறிவியல் இதழ்கள், புத்தகங்கள், ஆராய்ச்சி முடிவுகளை பதிவிறக்கம் செய்து அவற்றை டொரன்ட் (Torrent) போன்ற கோப்புகளை பகிரும் பிணையத்தில் சேர்க்க வேண்டும். ஓப்பன் ஆக்சஸ் கொரில்லா யுத்தத்தை நாம் நடத்த வேண்டும்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;உலகம் முழுவதும் நம்மைப் போன்றோரின் இச்செயலால், அறிவு என்பது தனியுடைமை ஆக்கப்படுவதை எதிர்ப்பது மட்டுமின்றி அது ஒரு பழங்கதையாக்கி புது சரித்திரம் படைப்போம். நீங்களும் இதில் பங்கெடுப்பீர்களா?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ஆரோன் ஸ்வாட்ஸ், ஜூலை 2008, எரேமோ, இத்தாலி&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="education"></category><category term="Internet"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="proprietary"></category><category term="web"></category></entry><entry><title>Whispering Pictures - Beware</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/privacy-pictures.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-01T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-01-01T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2017-01-01:/blog/privacy-pictures.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the english version of the &lt;a href="https://fsftn.org/blog/pesum-pugaipadangal-gavanam/"&gt;tamil post&lt;/a&gt; that I wrote for &lt;a href="https://fsftn.org/blog"&gt;FSFTN's blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We come across a lot of new people throughout our life. There is a reason we call them strangers. Not everyone wins our trust and vice-versa. We don't reveal much about ourselves to those strangers …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the english version of the &lt;a href="https://fsftn.org/blog/pesum-pugaipadangal-gavanam/"&gt;tamil post&lt;/a&gt; that I wrote for &lt;a href="https://fsftn.org/blog"&gt;FSFTN's blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We come across a lot of new people throughout our life. There is a reason we call them strangers. Not everyone wins our trust and vice-versa. We don't reveal much about ourselves to those strangers. We try to be more cautious about what information we reveal to them. This is what we call our &lt;strong&gt;Privacy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Privacy is the ability of an individual or group to seclude themselves, or information about themselves, and thereby express themselves selectively. - &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privacy"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever we talk about privacy, many people tend to think it in terms of &lt;em&gt;secrecy&lt;/em&gt;. While secrecy is more about the information whereas privacy is more about the ability of one's control over that information. Though they both are different, they both go hand in hand with each other most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There goes a song in Tamil cinema which is quite popular,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's take a selfie pulla...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this selfie cultured digital world around us, the need to take privacy seriously arises naturally. Usage of smartphones, laptops and DSR/DSLR camera have become quite common these days. We also know that all these devices are controlled by the software that are already inside those devices. It can be the firmware (or) the operating system (or) the application itself. One such module of these software is called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exif"&gt;EXIF&lt;/a&gt; which stands for &lt;strong&gt;EX&lt;/strong&gt;changeable &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;mage file &lt;strong&gt;F&lt;/strong&gt;ormat. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EXIF defines a lot of properties like the size of the image, dimension, name and model of the device used, date and time of the picture taken, location where this picture was taken (if GPS is enabled and the application has the ability to get location from GPS), whether flash was fired or not when the picture was taken, etc., believe me, there are &lt;a href="http://exiv2.org/tags.html"&gt;a lot of such data&lt;/a&gt; that can be embeded along with that awesome selfie / photograph that we shoot everyday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We think, we are just taking pictures, but most of us aren't aware of the fact that all these so called &lt;em&gt;smart devices&lt;/em&gt; also collect and embed a lot of other sensitive information with our pictures. You don't have to even believe what I am saying. You can try it yourself with this page that I built for demonstrating the same &lt;a href="https://prashere.gitlab.io/exifdata/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the above demonstration, the more &lt;em&gt;undefined&lt;/em&gt; you see, the more happy you can be, because those informations are not present with your pictures. Here is one example that I tried myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image of a fan" src="https://fsftn.org/blog/content/images/2016/12/20161228_162446.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What information can you extract from the above image? Yes, you are right. It's a ceiling fan and the fan is functioning. What else can you know?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="screenshot of fan with exif metadata" src="https://fsftn.org/blog/content/images/2016/12/with_geolocation.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh crap! This photograph seems to reveal a lot than what we thought! The location of where this picture was taken, the deivce used, date and time, whether flash used or not is also visible. Using these information we can also know that the person who shoot this photograph was using this particular device and this fan and the person was at that particular location on that particular date and time! and yeah the flash did not fire ;) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now what happens when I upload this to social networks (umm, I'll be specific, yeah facbeook)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="screenshot of the same image uploaded to facebook" src="https://fsftn.org/blog/content/images/2016/12/facebook_exif.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at this. Facebook retrieves the location and date from these pictures. A lot of such services on the web are waiting for us upload our data and build a profile around us and then sell it to third-party agencies for their profit. Even if we remove (or) edit, there is no way for us to make sure that those informations are actually removed from fb's server. This is how our privacy is compromised at a lot of stage. Remember, our intention was just to share a selfie or photograph that we just took, not any other information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine how much selfies and photograph of our family and friends we shoot and share it in Web! Most liberal minded people would easily say, &lt;em&gt;hey! you are ignorant and it's your mistake that you are not aware of such things&lt;/em&gt;, well I would rather say &lt;em&gt;No. It's not our mistake&lt;/em&gt;, because the software is proprietary in most of the case, we do not even know what the software does in the background and there is no way to know what else the software does when the source code is not available. Moreover, you and I didn't ask for such a feature and also we don't have the freedom to modify the source code under a proprietary regime. That is why we as a movement (Free Software movement) call for the adoption and usagae of &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.en.html"&gt;Free(dom) Software&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the proprietary software controls the device, it means the creator of the proprietary software is in indirect control of your device. It also means your device is not in your control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what can we do about this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;re-configure your smartphone and other smart devices that has camera in it, so that they don't embed these information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;remove sensitive metadata from your pictures before uploading or sharing it with others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GNU/Linux users can install a tool named &lt;a href="http://mat.boum.org/"&gt;MAT - Metadata Anonymisation Toolkit&lt;/a&gt; which is also a &lt;em&gt;free software&lt;/em&gt;. This software cleans our image of any such harmful metadata.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don't find any such free software EXIF removers for Windows (may be because, I don't use windows and so I don't find a need to search for it).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are some EXIF editors and removers for Android at Play Store. (again they are proprietary and I don't recommend them, for they can be harmful too).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no such EXIF editors / removers for Android in F-droid. (as far as I have searched).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;don't use the &lt;strong&gt;take picture&lt;/strong&gt; option directly from the social network and instant messengers app on your smartphone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid using proprietary softwares and apps. free yourself by using a free software operating system like GNU/Linux.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not arguing against EXIF metadata, I am arguing for the case of user's privacy. The application and the ecosystem should be designed in such a way that a user has the control over their digital activity, for it is their data that this ecosystem is making use of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: By the end of January 2017 (26, 27, 28 &amp;amp; 29) the 2nd National Conference and Convention of Free Software Movement of India is set to happen at Chennai, Tamilnadu, India. This conference and convention will be discussion topics ranging from privacy, software freedom, commons, community networks, programming, etc., The confernce is named as &lt;a href="https://4ccon.fsmi.in"&gt;4CCon&lt;/a&gt;. Students, academicians, researchers, software experts, Internet activists, free software hacktivists, social activists are participating. You are also invited. Do visit the site and register yourself if you are interested.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="privacy"></category><category term="code"></category><category term="free software"></category><category term="tech"></category><category term="web"></category></entry><entry><title>நாம் தேர்ந்தெடுக்காத போட்டி</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/comp-coop.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-30T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-11-30T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2016-11-30:/blog/comp-coop.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;ஒரு குழந்தை பிறந்த உடன் அதனை சுற்றியிருக்கும் ஒவ்வொருவரும் அதன் வரவை கொண்டாடுகின்றனர். அக்குழந்தை பிறக்கும் போது, அதற்கு இயற்கையை புரிந்த …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;ஒரு குழந்தை பிறந்த உடன் அதனை சுற்றியிருக்கும் ஒவ்வொருவரும் அதன் வரவை கொண்டாடுகின்றனர். அக்குழந்தை பிறக்கும் போது, அதற்கு இயற்கையை புரிந்துக் கொள்ள தெரியாது, கண்களை உருட்டி உருட்டி பிரம்மிப்போடும் ஆச்சர்யத்தோடும் இந்த பொருள்வயப்பட்ட உலகை முதன் முதலில் காண்கிறது. நாட்கள் செல்ல செல்ல மெதுவாக அதன் பெற்றோர் அதற்கு ஒவ்வொன்றாக கற்றுக் கொடுக்கின்றனர்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;இதில் முக்கியமானது, அக்குழந்தைக்கு கற்பிக்கப்படும் அனைத்தும் அதனை கற்றும் கொடுப்போரின் புரிதலிலிருந்தே வருகிறது. அதனால் தான் கடவுள் நம்பிக்கையின் மீதான என்னுடைய முதல் வாதம், அது அவர்களின் விருப்பம் இல்லாமலே, புரிதல் இல்லாமலேயே அதன் மீது திணிக்க்பபடுகிறது என்பது. மதம், சாதி, இனம், மொழி இப்படி அனைத்துமே தான் தேர்ந்தெடுத்ததல்ல என்பதை உணர நெடுங்காலம் தேவைப்படுகிறது அக்குழந்தைக்கு (அதுவும் சரியான வழிகாட்டுதல் இருந்தால் மட்டுமே).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;பள்ளிக்கு செல்லும் பருவம் வரும் பொழுது, சில குழந்தைகள் அழுகிறது. சில குழந்தைகள் மிகவும் மகிழ்கிறது. அழுவதற்கு காரணம், புதிய சூழல், புதிய மனிதர்கள் என்ற பயம். மகிழ காரணமும் அதுவே தான். தன் வயதை உடைய பலரை சந்திக்கப்போகிறோம், புதிய நண்பர்கள், புதிய விளையாட்டுகள், கூட்டாக சேர்ந்து நேரத்தை செலவிடுதல் என்ற மகிழ்ச்சி ஒரு சில குழந்தைகளிடம். புதிய நண்பர்கள் தன்னை ஏற்றுக் கொள்வார்களா? தன்னையும் விளையாட்டில் இணைத்துக் கொள்வார்களா இல்லை ஒதுக்கி விடுவார்களா என்கின்ற பயம் ஒரு சில குழந்தைகளிடம்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;தனிமைப்படுத்துதல் என்பது எவ்வுளவு கொடூரமானது என்பது அக்குழந்தைக்கு மிக நன்றாக யாரும் விளக்காமலேயே அதற்கு புரிகிறது. ஏனெனில், மனிதன் ஒரு சமூக விலங்கு. எதையும் கூட்டாக செய்வதே அதற்கு சிறப்பு. ஒரு பள்ளியின் முக்கிய கடமை இவ்வாறு பயத்தோடு இருக்கும் குழந்தைகளின் பயத்தையும் தயக்கத்தையும் சிறிது சிறிதாக தகர்த்து அனைவரோடும் பழக வழி வகுக்க வேண்டும் (பாலின பாகுபாடு இல்லாமல்). அனைத்து குழந்தைகளுக்கும் கூட்டுறவு மற்றும் கூட்டு முயற்சியின் பலன்களை புரிய வைக்க வேண்டும்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;அப்படி இல்லாமல் வணிகமயமாகிப்போன தனியார் பள்ளிகளின் ஆதிக்கத்தில் பள்ளிக் கூடம் என்பது ஒரு தொழிற்சாலை அல்லது இராணுவ கிடங்கு போலவும், குழந்தைகள் தொழிலாளிகள் அல்லது இராணுவ வீரர்கள் போல் கட்டளைகளை பின்பற்றுபவர்களாக மாற்றப் படுகிறார்கள். ஏற்கனவே அச்சத்தில் இருக்கும் குழந்தைக்கு இது மேலும் அச்சத்தைக் கூட்டுகிறது. மகிழ்ச்சியாய் வந்த குழந்தைக்கு ஏமாற்றம் அதிர்ச்சியளிக்கிறது.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;இக்குழந்தைகள் ஒன்றாக இணைந்து கூட்டுமுயற்சியின் மூலம் ஒருவருக்கொருவர் கற்றுக் கொடுத்தல், இலக்கை அடைதல் என்பதற்கு பதிலாக, முதன் முதலில் இவ்விடத்தில் இவர்களுக்குள் போட்டி உருவாக்கப்படுகிறது. நீ அதிக மதிப்பெண் எடுத்து முதலில் வர வேண்டும் என்கிற கருத்து திணிக்கப்படுகிறது. இக்குழந்தைகள் நாம் அனைவரும் போட்டி போடத்தான் பள்ளிக்கு வருகிறோம் என்று சேர்த்து விடும் பொழுது நினைத்தார்களா? அல்லது போட்டியில் கலந்து கொள்ள விருப்பம் கேட்கப் படுகிறதா? இப்படித்தான் நீயும், நானும், நாம் தேர்ந்தெடுக்காத ஒரு போட்டிக்குள், தள்ளப்படுகிறோம்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10th, 12th மட்டும் கஷ்டப்பட்டு படிச்சுட்டனா, அதுக்கப்பறம் காலேஜ் லைஃப் ஜாலி தான்&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;இந்த வாக்கியத்தை கேட்டிறாதவர் யாரும் இருக்க முடியாது. கல்லூரி படிப்பில் தற்போது இருப்பவர்களுக்கும் சரி, முடித்தவர்களுக்கும் சரி, அவ்வாக்கியத்தின் உண்மை தன்மை மிக நன்றாகவே தெரியும். இப்போட்டி கல்லூரியிலும் தொடர்கிறது. ஆனால் மதிப்பெண்களை காட்டிலும் வேலைவாய்ப்புக்காண போட்டியே இங்கு அதிகம். &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"வேலை கிடைச்சாச்சுனா லைஃப் செட்டில்" &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;என்று கல்லூரி ஆசிரியர்கள் முதற்கொண்டு அனைவரும் சொல்லியிருப்பார்கள். பாவம் அந்த கல்லூரி ஆசிரியர்கள், அவர்களுக்கு கிடைத்த வேலையிலேயே அவ்வுளவு போட்டி, பொறாமை, ஈகோ பிரச்சனைகளை ஒருவொருக்கொருவர் வைத்துக் கொண்டு நமக்கு கீதா உபதேசம் செய்கிறார்கள்!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;வேலை கிடைத்துவிட்டால் அதை தக்க வைத்துக் கொள்ளப் போட்டி. தக்க வைத்துக் கொண்டால் அடுத்த படிநிலைக்கு பயணிக்கப் போட்டி. வேலை கிடைக்காதவர்கள் தனிமைப் படுத்தப் படுகிறார்கள். தனிமைப்படுத்துதல் என்பது ஒரு குழந்தைக்கே தெரியும் எவ்வுளவு கொடுமையானது என்று. அதனால் தான் வேலை கிடைக்காமல் இருப்பவர்கள் தனிமையாக உணர்கிறார்கள். இது அவர்களின் தவறே இல்லை. இப்படி வாழ்க்கை முழுவதும் தான் தேர்ந்தெடுக்காத, ஒப்புக்கொள்ளாத ஒரு போட்டியிலும், போட்டியின் விதியையும் பின்பற்றி என்ன தான் சாதிக்கிறோம்? இயற்கையில் மனிதன் ஒரு சமூக விலங்கு எனில், கூட்டுமுயற்சிக்கு பதிலாக ஏன் தனிமனித அடையாளத்திற்குள் சிக்கி போட்டி, பொறாமை என்று அடுத்தவரை மட்டம் தட்டி கீழே தள்ளி, எட்டி உதைத்து ஏணியின் உச்சியில் ஏறுகிறோம்? கூட்டுமுயற்சி தோற்றுவிட்டதா?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;நிச்சயம் இல்லை. கூட்டுமுயற்சிக்கு இடமே அலிக்காமல், ஒருவருக்கொருவர் நேர் எதிராக நிறுத்தி வைக்கப்பட்டு களத்தில் போட்டி போட வைக்கும் விதியின் கீழ் கட்டப்பட்டுள்ளது. இவ்விதிகளுக்கு நம்மிடம் ஓப்புதல் கேட்கப்படுவதில்லை, விதிகளை மாற்ற நமக்கு அதிகாரமே கொடுக்கப்படவில்லை. &lt;strong&gt;Discipline&lt;/strong&gt; என்ற பெயரில் கட்டளைகளை கேள்வி கேட்காமல் ஏற்கும் இயந்திரங்களாக மாற்றப்படுகிறோம். இவற்றையெல்லாம் யார் செய்கிறார்கள்?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;உங்களிடம் கேட்டால் உங்கள் ஆசிரியர்கள், தலைமை ஆசிரியர், மேனேஜர் மற்றும் முதலாளியின் பெயர்களை சொல்வீர்கள். இவ்விதிகள் அனைத்து இடத்திற்கும் பொருந்துகிறது. அடிப்படையில் பள்ளியில் தொடங்கி வேலை அல்லது தொழிலில் முடியும் இந்த விளையாட்டிற்கு, விதிகளை கட்டமைப்பவர்கள் நம் கண்களுக்கு குறிப்பாக பள்ளி பருவத்திலும், கல்லூரி பருவத்திலும் தெரியவே மாட்டார்கள். வேலை பருவத்தில் இந்த "&lt;strong&gt;Invisible Hand&lt;/strong&gt;" என்பவர்களை கூட பல நேரங்களில் அடையாளம் காண்பது கடினம், ஏனெனில் அவர்கள் விதிகளை உருவாக்கி நமக்குள் மோதலை உருவாக்கிவிட்டு வெளியே நின்று பார்க்கிறார்கள். தொழிலில் சென்று முடியும் இந்த விளையாட்டில், பணியிடங்களுக்குச் சாதகமான, கேள்விக் கேட்காத, மிகச் சிறிதளவு கூட்டு முயற்சியுடன் (அதுவும் அவர்களுக்கு தேவையான அளவு மட்டும்) கட்டளைகளை அப்படியே பின்பற்றுகிற நபர்களே தேவை. அவர்கள் எங்கிருந்து வருகிறார்கள்? ஒவ்வொரு தலைமுறையிலிருந்தும் வருகிறார்கள். அப்படியானால், ஒரு தலைமுறை உருவாகும் போதே நமக்குத் தேவையான பணியாளர்களை உருவாக்குவதே சிறந்த திட்டம் என்று சப்தமில்லாமல் உருவாக்குவது இந்த முதலாளி வர்க்கமே. தன் வர்க்க நலன்களை பாதுகாக்க அது ஏற்படுத்தியுள்ள விதிகள் தான் இவை.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;சற்று சிந்த்தித்துப் பாருங்கள் கூட்டு முயற்சியின் மூலம், மனித மாண்புகளை இழிவு படுத்தாமல், யாரையும் தனிமைப்படுத்தாமல், என் சொத்து, உன் சொத்து என்று சண்டையிடாமல், அனைவருக்கும் பொதுவான இந்த பூமியை, இயற்கையை கூட்டாக பயன்படுத்துவதில், பாதுகாப்பதில், நம் தேவைகளை பிறர் உதவியோடும், பிறர் தேவைகளை நம் உதவியோடும் பூர்த்தி செய்து கொள்வதில் என்ன சிக்கல் இருக்கிறது? நமக்கான விதிகளை நாம் தான் உருவாக்க வேண்டும். அதுவும் கூட்டு முயற்சியின் மூலம். #Cooperatives #Commons #Communes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;இந்த வரிசையில் Paulo Friere எழுதிய &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/72657.Pedagogy_of_the_Oppressed"&gt;Pedagogy of the Oppressed&lt;/a&gt; என்னும் புத்தகத்தை நீண்ட காலமாக படிக்க வேண்டும் என்று என் காத்திருப்புப் பட்டியலில் இன்னும் காத்துக் கொண்டிருக்கிறது.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="books"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>தெரிந்தும் தெரியாமலும்</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/aandavan-kattalai.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-13T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-10-13T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2016-10-13:/blog/aandavan-kattalai.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"ஏதாவது படத்துக்கு போகலாமா?" &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;என்று என் அண்ணனிடம் கேட்டேன். &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"டேய்.. நானே கேட்கலாம்னு நெனச்சுட்டு இருந்தேன்"னு &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;பதில் சொன்னான். &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"சரி, என்னென்ன படம …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"ஏதாவது படத்துக்கு போகலாமா?" &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;என்று என் அண்ணனிடம் கேட்டேன். &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"டேய்.. நானே கேட்கலாம்னு நெனச்சுட்டு இருந்தேன்"னு &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;பதில் சொன்னான். &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"சரி, என்னென்ன படம் ஓடிட்டு இருக்கு-னு பாரு. போகலாம்" &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;என்றேன். சொல்லி முடிப்பதற்கு முன்பாகவே கையில் இருந்த தன்னுடைய ஸ்மார்ட்ஃபோனை எடுத்து தேய்த்துக் கொண்டிருந்தான். தேடும் படலத்தில் என்னையும் இணைத்துக் கொண்டேன்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"ரெமோ, இருமுகன், ஆண்டவன் கட்டளை..." என்று படத்தின் பெயர்களையும் அவற்றின் மதிப்பீடு எண்களையும் வாய்விட்டு சொல்லியவாரே  கடந்து கொண்டிருந்தான். நான் அவனிடம் கேட்டேன், நீ கடைசியாக பார்த்த படம் என்னவென்று, உடனே அவன் &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"டேய் நா படம் பாத்து ரொம்ப நாள் ஆச்சுடா, கடைசியா கபாலி தான் நா பாத்தது. அங்க (பெங்களூர்ல) காவிரி சிக்கலால, தமிழ் படம் எதுவுமே தேட்டர்ல ஓடல டா" &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;என்றான். &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"ஆண்டவன் கட்டளை போலாமா?" என்றேன். &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;உடனே ரேட்டிங் பார்த்து,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"நல்ல ரேட்டிங் தான்" &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;என்றான்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"நான் ஏற்கனவே பாத்துட்டேன், இருந்தாலும் நீ பாக்கலல... அதனால அந்த படத்துக்கு போரதுனா போகலாம்" &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;என்றேன். அவனும் சரி என்று உடனே புக் பண்ணிட்டான். &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;சமீபத்தில் மனநல மருத்துவர் ஷாலினி அவர்களின் ஒரு நேர்காணலை பார்க்க நேர்ந்தது. அதில் தமிழில் வெளியாகும் கமெர்ஷியல் சினிமா மற்றும் மாஸ் அல்லது அதிரடி நாயகர்களின் திரைப்படம் எப்படி பெண் அடிமை கருத்துக்கள் மற்றும் பாலியல் சீண்டல்களை கையாளுகிறது என்பதைப் பற்றி சிறப்பாக பேசியிருந்தார்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bHF00-FKwTg" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ரெமோ போன்ற படங்கள் அதற்கு விதிவிலக்கல்ல என்பதை படம் வெளிவந்த நாளே சிலருடைய பதிவை பார்த்தவுடன் புரிந்துக் கொள்ள முடிந்தது. எனவே, இருந்த பட்டியலில் எடைப் போட்டு பார்க்கும் போது, ஆண்டவன் கட்டளையை நான் பரிந்துரை செய்தேன்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://www.facebook.com/plugins/post.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2Fnelsonxavier08%2Fposts%2F10207292531219553&amp;width=500" width="500" height="161" style="border:none;overflow:hidden" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" allowTransparency="true"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe src="https://www.facebook.com/plugins/post.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2Fvikram.sundarraman%2Fposts%2F10154648735041522&amp;width=500" width="500" height="618" style="border:none;overflow:hidden" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" allowTransparency="true"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;அரசு சேவைகளை பெற இடைதரகர்களை அணுகுவது மூலம் ஏற்படும் பாதிப்புகள், சொந்த ஊரை விட்டு சென்னைக்கு தங்கள் உழைப்பை மூலதனமாக கொண்டு வரும் இளைஞர்கள் வாடகைக்காக வீடு தேடி அலையும் படலம், நாளுக்கு நாள் அதிகரித்துக் கொண்டே போகும் அத்யாவசிய பொருட்களின் விலை ஆகியவை பற்றி மக்களுக்கு எடுத்துச் சொல்ல வேண்டும் என்பது தான் படத்தின் மையம் என்றாலும், அதில் வரும் நாயகி கலாச்சார பெண் என்ற அடிமைக் கருத்துக்களை உடைத்தெரியும் ஒருவராக வந்திருக்கிறார். வேற யாரு... &lt;strong&gt;இறுதி சுற்று&lt;/strong&gt;-ல தெரிக்க விட்ட ரித்திக்கா சிங் தான். &lt;strong&gt;வாழ்க ஒரு ஒட்டகம், யாரோ பெத்த புள்ள, இம்சை ராணி&lt;/strong&gt;னு ஆரம்பிக்கும் மூன்று பாடல்களையும் திரும்ப திரும்ப கேட்டாலும் நல்லா இருக்கு.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;படத்தை முதலில் பார்க்க வேண்டும் என்ற எண்ணம் வந்ததிற்கு காரணம் என்னுடைய நண்பன் &lt;a href="https://joindiaspora.com/u/nisharthsibi"&gt;Nisharth&lt;/a&gt;. ஒரு நாள், என்னுடைய இரு சக்கர வாகனத்தில் சென்றுக் கொண்டிருந்தபோது இப்படத்தை பார்த்ததாகவும், அதைப் பற்றி எனக்கு சொன்னான். அவன் சொன்னதில், &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"படத்துல ஒரு இலங்கை தமிழர் ஒருத்தரையும் காமிச்சாங்க. அவரோட குடும்பத்த தொலச்சிட்டு தேடுவாரு. இப்படியெல்லாம் கஷ்டப் படுத்தினா.. போராளிகள் உருவாகாம என்ன பண்ணுவாங்க?" &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;என்று அழுத்தமாக அவன் சொன்னதே இப்படத்தை பார்க்க வேண்டும் என்று தோன்றியது. பார்த்தேன்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PY2sEuriqLM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"&lt;strong&gt;நேசா... ஒரு பாட்டு ஒண்ணு பாடு&lt;/strong&gt;" என்று எங்கே தான் பேசினால் இவர் இலங்கை தமிழர் என்று தெரிந்து விடுமோ என்பதற்காக ஊமையாக நடிக்கும் இவரிடம் யோகி பாபு கேட்க.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"&lt;strong&gt;மன்னிச்சுக் கொள்ளுங்கள் அடா... உங்களை ஏமாத்தனம் என்று நான் ஊமை போல் நடிக்க இல்ல. என்ட குடும்பத்த கண்டுபிடிக்கிறதுக்காகத்தான் நான் நடிச்சன். நான் ஶ்ரீலங்கன், யுத்த காலத்துல பெஞ்சாதியும் மகளும் நானும் அங்கிருந்து தப்பிச்சி, போட்டு மூலமா தமிழ்நாட்டுக்கு வந்தம். வந்த அன்னைக்கே ரெண்டு பேரையும் துலச்சி போட்டன். இன்றைய நாள் வரைக்கும் தேடிக் கொண்டிருக்கன்... இன்னும் கிடைக்க இல்ல. நாங்களே அகதிகள், நாங்கள் கம்ப்ளெயின் பண்ணி போஸ்டர் அடிச்சு. ம்ஹூம்... போலீசு பிடிச்சால் அகதி முகாமில் போட்டுவிடினும்&lt;/strong&gt;" என்று காரணம் கூறும் நேசனின் முகம் என் கண்ணையும் மனதையும் விட்டு விலக மறுக்கிறது.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://silverscreen.in/wp-content/gallery/sep-2016/aandavan-kattalai-movie-stills/aandavan-kattalai-movie-stills-0011.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;அதே போல் இறுதியில், போலீசிடம் மாட்டிக்கொள்ளும் நேசன், விஜய் சேதுபதியை அழைத்து தன்னுடைய மனைவி குழந்தையுடன் தான் எடுத்துக் கொண்ட புகைப்படத்தை கொடுத்து, "&lt;strong&gt;என்றைக்காவது இந்த பெஞ்சாதி பிள்ளைகள பாத்த நீ என்றால் நான் தேடிக் கொண்டிருத்தன் என்று சொல்லு.. என்ன?&lt;/strong&gt;" என்று கண்ணீருடன் இருவரும் அணைத்துக் கொண்டு ஒரு சிறு புன்னைகையோடு காட்சியிலிருந்து நம் கண்களிலிருந்தும் மறைந்தாலும் மீண்டும் நம் மனம் அவரை மறக்க மறுக்கிறது.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://maattru.com/%E0%AE%87%E0%AE%A4%E0%AF%81-%E0%AE%A8%E0%AE%AE%E0%AE%95%E0%AF%8D%E0%AE%95%E0%AE%BE%E0%AE%A9-%E0%AE%AA%E0%AF%8B%E0%AE%B0%E0%AF%8D-%E0%AE%85%E0%AE%B2%E0%AF%8D%E0%AE%B2/"&gt;இலங்கைத் தமிழராக இருந்தாலும், காஷ்மீரியாக இருந்தாலும் இவர்களை வாட்டி வதைக்கும் அரசுகள்&lt;/a&gt; தங்கள் பயங்கரவாத செயல்களை நிறுத்தாத வரையில் போராளிகள் ஏன் உருவாகிறார்கள் என்கிற கேள்விக்கு விடை தெரிந்தே நாம் விடை தெரியாதது போல் சுற்றிக் கொண்டிருக்கிறோம்.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="movie"></category><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Podcast 2 - Free Software Introduction</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/podcast-2.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-20T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-09-20T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2016-09-20:/blog/podcast-2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://archive.org/embed/fs-intro-tamil" width="500" height="30" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="true" mozallowfullscreen="true" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href="https://archive.org" href="_blank"&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt; for providing space to host the audio. Visit &lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/fs-intro-tamil"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to know more about license of this audio and formats to download.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://archive.org/embed/fs-intro-tamil" width="500" height="30" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="true" mozallowfullscreen="true" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href="https://archive.org" href="_blank"&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt; for providing space to host the audio. Visit &lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/fs-intro-tamil"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to know more about license of this audio and formats to download.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="podcast"></category></entry><entry><title>Podcast 1 - Welcome</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/podcast-1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-14T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-09-14T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2016-09-14:/blog/podcast-1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://archive.org/embed/tamil-podcast-introduction" width="500" height="30" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="true" mozallowfullscreen="true" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href="https://archive.org" href="_blank"&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt; for providing space to host the audio. Visit &lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/tamil-podcast-introduction"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to know more about license of this audio and formats to download.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://archive.org/embed/tamil-podcast-introduction" width="500" height="30" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="true" mozallowfullscreen="true" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href="https://archive.org" href="_blank"&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt; for providing space to host the audio. Visit &lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/tamil-podcast-introduction"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to know more about license of this audio and formats to download.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="podcast"></category></entry><entry><title>P2P File &amp; URL Sharing App on LAN</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/working-on-p2p-file-url-sharing-app.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-08T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-07-08T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2016-07-08:/blog/working-on-p2p-file-url-sharing-app.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the past 1 week, I have been working on a peer-to-peer File and URL sharing app and I have named it as &lt;strong&gt;Transceiver&lt;/strong&gt; (the ability to transmit and receive data). I would like to log the progress of what I have done so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are various reasons, why …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the past 1 week, I have been working on a peer-to-peer File and URL sharing app and I have named it as &lt;strong&gt;Transceiver&lt;/strong&gt; (the ability to transmit and receive data). I would like to log the progress of what I have done so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are various reasons, why I am writing this application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to try and learn how to build cross platform Desktop applications using &lt;a href="http://electron.atom.io/"&gt;electron&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to write a p2p application, since I have been exploring p2p and mesh networking quite often.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Last thing, I needed this application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever I attend meetups and I wanted to share some URLs that I have bookmarked to others, we do this by using some service that runs on Internet. It could be IRC or any Instant Messengers. Sometimes we have even tried using Pidgin + Bonjour (Avahi for GNU/Linux) and that have worked well too. But we have never succeeded file transfer through Pidgin + Bonjour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following is a GIF of what have been done so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style="border: 1px solid black" src="images/transceiver.gif"&gt;&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First thing, it doesn't make sense to send URL links or Files or any data through Internet to a person who is sitting next to me or in the same hall, connected to the same network. The data doesn't need to leave the network in first place and also you don't need to expose to all those centralized services out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second thing, even in such a WLAN (or) LAN, there should be no central server / single point of failure. People should be able to form ad-hoc networks and should be able to communicate. In this sense, this application is serverless and peer-to-peer such that it doesn't need any central server (or) signalling server (like how they have in torrent trackers or webRTC peer connection) to connect to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third thing, it has to be a Free Software. There already exists few of them like D-LAN (Distributed File Sharing on LAN), Lan Messenger, etc., I am just stacking up mine to the list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.zeroconf.org/"&gt;Zeroconf&lt;/a&gt; (also known as Bonjour or Avahi in GNU/Linux) for automatically registering and discovering peers on the same network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://socket.io/"&gt;Socket.io&lt;/a&gt; for end to end socket connection. (I could still make use of socketio to upgrade the connection to webRTC).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electron + nodejs as a cross-platform framework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An instance of this application can act as both server and client at the same time, thus can listen for incoming data and also it can send data to other peers on the network. Since the peers are discovered through zeroconf, their identities are exposed to everyone on the network using this app and thus we are able to eliminate central signalling server here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now the text / URL sharing is complete. I am yet to work on the File transfer part. I am releasing this work under Free Software license (GPL v3) and the source code is hosted on &lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/prashere/transceiver/"&gt;gitlab here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="code"></category><category term="free software"></category><category term="networks"></category><category term="tech"></category></entry><entry><title>Cross Compilation in Go</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/go-cross-compilation.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-06-24T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-06-24T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2016-06-24:/blog/go-cross-compilation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I have started to explore the Go programming language or golang in short. Go is a compiled language which can produce standalone binaries for the go programs, which means the receiver of this binary need not have go compiler and the libraries that this program is dependent installed on …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I have started to explore the Go programming language or golang in short. Go is a compiled language which can produce standalone binaries for the go programs, which means the receiver of this binary need not have go compiler and the libraries that this program is dependent installed on their machine, instead they can just run the binary and the program will be executed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also the same case with C and C++. If you have used GCC (GNU Compiler Collection) then you could have come across something called cross-compilation in gcc. Compilation means converting from source code to binary, while cross compilation means producing binaries that can be used on other target architectures too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I am writing code in my laptop which is running Linux kernel and the cpu &amp;amp; operating system architectures are 64-bit (often represented as amd64 or x86_64). When I compile this source code on my laptop, I will get a binary. I can execute this binary and can also distribute. But the only constraint is this binary is build for 64bit architecture and linux based machines only. Therefore if someone who runs 32bit or ARM based architectures even with Linux kernel, they cannot use this binary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to overcome this, gcc allows developers to do cross compilation. Similarly go compiler also has this feature inbuilt. Here is how we do it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;env GOOS=linux GOARCH=arm go build somefile.go
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the above command, I am setting values for two environment variables GOOS and GOARCH respectively where GOOS is the name of the kernel used in target operating system and GOARCH is the name of the cpu architecture used in the target computer hardware. Succeeding that is the go command to build binary from the source code &lt;code&gt;somefile.go&lt;/code&gt;. It will take few seconds to build the binary, once that is done now the binary can be used to execute the program in the target machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To know the valid and available GOOS and GOARCH values that go accepts, &lt;a href="https://golang.org/doc/install/source#environment"&gt;go here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Producing binaries and distributing them is very good from users usability point of view. It will be convinient for users to just double click on something to see it work (in fact that's how most of them were training through Microsoft Windows). As a free software activist, I appeal that we should also consider the users freedom point of view and give them links to access the source code of the same program that they use in their computer in the binary. The users have the right to know what is being executed in their machines.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="tech"></category><category term="code"></category></entry><entry><title>Marx, Wikipedia &amp; Torrents</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/marx-wiki-torrents.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-06-17T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-06-17T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2016-06-17:/blog/marx-wiki-torrents.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl_Marx"&gt;Karl Marx&lt;/a&gt; - 19th Century Philosopher, Economist, Sociologist, Journalist and an Revolutionary Socialist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; - An Internet encylopedia available in many languages built by people around the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BitTorrent"&gt;BitTorrent&lt;/a&gt; - A Peer-to-Peer file sharing protocol / program that is used by most of the people around the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why did I pick these …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl_Marx"&gt;Karl Marx&lt;/a&gt; - 19th Century Philosopher, Economist, Sociologist, Journalist and an Revolutionary Socialist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; - An Internet encylopedia available in many languages built by people around the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BitTorrent"&gt;BitTorrent&lt;/a&gt; - A Peer-to-Peer file sharing protocol / program that is used by most of the people around the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why did I pick these three? What is so common about these three topics and how are these topics related to each other? For quite sometime, I was reading works based on Marx and was also reading materials that took a marxist approach on analysing the free software and other technologies. It is under this context, I am writing this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Marx &amp;amp; Engels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karl Marx is well known for his work on analysing and understanding &lt;strong&gt;Capitalism&lt;/strong&gt; and is also known for his famous work along with his comrade &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friedrich_Engels"&gt;Friedrich Engels&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1848/communist-manifesto/index.htm"&gt;The Communist Manifesto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. As a sociologist, economist and  philosophers they both had a vision to change the world. That vision echoed in their famous statement,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/From_each_according_to_his_ability,_to_each_according_to_his_needs"&gt;From each according to his ability, To each according to his needs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i.e the society they envisioned will revolve around this central theme where people can contribute something to the commons according to their ability or capacity and they can take back from the commons based on how much they need. Whenever people discuss about communism or socialism they miss this central theme and the discussion always gets diverted to the failure of U.S.S.R and other attempts of 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marx was also right about capitalism that, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"It will take science and technology to greater level in order to increase their productivity and it will do wonders". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And today we are seeing this live all around us and our next generations will continue to see more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now heading to Wikipedia. It is no doubt that Wikipedia has disrupted the knowledge sector, especially the Intellectual Property Rights and Copyrights of the encyclopedia industry. Today Wikipedia is one of the world's largest Digital Commons (i.e belongs to everyone) available and continues to grow into many more projects like Wiktionary, Wikibooks, Wikidata, etc., It is also well known fact that Wikipedia is built by people all around the world. We approach wikipedia whenever we wanted to lookup for something (search engines doesn't matter, all of them point to wikipedia) and if I know about something, I can also contribute back to Wikipedia by creating or editing an existing article. This is exactly the same vision of Marx and Engles, taking what is necessary and giving back based on the ability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Torrents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's focus on Torrents. People using torrents definitely would have encountered these words, "seeding" and "peers". When we download from a torrent file, we look for more peers. Peers are those people who already have these files in their computers. If those peers upload what they have in their computers to other people who wanted to download the same file through this torrent file, then we call this process as seeding and those peers who does seeding are termed as seeders. While we expect more peers during the download, we look for more seeders. Downloading what you need and seeding back what you can!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are just two examples. this is the same case with how a free software is also developed. Of course, one can point out and say "hey, the examples you have pointed out are immaterial things. what about material things?". Indeed they are right, Marx's works were based on 19th century capitalism and even with that he is able to pin-point a lot of things about capitalism beyond his age. We shouldn't miss to see the fact that today Capitalism is also riding on these immaterial stuff which in turn reflects on their material wealth. For mens (Marx &amp;amp; Engels) who have developed their framework based on &lt;a href="https://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/stalin/works/1938/09.htm"&gt;Dialectical Materialism&lt;/a&gt;, they wouldn't be stupid to deal with material stuffs either, for they did not leave any readymade blueprint, rather they left their vision to be carried by the actors of the corresponding age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether the society goes towards dystopia or utopia, we are all collectively responsible for it. So don't stay neutral, pick you side and act.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Internet"></category><category term="networks"></category><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Contradictory Microsoft</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/microsoft-contradiction.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-04-08T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-04-08T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2016-04-08:/blog/microsoft-contradiction.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;At Pondicherry University, we (Computer Science Students) were invited to attend a lecture by someone from Microsoft. My anticipation was that someone is going to promote (or) show-case the products of Microsoft. If this is going to happen, I made sure I have to rip off the evilness of proprietary …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At Pondicherry University, we (Computer Science Students) were invited to attend a lecture by someone from Microsoft. My anticipation was that someone is going to promote (or) show-case the products of Microsoft. If this is going to happen, I made sure I have to rip off the evilness of proprietary culture by raising questions from their End Users License Agreement itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were seated at an auditorium and waiting for the guest to arrive. In the meantime myself and Shaswata (free software activist from West Bengal) were discussing about which questions to fire from their licensing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally a male guest arrived and the professors introduced him to us as one of the youngest man to be at the director level of Microsoft India and gave the chance for him to address us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He shared his experience. To be frank, I felt like reading some self-help tips book, like how to be successful in your life, what is your carrier goal, etc., because he did speak about that. And my thought is, "Why the hell, use MICROSOFT label for this?". Ironically, while pointing out some examples, he used the name of Jack Ma, Steve Jobs and no where he mentioned Bill Gates nor Satya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seems he is from the Consultancy section and no surprise, he spoke about managerial skills. He spoke for about 20 to 25 minutes and gave a chance for us to question him. After some couple of people, I raised my questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Points follow after 'My take' is presented here, but I did not talk there, because more the argument, more people are going to hate and blame me for spoiling the event, after all our university professors want to impress him to bring Microsoft for campus recruitment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Question&lt;/strong&gt;: After Mr. Sathya Nadella took charge as the CEO, we are seeing a lot of FOSS integration into Microsoft,  What's preventing Microsoft from Open Sourcing their entire products?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;His Answer&lt;/strong&gt;: Because we make money out of selling it closed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My take: First of all, the assumption that open sourcing (or) releasing the source code under GPL cannot be used for making money is false. This shows their lack of understanding of the model itself. &lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/selling.en.html"&gt;Selling Free Software is Ok&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Business_models_for_open-source_software"&gt;Business models for FOSS&lt;/a&gt;. Most people have only heard of the terms Open Source software and assume they know everything about it and more incorrectly they equate &lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html"&gt;Free Software&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freeware"&gt;Freeware&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Question&lt;/strong&gt;: Do you think, selling the proprietary software (i.e binary only) is ethical because software code is not material? Let's assume for example, my friend wanted a software binary from me and there is nothing that prevents me from sharing it with him, but the label that we get is "Pirates". Should I share the binary file with my friend or should I risk losing their relationship abiding to the definition of Piracy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;His Answer&lt;/strong&gt;: See, there is no question of ethical or unethical. If someone does something that gradually becomes their livelihood, then people would continue doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My take: Right, I don't disagree about the fact that someone does something can gradually become their livelihood. Still my question is whether that 'something' they do is ethical or unethical. For example, the practice of stealing something from someone is what we call a theft. Theft is universally considered to be an unethical practice. Still someone can have a livelihood by stealing off. So he didn't answer my question, but just tried to beat around the bush. And for the second part regarding piracy, he ignored it. I did not get a answer from that context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://p2pfoundation.net/Why_All_Knowledge_Should_Be_Free"&gt;Proprietary software has been considered to be an unethical practice&lt;/a&gt; by a lot of people at FOSS community. Microsoft today is facing a self-contradictory situation where they support and oppose the practice of FOSS at the same time. Pity!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Question&lt;/strong&gt;: When you spoke to us initially, you said that, everyone should be driven by Curiosity. Now as a Computer Science students, if we had curiosity to look at the source code of windows operating and learn from it and at the same time improve the algorithms, the End Users License Agreement of Windows doesn't allow us to do. Your license puts restrictions on, "Reverse engineering, decompilation or working around technical restrictions". While these restrictions are in effect, how are your products useful for computer science engineers which very well kills these curiosities?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;His Answer&lt;/strong&gt;: See you cannot label that as curiosity. For example, take this wooden work (he pointed at the podium where he stood nearby), you may not be interested in how it was made, but you may be interested with how you can have creative ways of putting this to use. That's how you should see it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My take: I had to laugh myself. He defines what curiosity other people should have. How can someone decide for someone else what they should be curious about? A user can anytime become a developer, provided he had access to the knowledge and tools. Limiting what a user should think or do is nothing but controlling the thoughts of the users itself. I clearly mentioned him that I am posting this question from academics point of view and he gives an explanation from a naive end-users point of view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Immediate Statement&lt;/strong&gt;: I think, in this context an operating system like Linux and the community behind it is more open and democratic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;His Reply&lt;/strong&gt;: Well, there is no doubt about it. Linux is!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Statement&lt;/strong&gt;: Thanks for acknowledging that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally arrived at what I was looking for. In a crowd of around some 60+ people getting this statement from someone at director level of Microsoft, Mission Accomplished!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When FOSS pitches a new mode of production, distribution and consumption inclusive of all, the traditional monopoly giants doesn't want to change and thinks from the same old system. No surprise, why google surpassed microsoft through their Open Source Android Project. This is not to assume Google is not evil. The "Do No Evil" is evil as well. This post is just dedicated to MS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="proprietary"></category><category term="microsoft"></category></entry><entry><title>Learning Basics of Radio Physics for Meshnet</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/learning-basics-radio-physics-meshnet.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-02-12T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-02-12T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2016-02-12:/blog/learning-basics-radio-physics-meshnet.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I don't exactly remember when &amp;amp; by whom I first came across the idea of meshnet, but I do remember the video that inspired me to work towards meshnet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/1tEkyLOh-tY?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From then on, I started to explore more and more links on the web about meshnet and this is how I aggregated …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I don't exactly remember when &amp;amp; by whom I first came across the idea of meshnet, but I do remember the video that inspired me to work towards meshnet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/1tEkyLOh-tY?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From then on, I started to explore more and more links on the web about meshnet and this is how I aggregated the list of various resources, community knowledge base &amp;amp; community meshnet projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of these resources, I consider a book named &lt;a href="http://wndw.net/" target="_blank"&gt;WNDW - Wireless Network in Developing World&lt;/a&gt; to be one of the most important resource. The reason I consider it to be important is because this book is a practical guide to build a wireless network written by field experts covering every basics including radio physics, telecommunication basics, antennnas, networking, installation &amp;amp; maintenance. The digital copy of this book is available under &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/" target="_blank"&gt;CC-BY-SA&lt;/a&gt; and you can download the &lt;a href="http://wndw.net/book.html" target="_blank"&gt;free digital copy&lt;/a&gt; of this book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am finding this book extremely useful and have started learning Radio Physics since the meshnet that we are trying to build is a wireless meshnetwork using 802.11 (Wifi). WiFi signals are electromagnetic radiations (EMR) also known as Radio Signals that operate at 2.4GHz and 5GHz frequency (license exempt bands).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting up meshnet involves setting up wireless nodes, antennas that propogates the signals and in order to do that we need to understand the basics of radio physics not just computer applications &amp;amp; protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any node or host machine has to satisfy certain requirements in order to be able to join a network. These requirements are labelled traditionally as layers like in OSI Layering &amp;amp; TCP/IP Layering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter what layering model, the Physical layer forms the foundation which denotes the signal carrier &amp;amp; the medium of transmission. It is this physical layer that deals mostly with the property of radio physics namely frequency, bandwidth, wavelength, phases, etc., If we proceed without understanding these basics we might end up with a poor network infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="web"></category><category term="meshnet"></category><category term="radio physics"></category></entry><entry><title>The Internet As We Know</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/the-internet-as-we-know.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-02-02T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-02-02T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2016-02-02:/blog/the-internet-as-we-know.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Links for community initiatives, projects, discussion, articles on meshnet are listed at the end of this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internet (இணையம்) as you know is defined as "network of networks". These networks are setup by users and communities. But inter-connecting these networks across street, cities, state, countries and the world …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Links for community initiatives, projects, discussion, articles on meshnet are listed at the end of this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internet (இணையம்) as you know is defined as "network of networks". These networks are setup by users and communities. But inter-connecting these networks across street, cities, state, countries and the world are done by corporations. The corporation could be either a public corporation (driven by Government like BSNL in India) or private corporation (driven by private interests for profit, like Airtel, Reliance, Tata, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corporations who inter-connect these simple networks to global network are called Internet Service Providers (ISPs). There are also small scale ISPs who depend on the large corporations for lines and cover only smaller area (for example ACT in Bangalore &amp;amp; Chennai).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of creating a network is to communicate. This communication could be anything from  simple text message, real time chats, VOIP calls, sharing pictures, videos (or) any digital content. So if I have a network in my place and you have a network in your place, it is based on our interests to decide what to share between ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with the Internet starts here. I have understood 3 major flaws with the current network,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Censorship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mass Surveillance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Violation of Net Neutrality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem 1 (Censorship)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I already pointed out above, "it is based on our interests to decide what to share between ourselves" in a network. Since the ISPs are inter-connecting the networks, they automatically gain a power to decide whether to allow data from one network to reach the other network or not. If I send you anything and you are not able to receive only from me or some specific person, there is a lot of possibility that either the ISP that you are connected to or the ISP that I am connected to is censoring communication, thus preventing us from communicating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not just that, if you are not able to access any website which you have previously visited and you still know it is accessible from other parts of the world, then you can be very sure that your ISP is censoring you from accessing that website (or) content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When ISPs can do censorship, how does this statement of "it is based on our interests to decide what to share between ourselves" is true anymore?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This problem can be overcome by using tunnels like VPN, TOR, I2P, Psiphon, etc., But this doesn't remove the porblem. These are just an workaround. The problems still exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem 2 (Mass Surveillance)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we already have censorship, it's very clear that ISPs can also inspect or read what we are sending to others &amp;amp; the vice-versa (they can also read what we receive). We think our communications are happening only between ourselves, but since ISPs are in the middle of you and me, it means whatever we send &amp;amp; receive is also visible to the ISPs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If ISPs can listen and continuously monitor our communications they can also store it permanently in their servers. This is also true with proprietary web platforms like Facebook, Google, Amazon, etc., This is violation of an user's privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Privacy means whoever owns the data should decide when, where and to whom they should reveal that data (i.e the control is with the user). If ISPs (or) the proprietary platform can gain access to these data which you are actually sending it to your friend or relatives this is what we call surveillance. Instead of targeting suspicious users, if everyone are targetted then we call it as mass surveillance and this is a potential threat to Democrarcy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine a country or a world where everything you do, wherever you go, whoever you meet is monitored or surveilled, would you be the same? Won't the sense of someone monitoring affect your thought process? or how you do things? Is that really you? Are we trying to build a society based on fear instead of mutual consent? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There goes a famous dialogue from the movie &lt;strong&gt;V for Vendetta&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People should not be afraid of their governments. Governments should be afraid of their people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By monitoring (or) surveilling the institutions are enforcing obedience into our minds. Most of us won't even bother to point out the mistakes of institutions, there would be no freedom of speech. Everything will boil down to self-censorship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, like the previous case we can overcome this by protecting our online communications with the use of mathematics &amp;amp; encryption. The problem with the current Internet is that encryption &amp;amp; decryption are not embedded into the design, rather they have become the burden for the users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem 3 (Violation of Net Neutrality)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have seen this a lot in our country. We have seen how Facebook along with Reliance &amp;amp; Airtel  tried to build a walled garden in the name of Free basics (Internet.org) &amp;amp; Airtel Zero. The strategy they followed is termed as differential pricing / zero rating (i.e charging differently for different services like messenger, VOIP, etc., (or) allowing only certain sites registered with them for free). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most important thing to note here is how these mega-corporations tried to manipulate and mislead the people through their platforms. In fact, TRAI (Telecom Regulatory Authority of India) has condemned their act as "Platform Abuse".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above 3 problems are fair enough to destroy the democratic nature and therefore curtain the freedom of the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have identified the problems with the Internet, we need to think about solving these problems and to come up with a network design which will not have these problems in first place. People around the world are already into the research of designing such networks. It's called Mesh Networks. There are various communities online, especially the &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/darknetplan"&gt;darknetplan&lt;/a&gt; subreddit on reddit.com, the &lt;a href="http://hyperboria.net/"&gt;hyperboria&lt;/a&gt; community and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Articles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.wired.com/2014/01/its-time-to-take-mesh-networks-seriously-and-not-just-for-the-reasons-you-think/"&gt;It's time to take mesh networks seriously - Wired.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg21929294.500-meshnet-activists-rebuilding-the-internet-from-scratch"&gt;Meshnet activists rebuilding the Internet from Scratch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussions &amp;amp; Resources&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://discuss.fsftn.org/t/is-internets-centralized-architecture-a-problem/133"&gt;Problems with the Centralized Architecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://discuss.fsftn.org/category/engineering-programming/project-meshnet"&gt;FSFTN Discussion Forum on Meshnet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="discuss.fsftn.org/t/free-the-network-hackers-take-back-the-web/557/"&gt;Free The Network - Documentary on Meshnet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://p2pfoundation.net/Mesh_Networks"&gt;Introduction to meshnet - p2pfoundation.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wirelessafrica.meraka.org.za/wiki/index.php/DIY_Mesh_Guide"&gt;Mesh Guide - Wireless Africa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wndw.net/"&gt;Wireless Networking in the developing world&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://reddit.com/r/darknetplan"&gt;Darknetplan - Mesh community on Reddit.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community Initiatives &amp;amp; Projects&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://thefnf.org/"&gt;The Free Network Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://guifi.net"&gt;Guifi.net - Largest mesh network operating from Spain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://freifunk.net/en/"&gt;Freifunk - free radio networks group operating from Germany&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://project-byzantium.org"&gt;Project Byzantium - A live GNU/Linux distribution to create Ad-hoc mesh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://openwrt.org/"&gt;OpenWRT - Linux distribution for embedded devices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.dd-wrt.com/site/index"&gt;DDWRT - Fork of OpenWRT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://librecmc.org/librecmc/home"&gt;LibreCMC - Libre Embedded GNU/Linux distribution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://disruptedsystems.org"&gt;Rumble - Off the grid, Delay Tolerant Networking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://commotionwireless.net/"&gt;Commotion Wireless Mesh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://metamesh.org"&gt;Metamesh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://seattlemesh.net/"&gt;Seattle Meshnet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nycmesh.net/"&gt;NewYork Meshnet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="portlandmeshnet.org"&gt;Portland Meshnet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="networks"></category><category term="Internet"></category><category term="meshnet"></category></entry><entry><title>Do You Have A URL?</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/revolt-against-free-basics.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-12-19T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2015-12-19T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2015-12-19:/blog/revolt-against-free-basics.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;1. Do I have a (web)site / blog?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, I do. You are reading it and also I have some other blogs too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. Can you access it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answer 1: &lt;strong&gt;Yes&lt;/strong&gt;, if you are connected to the global network called Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answer 2: &lt;strong&gt;No&lt;/strong&gt;, if you are trying to access …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;1. Do I have a (web)site / blog?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, I do. You are reading it and also I have some other blogs too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. Can you access it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answer 1: &lt;strong&gt;Yes&lt;/strong&gt;, if you are connected to the global network called Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answer 2: &lt;strong&gt;No&lt;/strong&gt;, if you are trying to access from Free Basics by Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. Why is my blog / site not accessible through Free Basics?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becuase to make my site / blog accessible through Free Basics, I need to register my site URL to them (Facebook).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. Why did I not add my URL to Facebook? Is it a paid service?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, it's not a paid service. Even though it's free to register my URL, I am not going to add there. &lt;strong&gt;Why should I add my site to them, when my URL is already on the Internet? There is only one Internet. Free Basics !== Internet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook is trying to take over the control of the global network in their hands and establish their empire in it. This is nothing short of Monopoly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Internet is always Free (Free as in Freedom) and Facebook is trying to put a chain on those free hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand the context better, there are two ways of Censoring in Internet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blacklisting - list of sites not to allow (blocked sites).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whitelisting - list of allowed sites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Free Basics is a WHITELIST CENSORSHIP&lt;/strong&gt; which divides / breaks the Internet into fragments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5. What do we need to do now?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revolt against Freebasics&lt;/strong&gt;! If you have a (WEB)site or blog take a Stand. Do not add your Website / Web-blog / Web Application / Web Service to Free Basics List.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Let us Stand for Internet Freedom.&lt;/h3&gt;</content><category term="Internet"></category><category term="networks"></category><category term="censorship"></category></entry><entry><title>Students Practice Free Software. Yet, They Do Not Know</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/looking-for-free-software-yet.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-11-25T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2015-11-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2015-11-25:/blog/looking-for-free-software-yet.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I started writing this post soon after I came out of the computer lab completing my lab internal exam. We are given 10 exercise to complete during our semseter lab sessions out of which a random of 2 exercise are given for this internal exam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title of these 10 …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I started writing this post soon after I came out of the computer lab completing my lab internal exam. We are given 10 exercise to complete during our semseter lab sessions out of which a random of 2 exercise are given for this internal exam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title of these 10 exercises are given to us from our seniors and they also shared their code to us through email. Most of these code are downloaded from the Internet &amp;amp; are written in Java.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am someone who hates the verboseness of Java. Anyway I attempted to compile and execute those codes to see what output does the code produce. There were bugs, typos in the code. I debugged &amp;amp; compiled them successfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While discussing with my class peers, they said me they were not able to compile successfully for same reasons. Then I shared them the revised code with bugs and typos fixed. They used it to compile and got the lab record completed. I had the same experience during my under-graduate course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless I implemented some of the programs in python for my convinience and also gave the same for those who were looking for much simpler and non-verbose code. Another friend of mine in my class named &lt;code&gt;Dipankar&lt;/code&gt; also tried implementing the algorithms in the languages that he preferred. We both shared our code to our peers and asked them to pick the one they feel better (No, we both were not in a competition. Instead we co-operated with each other).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think, this is nothing short of the Free Software practice except the fact that the code are not licensed and might fall under public domain. The majority of student community today, when given a lab programming exercise to complete, searches for existing code online to reuse and to study the code. They are using it for their own purpose and some even modify the program to fit their requirements. Now this new version of code will be shared with the next batch of students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/"&gt;Free Software says&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the reciever, of the program code, can run the program for any purpose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the reciever, of the program code, can study the program to know how it works.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the receiver, of the program code, can redistribute the copies of the code to anyone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the receiver, of the program code, can improve / modify the code and share it with anyone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above practice by the student community is in par with what Free Software says. Yet, the student community is unaware of this philosophy and are failing to utilise it to study and improve. They fail to understand that this is the only potential source of knowledge for them. This free flow of knowledge is a gift for them by their predecessors. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of rewriting everything from scratch they can reuse them. When they attempt to study the code while reusing them, they can improve them. During this process they might get different ideas that could take their thinking (or) understanding to a new level which might even kindle them, to pursue researches (or) question the current practice of proprietary software development. By this they can set an example for their successors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope the student community will think about it and take this philosophy seriously for the betterment of it's own existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After having some discussion with my peers who are inspired by Free Software, we decided to setup a git repository of these codes and add Free Software Licenses to them and share it with everyone (I will update the post, when the git repository is ready).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="free software"></category><category term="education"></category></entry><entry><title>புத்தக வாசிப்பு</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/book-reading.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-10-25T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2015-10-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2015-10-25:/blog/book-reading.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;மூன்று வருடங்களுக்கு முன்னால் என்னுடைய வாழ்க்கை என்பது இன்றைய பெரும்பாலான இளைஞர்களின் வாழ்க்கையாகவே இருந்தது. கையில் ஒன்றும …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;மூன்று வருடங்களுக்கு முன்னால் என்னுடைய வாழ்க்கை என்பது இன்றைய பெரும்பாலான இளைஞர்களின் வாழ்க்கையாகவே இருந்தது. கையில் ஒன்றும், காதில் இரண்டும், மேஜையில் ஒன்றுமாய் ஸ்மார்ட்ஃபோன், மடிக்கணினி என்று அதிலேயே மூழ்கிக் கிடந்தேன். நான் சுயமாகச் சிந்தித்து ஏற்றுக் கொண்ட கருத்து என்று எப்போதுமே இருந்ததில்லை. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;காரணம், சமூக வலைதளங்களில் முகம் தெரியாத, தெரிந்த நபர்கள் என்ன பகிர்கிறார்களோ அதுவே பெரும்பான்மை கருத்தாக மாறி மாறிப் பலரைப் போல் என் மூளைக்குள்ளும் புகுந்துவிடும். அதை என் நட்பு வட்டங்களுக்கும் பகிர்ந்துவிடுவேன். அதைப் பற்றி ஒன்றுமே தெரியவில்லை என்றாலும் (அது உண்மையா பொய்யா என்று தெரியாமலும்) படித்த நேரத்தில் பிடித்திருப்பது போல் தோன்றினால் பகிர்ந்துவிடுவேன்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ஒருவர் ஒரு கருத்தைச் சரி என்பார், மற்றொருவர் தவறென்பார். சரி என்று சொன்னவரின் கருத்தைப் படித்தால் சரியாகத்தானே இருக்கிறது என்றும், தவறென்று சொல்பவரின் கருத்தைப் படித்தால் முன்னவர் சொன்னது தவறு என்பது போல் தோன்றும். யார் சொல்வது சரி, யார் சொல்வது தவறு என்று பகுப்பாய்வு செய்யும் திறனைச் சமூக வலைதளங்கள் வளர்க்கவில்லை. மாறாகத் தொடர்ந்து அடுத்தடுத்த கருத்துக்களையும், செய்திகளையும் நம் கண்முன்னே ஓடவிட்டுக் கொண்டே இருக்கும். &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;தன்னை சுற்றி நடக்கும் எந்த ஒரு விஷயத்தையும் 140 எழுத்துக்களில் சுருக்கிட விரும்புகிறான் (&lt;code&gt;திருக்குறள் 2 அடிதான் ஆனால் அதன் அர்த்தம் எவ்வுளவு பெரியது என்று நீங்கள் நினைக்கலாம். உண்மைதான். அதன் பெரிய அர்த்தத்தை நாம் புரிந்துக்கொண்டால் தானே அந்தச் சிறிய 2 அடியின் முக்கியத்துவம் நமக்குத் தெரியும்!&lt;/code&gt;).  இதன் விளைவு, ஒரு குழப்பமான மனிதன் உருவாக்கப்படுகிறான், யாரையும், எதன் மீதும் ஒரு நம்பிக்கை இல்லாமல் போகிறான். &lt;a href="https://ipfs.io/ipfs/QmWhpJ9Ptdsgapzh4gwiDnb5bN8mFDrtJ6TjTVgdZ64TSF"&gt;கேள்விகளை கேட்காமல் தகவல்களை கடந்து செல்லும் தகவல் நுகர்வு வெறி கலாச்சாரத்திற்கு அடிமையாகிறான்&lt;/a&gt;. சமூக வலைதளங்கள்மூலம் 1000 நண்பர்களோடு சோஷியலைஸ் (Socialize), அதாவது சமூகத்துடன் தொடர்பு வைத்திருப்பதாக ஒரு மாயையில் சிக்கி, தன்னைச் சுற்றியுள்ள உண்மையான சமூகத்திலிருந்து அறுத்தெரியப்படுகிறான்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;தன்னைச் சுற்றி வறுமையும், வேலைவாய்பின்மையும், சாதி, மதம் பெயரால் சமூக அநீதிகளும், சுரண்டல்களும், பாலின சமத்துவமின்மை, கடும் விலைவாசி உயர்வு என்று பல்வேறு அநீதிகள் நடந்துக் கொண்டிருக்கையில், &lt;code&gt;மதம் ஒரு அபின் (போதை) போன்றது&lt;/code&gt; என்று தத்துவஞாநி &lt;a href="https://ta.wikipedia.org/wiki/காரல்_மார்க்சு"&gt;கார்ல் மார்க்ஸ்&lt;/a&gt; அன்று சொன்னது போல இளைஞர்கள் மத்தியில் சமூக வலைத்தளங்கள் இன்றைய அபினாக மாறியிருக்கிறதோ என்று தோன்றுகிறது! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;இது போதாதென்று கமெர்ஷியல் சினிமா, ரியாலிட்டி ஷோ என்று தொலைக்காட்சிகளும் அதன் பங்கிற்கு மக்களை மிகவேகமாகத் திசைத்திருப்புகிறது. &lt;strong&gt;விளைவு?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code&gt;சிந்தனை என்பது மேலிருந்து கீழே மக்கள் மனதில் விதைக்கப்படுகிறது. எளிமையாகச் சொல்லவேண்டுமானால் நாம் அனைவரும் பொம்மாலாட்டத்தில் ஆடும் பொம்மைகள் ஆகிறோம்.&lt;/code&gt; சரி யார் மேலிருந்து மக்கள் மனதில் இவற்றை விதைக்கிறார்கள்? இது போன்ற கேள்விகளைக் கேட்காமல் இருப்பதற்காகத்தானே இவ்வுளவு திசைத் திருப்பலும்.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;நானும் இவற்றிற்கான பதிலைத்தான் தேடிக் கொண்டிருக்கிறேன். முயற்சியில் முன்னேற்றமும் அடைந்திருக்கிறேன். காரணம், புத்தக வாசிப்பு. புத்தக வாசிப்பு என்றதும் குங்குமம், குமுதம், ஆனந்த விடகன் என்று நினைத்துவிட வேண்டாம். வேண்டுமானால் பொழுது போக்க இப்புத்தகங்களைப் படிக்கலாம். ஆனால் சமூகத்தின் மீதும், என்னச் சுற்றி நடக்கும் காரியங்கள் ஏன் நடக்கிறது, யாரால் நடத்தப்படுகிறது, எப்படி நடக்கிறது என்ற காரண காரணிகளைப் புரிந்துக் கொள்ள உதவியது புத்தகங்கள் தான். &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;முதலில் நாம் வாழும் சமூகத்தைப் புரிந்துக் கொண்டால் தான் நாம் அடுத்த செயல்களைத் திட்டமிட முடியும். அப்படி புரியாத காரணத்தால் தான், உதாரணத்திற்கு, வேலை கிடைக்கவில்லை என்றால் தனக்கு மட்டும் இந்த உலகம் இருண்டுவிட்டது போல் உணர்வதும், எதிர்காலத்தை நினைத்து ஒருவித கலக்கமும் பயமும் பற்றிக் கொள்கிறது. காரணம் தெரிந்துவிட்டால் தீர்வுகளை நோக்கிய அடியைத் தைரியமாக வைக்கலாம் அல்லவா! உலகின் வேறொரு பகுதியில் நடக்கும் ஒரு காரியத்திற்கும், நம் ஊரில் நடக்கும் ஒரு காரியத்திற்கும் தொடர்பில்லாதது போன்றும், அதனால் நமக்கு எந்தப் பாதிப்பும் இல்லை என்பது போன்றும் தோன்றலாம், ஆனால் எதார்த்தம் வேறு, நாம் ஒரு சங்கிலித் தொடராகச் செயல்பட்டுக் கொண்டிருக்கிறோம் என்பதே உண்மை. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;உதாரணத்திற்கு,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;சவுதியில் கச்சா எண்ணெய் விலை குறைந்தாலோ ஏறினாலோ நம் ஊரிலும் அதற்கேற்றாற் போல் மாறுதல் நிகழ்கிறதே! ஏன்?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;இந்தியாவின் முதுகெலும்பே விவசாயம் தான் என்று பாடத்தில் படித்தாலும், விவசாயிகள் ஏன் அதிக அளவில் தற்கொலை செய்துக் கொள்கிறார்கள் அல்லது நிலங்களை ரியல் எஸ்டேட் காரர்களிடம் விற்று விடுகிறார்கள்?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;முதலில் நாம் எதிர் கேள்விகளைக் கேட்கும் மனிதர்களாக மாற வேண்டும். அவற்றிற்கான பதில்களைத் தேட வேண்டும். அந்தத் தேடுதலில் தான், மக்கள் அனைவரும் busy-ஆகிப் போன இந்தக் காலத்தில் புத்தகம் நம்மிடம் நிறைய பேசும். அதுவும் காலம் நேரம் பார்க்காமல் தொடர்ந்து பேசிக் கொண்டே இருக்கும். நான் வாசித்த, வாசித்துக் கொண்டிருக்கும் புத்தகங்களைப் பற்றி, எனக்குப் பல காரணங்களை விளங்க வைத்த புத்தகங்களைப் பற்றியும் அதே நேரத்தில் எனக்குப் புத்தகம் வாசிக்கும் பழக்கதை கற்றுக் கொடுத்த தோழர்களைப் பற்றியும் எழுதி உங்களோடு பகிர்வது என்று முடிவு செய்துள்ளேன்.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="books"></category></entry><entry><title>Uncensored - Circumventing Censorship</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/uncensored.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-10-12T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2015-10-12T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2015-10-12:/blog/uncensored.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's been 2 months since I have enrolled myself for the post graduate course in Networks &amp;amp; Internet Engineering (NIE) at Pondicherry University. The campus is a beautiful place to be and has rich bio-diversity preserved inside. It is also a Wi-Fi enabled campus scaling to various schools from engineering to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's been 2 months since I have enrolled myself for the post graduate course in Networks &amp;amp; Internet Engineering (NIE) at Pondicherry University. The campus is a beautiful place to be and has rich bio-diversity preserved inside. It is also a Wi-Fi enabled campus scaling to various schools from engineering to management, Life Sciences to Performing Arts, Social Sciences to Medical Sciences, etc.,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I belong to Department of Computer Science which comes under School of Engineering &amp;amp; Technology and the funny part is our department receives very poor Wi-Fi signal at class rooms, sometimes not even that. As a student of NIE, I feel the classroom is powerless without even access to wireless networks (at times, we do form ad-hoc networks).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Problem (Status Quo)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, let's focus on the censorship part from here on. Even if one can get a strong wi-fi signal or access to the wired network, not all the websites over the internet are accessible through the network. Social networks like Facebook, Video streaming platforms like Youtube, etc., are blocked in a temporal manner (i.e these sites cannot be accessed during class hours). The problem here is, not everyone have uniform class hours. So if one set of people are inside classrooms, some other set of people at some other department will be idle and they won't be able to access websites that are blocked. These rules are applicable even on weekends when the university is not functioning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also other issues like,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;torrent downloads are blocked.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;downloading files more than a specific size are blocked (for eg, when the free software users group were preparing to organize a GNU/Linux installation fest inside the campus and we wanted to download the latest / stable iso images of distributions like Ubuntu, Fedora, Trisquel, Mint, etc., we were not allowed to download since the file size were large).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a GNU/Linux user could not use the package management tools like &lt;strong&gt;apt-get&lt;/strong&gt; (or) &lt;strong&gt;dnf&lt;/strong&gt; to update or download tools from the distributions repository which is really irritating, since this is the most preferred way of installing a package (or) software in gnu/linux distributions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Solution (Moving Forward)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With technology, there are always ways to circumvent blockades. I would like to remind you incidents like &lt;a href="http://mashable.com/2011/01/27/bypass-twitter-facebook-block-egypt/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.wired.com/2014/10/firechat-hong-kong-usage/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. Using web proxy seems to be a easy option for most of them to access sites that are blocked. But proxy sites will soon hit it's limitations, in our scenario described above, using web proxy one cannot download large files, web proxy sites has no connection with respect to torrent downloads &amp;amp; solving apt-get or package download problem. Also if certain sites are blocked in the country that the web proxy site is located, then that would be the dead end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our university uses a proxy server that sits in between the local networks (i.e the campus network) and the rest of the Internet and this proxy server is powered by a software named &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.squid-cache.org/"&gt;squid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; which is a &lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html"&gt;free software&lt;/a&gt;. Every request made from a computer connected to a university network will have to pass or go through the proxy server. The proxy server would inspect the packets header and match it against with the rules written to allow / drop the packets by the network administrator. They could write complex rules combining multiple parameters like the url pattern, response size &amp;amp; type, etc.,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like everyone else in the campus, I was also confronted with these problems, so I decided to share what works for me, so that you people could use it to circumvent it, especially gnu/linux users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have seen most of the people inside the campus are using an application in their android phones called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://psiphon.ca/"&gt;Psiphon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; which also is a free software. But Psiphon is limited to only Android and Windows currently and so other platforms are left out especially gnu/linux users. Since Psiphon is free software, we can attempt to build our own client for the platforms that are left out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://torproject.org"&gt;Tor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; network to bypass the censorship. Tor is a &lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html"&gt;free software&lt;/a&gt; project aimed to provide anonymity for users, journalists, activists, etc., around the world and also used to bypass the censorship. This &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JWII85UlzKw"&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; will better explain the idea behind tor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Psiphon and Tor's objective are completely different. Psiphon's objective is to &lt;code&gt;bypass censorhip&lt;/code&gt; while Tor's objective is to provide &lt;code&gt;anonymity&lt;/code&gt; and the fact that tor can also bypass censorship is just a &lt;strong&gt;side-effect of it's network architecture&lt;/strong&gt;. So with tor one can stay anonymous while circumventing censorship too. Moreover Tor is cross-platform. It has clients for GNU/Linux, Windows, Mac &amp;amp; Android. Tor also has got a &lt;code&gt;Tor browser&lt;/code&gt; for desktops which is a fork of Firefox browser and tweaked to be compatible for Tor and released.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am using Fedora 22 in my laptop and I have installed Tor daemon and have configured my existing firefox browers to use socks proxy. To install Tor in gnu/linux distributions we need access to uncensored internet at the first place, since apt-get (or) dnf yum won't be able to download through the censored network here. So if you visit your friends house with Internet access (or) if you have other means of connecting to internet like mobile data, you can use that to install tor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instructions to,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;install Tor in &lt;a href="https://www.torproject.org/docs/rpms.html.en"&gt;Fedora / CentOS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;install Tor in &lt;a href="https://www.torproject.org/docs/debian.html.en"&gt;Debian / Ubuntu / LinuxMint&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have installed tor successfully, also install another tool named &lt;code&gt;proxychains&lt;/code&gt; (usage is explained below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instructions to install proxychains,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fedora:&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sudo dnf -C install proxychains&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;debian / ubuntu / mint:&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sudo apt-get install proxychains&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow these instructions to set it up and start tor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;search for &lt;code&gt;terminal&lt;/code&gt; in applications and open it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if your network is behind a proxy server, we need to enter the proxy location in torrc file. In our university we are sitting behind a squid proxy server and the location is &lt;code&gt;http://10.10.80.11:3128&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;https://10.10.80.11:3128&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;copy both (http and https) url and enter the following in terminal which will open the torrc file in nano text editor&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sudo nano /etc/tor/torrc&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;scroll down to the end of the file and type the following&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HTTPProxy 10.10.80.11:3128&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HTTPSProxy 10.10.80.11:3128&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;press &lt;code&gt;ctrl+x&lt;/code&gt; then &lt;code&gt;Y&lt;/code&gt; and press &lt;code&gt;Enter&lt;/code&gt; to save and quit. The edited file should look like the image below&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://ipfs.io/ipfs/QmYdULp2HnNir4d9EUnr2pcQYLAiinZEdRKN4VTDn3RLJe"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have successfully configured &lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt; to use the network proxy, let's start using tor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt; will be started automatically in the background for ubuntu / debian / mint. Let's stop it first through terminal.&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sudo service tor stop&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now let's start the &lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt; again. This is a common step for both fedora and debian based distributions.&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tor&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should be seeing some outputs in number of lines like Bootstrapped 0% (refer the image below). When tor reaches &lt;code&gt;Bootstrapped 100%: done&lt;/code&gt; it means our computer can now participate in the tor network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt; is pre-configured to run on port 9050 in your computer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://ipfs.io/ipfs/QmcJf5qhgDf9DMHU7N4qhJ5vYPyxum6AHKc5YWyiDrcqsD"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: The reason why stopped and started tor is that, by default tor will be running in the background if started automatically, when we invoke &lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt; via command line manually, we will be able to see the logs and can check if tor is successfully establishing the connection or struck somewhere so that we can try to debug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just leave the terminal open with tor running and let's open &lt;code&gt;firefox&lt;/code&gt; browser to use tor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in firefox, go to &lt;code&gt;Edit&lt;/code&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;preferences&lt;/code&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;Advanced&lt;/code&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;Network&lt;/code&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;Settings&lt;/code&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;Manual Proxy configuration&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;find &lt;code&gt;SOCKS Host&lt;/code&gt; and enter &lt;code&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt; in the first field and &lt;code&gt;9050&lt;/code&gt; in the port field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;click on &lt;code&gt;ok&lt;/code&gt; and now you should be able to visit websites that are blocked previously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website censorship is solved, now let's focus on package manager. Remember we installed &lt;code&gt;proxychains&lt;/code&gt;? This is where we will make use of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open &lt;code&gt;/etc/proxychains.conf&lt;/code&gt; file using &lt;code&gt;nano&lt;/code&gt; editor like how we opened the &lt;code&gt;/etc/tor/torrc&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;scroll down to the end of the file and you could find &lt;code&gt;#socks4 127.0.0.1 9050&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if there is a &lt;code&gt;#&lt;/code&gt; like above, just delete that character alone, save and quit the editor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt; running in the background, now if we invoke any program from the &lt;code&gt;terminal&lt;/code&gt; using &lt;code&gt;proxychains&lt;/code&gt; we can make that program to redirect the traffic through &lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt;. For example,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sudo proxychains apt-get install uget&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;will install uget download manager and install it in your debian based machines. I hope you got the key point here. If you want to redirect any application to use tor, you will have to set &lt;code&gt;SOCKS proxy&lt;/code&gt; for the application. the proxy address would be &lt;code&gt;localhost:9050&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;127.0.0.1:3128&lt;/code&gt; where &lt;code&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;127.0.0.1&lt;/code&gt; is the address and &lt;code&gt;3128&lt;/code&gt; is the port number. For applications which doesn't support SOCKS proxy yet, you can use &lt;code&gt;proxychains&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also you can use &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://ugetdm.com/"&gt;uGet Download Manager&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to download files (uget has support for SOCKS proxy, so remember to start tor and set socks 4 proxy in uget preferences before starting your download).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above chain of solutions solves the following problems that I already mentoned above:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bypassing website censorship.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;downloading and installing software (or) package management in gnu/linux distributions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;downloading large files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only problem that relies unanswered is &lt;code&gt;torrent downloads&lt;/code&gt;. Using &lt;code&gt;torrent&lt;/code&gt; downloads via &lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt; traffic is a &lt;a href="https://blog.torproject.org/blog/bittorrent-over-tor-isnt-good-idea"&gt;bad idea&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Endnote&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the State exists there can be no freedom; when there is freedom there will be no State - V.I. Lenin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right from the beginning we have been encountering names of software like &lt;code&gt;squid&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;psiphon&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;proxychains&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;uget&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;fedora&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;debian&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;ubuntu&lt;/code&gt;, etc., all of them are &lt;strong&gt;Free Software&lt;/strong&gt;. Amidst the fact that &lt;code&gt;free software&lt;/code&gt; stresses the freedom of user, it doesn't completely libreate or free the masses from oppression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we are seeing two classes of people, one is the &lt;code&gt;oppressing&lt;/code&gt; class and the other is the &lt;code&gt;oppressed&lt;/code&gt; class both are using Free Software for their purposes. In our case &lt;code&gt;squid&lt;/code&gt;, a free softwrae is used to enforce censorship and &lt;code&gt;psiphon&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;tor&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;proxychains&lt;/code&gt;, etc., which are free softwrae too, are used to fight back. But not everyone are liberated. &lt;code&gt;You and I&lt;/code&gt; can be exceptions, but exceptions cannot become mainstream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Science &amp;amp; Technology&lt;/strong&gt; can be used as tools and catalyst while fighting for freedom, but they alone cannot bring about freedom or revolution. We also need to be &lt;strong&gt;politically aware&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="tor"></category><category term="tech"></category><category term="free software"></category><category term="proxy"></category><category term="internet"></category><category term="web"></category><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Hello World</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/hello-world.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-10-11T23:55:00+05:30</published><updated>2015-10-11T23:55:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2015-10-11:/blog/hello-world.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello World! Welcome to my blog. I previously owned a domain named "impras.in" and had written my own &lt;a href="https://github.com/PrasannaVenkadesh/blogster"&gt;blog engine&lt;/a&gt; powered by python. Now I no longer own the domain due to financial constraints. Also I have been writing in places like Diaspora, Discourse, etc., But then I have …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello World! Welcome to my blog. I previously owned a domain named "impras.in" and had written my own &lt;a href="https://github.com/PrasannaVenkadesh/blogster"&gt;blog engine&lt;/a&gt; powered by python. Now I no longer own the domain due to financial constraints. Also I have been writing in places like Diaspora, Discourse, etc., But then I have stopped blogging even though I have wordpress blogs. Somehow I got bored writing with Wordpress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.getpelican.com/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to be interesting, also writing a blog in a text-editor like vim &amp;amp; using markdown syntax for content makes me excited. Typing down my thoughts without the need for in-browser editor and web connectivity keeps me away from distractions online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think Pelican + Git + Github-Pages is more convinient than traditional blogging platforms for multiple reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No worries about managing / maintaining Database (just markdown, html)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Absence of db means the data is distributed. Git is tracking and so the copy of files stays in my local hard disk as well as on github repository. So need not worry about data loss / disk corruption.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple markdown syntax helps in focusing on contents for blog post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can always move the site to other providers / host my own, if I at some point needed to abandon github (it's already a proprietary platform).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="pelican"></category></entry></feed>