<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Towards Freedom - Free Software</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/feeds/free-software.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/</id><updated>2018-06-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>On Microsoft Acquiring GitHub</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/microsoft-github-gitlab.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-09T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-06-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2018-06-09:/blog/microsoft-github-gitlab.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Richard Mathew Stallman (RMS) who is widely known as the founder of Free Software Foundation (FSF) and GNU is Not Unix (GNU) project, wrote an email [1] to GNU mailing list 3 years back, asking developers not to use GitHub for hosting their source code and instead asks them to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Richard Mathew Stallman (RMS) who is widely known as the founder of Free Software Foundation (FSF) and GNU is Not Unix (GNU) project, wrote an email [1] to GNU mailing list 3 years back, asking developers not to use GitHub for hosting their source code and instead asks them to find a better alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why did he say that? Because, is he some kind of prophet who knows that Microsoft will acquire a platform like GitHub in the future? No! The primary contradiction in this case is that, Github which started as a platform to help developers of Free/Libre &amp;amp; Open Source Projects itself is neither a Free Software nor Open Source Software!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they started attracting various FOSS communities including Mozilla, The Linux Kernel (maintains their mirror there), etc., All of the sudden, it become a place for developers to figure out FOSS projects, start contributing and host their own. I remember reading an article on CNET titled, "Forget LinkedIn, Companies turn to Github to find Tech Talent"[2] back in 2012. A developers profile on GitHub along with their contributions towards public projects was valued (and still being) more than the information that they have provided in their Resume when they applied to software development jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even a company like Google, who had their own code hosting platform [3], had shutdown it's service and moved some of their projects to GitHub as well. There was even a popular trend among developers who understood that FOSS is empowering their skills and knowledge started ignoring tools or services which are proprietary and comes from organizations that promote proprietary software rather than a FLOSS. This in-turn created another trend among the companies who started publishing some of their projects source code under a FLOSS license and wanted to stay alive among developers. It's a strategic move by these companies based on market conditions and not based on the principles or philosophy behind FLOSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It includes Microsoft as well! Back in the early 2000-2001 Microsoft's Steve Ballmer called GNU/Linux and the Free Software ecosystem as Cancer and even attributed the nature of GNU GPL to Communism! [4]. And 12 years later, they ridiculed themselves being one of the Top 20 contributors to the Linux kernel itself! [5] The market trends started changing in those decades. The Internet, Web and FLOSS had grown together. It was evident that the connectivity the Internet and Web provided had brought developers together crossing national boundaries and changed the way they develop and produce software. From that point, software production was in a sense democratized that they are no longer constrained within the walls of tech corporations but was out in the open. Soon after this another trend started emerging in the name of Cloud Computing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to keep pace with the fast changing domain, Microsoft and similar companies had to restrain from their previous stands. The market forces compelled them for a change. Soon after Satya Nadella was made CEO of Microsoft he made announcements like "Microsoft Loves Linux". This announcement again comes in the background of Microsoft's launching of it's own cloud platform called Azure where GNU/Linux was the primary operating system demanded by developers who operate in the cloud. Steve Ballmer, once again came out and said "I may have called Linux a cancer but now I love it" as quoted in ZDNET[6].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the sudden Microsoft started embracing Open Source (not Free Software) not because of the principles again, but because of the demand by capital and market conditions for profit and for their survival. Today, Microsoft has announced that they are acquiring the proprietary source code hosting and development platform GitHub and more than surpise, it had come as shock to a lot of developer communities. The developers seems to be disappointed and worried about this move and it was evident by the trended hashtag #movingtogitlab on Twitter [7] and Fediverse [8]. Gitlab is an FLOSS alternative to GitHub and developers started migrating to it as reported by GitLab [9].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were also creative memes that was trending [10]. It was also mentioned that GitHub has been valued at $7.5 billion in this acquisition and GitHub said they are happy about it. "They" here refers to the board members, venture capitalists and angel investors. They are happy about it while the developer community is raging aginst this move. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should be raising few questions on this moment. What would attract another company to acquire another companies product, if not for the value they see in? If it has a value, who and what had created that value? Is it just the developers and marketting folks at GitHub (or) is that the whole developer community who have their accounts and actively developing software in GitHub? Would a company buy a product of another company at higher price if there were no active users? If both the developers who built the platform and the users (in this case are also developers who uses the platform) are those who brought such value for this product, then it is certainly beaurocratic and undemocratic that their consents have never been sought and when it happens, the other side rages and starts their counter action. Moving to Gitlab is a political stance by the developer community. It is their way of resisting back. The developer community should have listened to the early warnings of RMS and shouldn’t have chosen a proprietary platform for development and hosting of FLOSS projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the past records and u-turns of Microsoft why would the community trust them, no matter how much they come in disguise? The Free Software movement is a bottom-up movement with the principles of Freedom at it's core, while the changes happening in these top tech companies are top-down and they both clash with each other. Because the top-down management can any time will make another u-turn if the capital profit and the market conditions demands them to do so. Therefore they cannot be trusted and the alternative lies on building a decentralized &amp;amp; federated solutions to these centralized platforms. The hacker and developer community needs to stay vigilant about the moves of these monopolies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from GitLab, Gogs, Gitea, GitTorrent and git-ssb are other examples for alternatives. Seek alternatives, if there is none, build many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://lists.gnu.org/archive/html/discuss-gnustep/2015-12/msg00168.html&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://www.cnet.com/news/forget-linkedin-companies-turn-to-github-to-find-tech-talent/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://opensource.googleblog.com/2015/03/farewell-to-google-code.html&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://www.theregister.co.uk/2000/07/31/ms_ballmer_linux_is_communism/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://www.theregister.co.uk/2012/04/03/microsoft_linux_kernel_contributions/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://www.zdnet.com/article/ballmer-i-may-have-called-linux-a-cancer-but-now-i-love-it/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://twitter.com/hashtag/movingtogitlab&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://mastodon.social/tags/movingtogitlab&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://about.gitlab.com/2018/06/03/movingtogitlab/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://twitter.com/cdrrazan/status/1003419271563628544&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Free Software"></category><category term="blog"></category><category term="proprietary"></category><category term="microsoft"></category><category term="gitlab"></category></entry><entry><title>What Did I Learn From Free Software Movement?</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/learnings-from-fsm.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-21T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-06-21T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2017-06-21:/blog/learnings-from-fsm.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back in 2010-2011, when I was a under-graduate student of computer science, I got introduced to GNU/Linux operating system and then gradually got introduced to the free software movement through &lt;a href="https://fsftn.org"&gt;FSFTN&lt;/a&gt;. Since then, I have been active with the free software movement by doing activism (i.e asking people …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back in 2010-2011, when I was a under-graduate student of computer science, I got introduced to GNU/Linux operating system and then gradually got introduced to the free software movement through &lt;a href="https://fsftn.org"&gt;FSFTN&lt;/a&gt;. Since then, I have been active with the free software movement by doing activism (i.e asking people and helping them to switch to free software by explaining the values underlying it), &lt;a href="https://code.purambokku.me/prashere"&gt;releasing all the code and utility scripts&lt;/a&gt;, that I create, under a free software license.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So with all these activities, I have learned &lt;strong&gt;certain values&lt;/strong&gt; from the free software movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be Inclusive&lt;/strong&gt; - make sure everyone has option to take part in production as well as consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A software is free software, if it's license allows anyone to use, study, modify, distribute or redistribute the code to anyone for any purpose. It invites everyone to use and it doesn't stop there, it even invites them to study and modify the code based on their needs and promotes them to share their modification to others as well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's say we buy a bike. A bike is useless without fuel for it's engine, therefore we need fuel to run bikes. Fuel production is a separate industry on a large scale by itself. We cannot produce fuel with bike, we can only consume or use fuel with bike. If we substitute bike for a computer here, then a computer hardware is also useless without a software. If software is the fuel for computer hardware, then software is both produced and used in computers. The means used to produce and use are the same. This invites a new question, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Why can't a user with a knowledge or a user with a friend who has knowledge on how to study and modify the software is unable to do so for their own computer?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is, we are able to do, but the proprietary software distributors have written their license that doesn't allow users to do so, instead puts a chain of dependency around the neck of the users.
&lt;img alt="" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/65/Roman_collared_slaves_-_Ashmolean_Museum.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By separating software production and software usage it has built an exclusive system. Free Software is trying to liberate users by breaking these chains and invites everyone to produce as well. It is designed to be inclusive. It doesn't restrict people from a particular race or gender or religion or caste or color or whatever from contributing to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collective progress &amp;gt; Individual Progress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is pretty straight-forward. In a group of people, if only one of them gets access to a resource, then all others have to depend on that one individual. Now that individual, based on their morals and values, may or may not exploit the others for their own profit. In case of collective progress, everyone gets access to the resource and everyone collectively frames a guideline on how to utilize and manage a resource. This is how any free software project is developed, initially a community is formed around it and based on their contribution and suggestions bugs are fixed, new features are added and this in turn used by everyone benefits everyone. Mailing lists, forums, irc channels, bug trackers, pull requests, this is how the community self-organizes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When contribution is to the collective, the resource should be managed as a commons&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drawing from the first two values of inclusiveness and collective progress, the outcome of such production cannot become a private property. The non-permissive free software licenses like GNU GPL, AGPL, etc., provides legal protection to the software produced in this manner from being appropriated or enclosed by private ownership. Similarly creative commons and PPL are doing the same for digital artistic creations like Music, Articles (wikipedia), Pictures, Videos, Audio, etc., This is why, I see permissive licenses as counter-forces which takes us back to the old system at the same time appropriating all the values created by the commoners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commons &amp;gt; Private Property&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commons as a social product promotes collaboration whereas private property promotes egoism and individual greed and thus exploitation. Private property pitches one individual against the other. This competition becomes more intensive and barbaric as the population grows. In this case, if people didn't bring resources under commons, then this inevitably leads to exploitation of one another. i.e one's cost of living depends on one's cost of suffering under private property regime. This is already true with wealth inequality &amp;amp; income inequality. It is this private property (specifically, Intellectual Property rights) that free software is questioning and proposes commons based organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Innovations doesn't rely on monetary benefits&lt;/strong&gt;, rather innovations are driven by necessity to overcome certain limitations. For example, when centralized infrastructure of a website or a webservice is prone to single point of failure or power abuse like fb or twitter, people come up with interesting solutions like &lt;strong&gt;decentralized&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;p2p alternatives&lt;/strong&gt; like torrents, &lt;a href="join-scuttleverse.html"&gt;ssb-patchwork&lt;/a&gt;, GNU social, diaspora, OStatus, Rumble, which are all free software or open protocols. It may or may not be later appropriated by private property regime like how skype was once p2p and then back to centralization again. For democratic control &amp;amp; ownership, distributed software run by different collectives is the way forward. And in order for the software to be run by different collectives, it has to be in commons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;privacy&lt;/strong&gt; for everyone cannot be guranteed by private property, instead it can only be guarenteed by being inclusive. When we have private property regime, we have competition among eveyrone to acquire the property for exclusive access, this automatically brings an insecure feeling about the future. What if someone steals or damages my property? Therefore, property owners promotes surveillance. In case of softwares, there is no way to make sure that a proprietary software spy or doesn't spy on you, because users have no access to the source code. It is a blind trust. With free software, access to the source code reveals any such malware practices and since free software also allows modification, anyone can get rid of such practices and can ensure security and privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now all these values of software production comes into conflict with the existing model. It is bascially a transition towards a commons oriented production. But the existing system based on private property, especially the contemporary owners of private property will not allow this transition to pass through easily. They will engage in all sorts resistance for the sake of their own profit and privilige in this system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A change proposed in how production happens, also demands a change in economy. This is how production, economy, politics and society are all inter-related. We need to transition to &lt;a href="http://p2pfoundation.net/"&gt;commons based peer production&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for the sake of our species and our planet, especially when the current system is polluting everything.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Free Software"></category><category term="free software"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="tech"></category><category term="Internet"></category></entry><entry><title>Whispering Pictures - Beware</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/privacy-pictures.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-01T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-01-01T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2017-01-01:/blog/privacy-pictures.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the english version of the &lt;a href="https://fsftn.org/blog/pesum-pugaipadangal-gavanam/"&gt;tamil post&lt;/a&gt; that I wrote for &lt;a href="https://fsftn.org/blog"&gt;FSFTN's blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We come across a lot of new people throughout our life. There is a reason we call them strangers. Not everyone wins our trust and vice-versa. We don't reveal much about ourselves to those strangers …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the english version of the &lt;a href="https://fsftn.org/blog/pesum-pugaipadangal-gavanam/"&gt;tamil post&lt;/a&gt; that I wrote for &lt;a href="https://fsftn.org/blog"&gt;FSFTN's blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We come across a lot of new people throughout our life. There is a reason we call them strangers. Not everyone wins our trust and vice-versa. We don't reveal much about ourselves to those strangers. We try to be more cautious about what information we reveal to them. This is what we call our &lt;strong&gt;Privacy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Privacy is the ability of an individual or group to seclude themselves, or information about themselves, and thereby express themselves selectively. - &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privacy"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever we talk about privacy, many people tend to think it in terms of &lt;em&gt;secrecy&lt;/em&gt;. While secrecy is more about the information whereas privacy is more about the ability of one's control over that information. Though they both are different, they both go hand in hand with each other most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There goes a song in Tamil cinema which is quite popular,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's take a selfie pulla...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this selfie cultured digital world around us, the need to take privacy seriously arises naturally. Usage of smartphones, laptops and DSR/DSLR camera have become quite common these days. We also know that all these devices are controlled by the software that are already inside those devices. It can be the firmware (or) the operating system (or) the application itself. One such module of these software is called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exif"&gt;EXIF&lt;/a&gt; which stands for &lt;strong&gt;EX&lt;/strong&gt;changeable &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;mage file &lt;strong&gt;F&lt;/strong&gt;ormat. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EXIF defines a lot of properties like the size of the image, dimension, name and model of the device used, date and time of the picture taken, location where this picture was taken (if GPS is enabled and the application has the ability to get location from GPS), whether flash was fired or not when the picture was taken, etc., believe me, there are &lt;a href="http://exiv2.org/tags.html"&gt;a lot of such data&lt;/a&gt; that can be embeded along with that awesome selfie / photograph that we shoot everyday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We think, we are just taking pictures, but most of us aren't aware of the fact that all these so called &lt;em&gt;smart devices&lt;/em&gt; also collect and embed a lot of other sensitive information with our pictures. You don't have to even believe what I am saying. You can try it yourself with this page that I built for demonstrating the same &lt;a href="https://prashere.gitlab.io/exifdata/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the above demonstration, the more &lt;em&gt;undefined&lt;/em&gt; you see, the more happy you can be, because those informations are not present with your pictures. Here is one example that I tried myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image of a fan" src="https://fsftn.org/blog/content/images/2016/12/20161228_162446.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What information can you extract from the above image? Yes, you are right. It's a ceiling fan and the fan is functioning. What else can you know?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="screenshot of fan with exif metadata" src="https://fsftn.org/blog/content/images/2016/12/with_geolocation.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh crap! This photograph seems to reveal a lot than what we thought! The location of where this picture was taken, the deivce used, date and time, whether flash used or not is also visible. Using these information we can also know that the person who shoot this photograph was using this particular device and this fan and the person was at that particular location on that particular date and time! and yeah the flash did not fire ;) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now what happens when I upload this to social networks (umm, I'll be specific, yeah facbeook)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="screenshot of the same image uploaded to facebook" src="https://fsftn.org/blog/content/images/2016/12/facebook_exif.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at this. Facebook retrieves the location and date from these pictures. A lot of such services on the web are waiting for us upload our data and build a profile around us and then sell it to third-party agencies for their profit. Even if we remove (or) edit, there is no way for us to make sure that those informations are actually removed from fb's server. This is how our privacy is compromised at a lot of stage. Remember, our intention was just to share a selfie or photograph that we just took, not any other information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine how much selfies and photograph of our family and friends we shoot and share it in Web! Most liberal minded people would easily say, &lt;em&gt;hey! you are ignorant and it's your mistake that you are not aware of such things&lt;/em&gt;, well I would rather say &lt;em&gt;No. It's not our mistake&lt;/em&gt;, because the software is proprietary in most of the case, we do not even know what the software does in the background and there is no way to know what else the software does when the source code is not available. Moreover, you and I didn't ask for such a feature and also we don't have the freedom to modify the source code under a proprietary regime. That is why we as a movement (Free Software movement) call for the adoption and usagae of &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.en.html"&gt;Free(dom) Software&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the proprietary software controls the device, it means the creator of the proprietary software is in indirect control of your device. It also means your device is not in your control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what can we do about this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;re-configure your smartphone and other smart devices that has camera in it, so that they don't embed these information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;remove sensitive metadata from your pictures before uploading or sharing it with others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GNU/Linux users can install a tool named &lt;a href="http://mat.boum.org/"&gt;MAT - Metadata Anonymisation Toolkit&lt;/a&gt; which is also a &lt;em&gt;free software&lt;/em&gt;. This software cleans our image of any such harmful metadata.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don't find any such free software EXIF removers for Windows (may be because, I don't use windows and so I don't find a need to search for it).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are some EXIF editors and removers for Android at Play Store. (again they are proprietary and I don't recommend them, for they can be harmful too).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no such EXIF editors / removers for Android in F-droid. (as far as I have searched).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;don't use the &lt;strong&gt;take picture&lt;/strong&gt; option directly from the social network and instant messengers app on your smartphone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid using proprietary softwares and apps. free yourself by using a free software operating system like GNU/Linux.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not arguing against EXIF metadata, I am arguing for the case of user's privacy. The application and the ecosystem should be designed in such a way that a user has the control over their digital activity, for it is their data that this ecosystem is making use of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: By the end of January 2017 (26, 27, 28 &amp;amp; 29) the 2nd National Conference and Convention of Free Software Movement of India is set to happen at Chennai, Tamilnadu, India. This conference and convention will be discussion topics ranging from privacy, software freedom, commons, community networks, programming, etc., The confernce is named as &lt;a href="https://4ccon.fsmi.in"&gt;4CCon&lt;/a&gt;. Students, academicians, researchers, software experts, Internet activists, free software hacktivists, social activists are participating. You are also invited. Do visit the site and register yourself if you are interested.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Free Software"></category><category term="privacy"></category><category term="code"></category><category term="free software"></category><category term="tech"></category><category term="web"></category></entry><entry><title>Students Practice Free Software. Yet, They Do Not Know</title><link href="https://prasannavenkadesh.github.io/blog/looking-for-free-software-yet.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-11-25T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2015-11-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prasanna Venkadesh</name></author><id>tag:prasannavenkadesh.github.io,2015-11-25:/blog/looking-for-free-software-yet.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I started writing this post soon after I came out of the computer lab completing my lab internal exam. We are given 10 exercise to complete during our semseter lab sessions out of which a random of 2 exercise are given for this internal exam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title of these 10 …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I started writing this post soon after I came out of the computer lab completing my lab internal exam. We are given 10 exercise to complete during our semseter lab sessions out of which a random of 2 exercise are given for this internal exam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title of these 10 exercises are given to us from our seniors and they also shared their code to us through email. Most of these code are downloaded from the Internet &amp;amp; are written in Java.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am someone who hates the verboseness of Java. Anyway I attempted to compile and execute those codes to see what output does the code produce. There were bugs, typos in the code. I debugged &amp;amp; compiled them successfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While discussing with my class peers, they said me they were not able to compile successfully for same reasons. Then I shared them the revised code with bugs and typos fixed. They used it to compile and got the lab record completed. I had the same experience during my under-graduate course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless I implemented some of the programs in python for my convinience and also gave the same for those who were looking for much simpler and non-verbose code. Another friend of mine in my class named &lt;code&gt;Dipankar&lt;/code&gt; also tried implementing the algorithms in the languages that he preferred. We both shared our code to our peers and asked them to pick the one they feel better (No, we both were not in a competition. Instead we co-operated with each other).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think, this is nothing short of the Free Software practice except the fact that the code are not licensed and might fall under public domain. The majority of student community today, when given a lab programming exercise to complete, searches for existing code online to reuse and to study the code. They are using it for their own purpose and some even modify the program to fit their requirements. Now this new version of code will be shared with the next batch of students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/"&gt;Free Software says&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the reciever, of the program code, can run the program for any purpose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the reciever, of the program code, can study the program to know how it works.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the receiver, of the program code, can redistribute the copies of the code to anyone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the receiver, of the program code, can improve / modify the code and share it with anyone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above practice by the student community is in par with what Free Software says. Yet, the student community is unaware of this philosophy and are failing to utilise it to study and improve. They fail to understand that this is the only potential source of knowledge for them. This free flow of knowledge is a gift for them by their predecessors. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of rewriting everything from scratch they can reuse them. When they attempt to study the code while reusing them, they can improve them. During this process they might get different ideas that could take their thinking (or) understanding to a new level which might even kindle them, to pursue researches (or) question the current practice of proprietary software development. By this they can set an example for their successors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope the student community will think about it and take this philosophy seriously for the betterment of it's own existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After having some discussion with my peers who are inspired by Free Software, we decided to setup a git repository of these codes and add Free Software Licenses to them and share it with everyone (I will update the post, when the git repository is ready).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Free Software"></category><category term="free software"></category><category term="education"></category></entry></feed>